<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>12.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>cruciata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Wahlenberg</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Kongl. Vetensk. Acad. Nya Handl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>24: 149. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>十字薹草 shi zi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>bengalensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Roxburgh</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>cruciata</species_name>
    <subspecies_name>rubrobrunnea</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>(Ohwi) T. Koyama</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>cruciata</species_name>
    <variety_name>rubrobrunnea</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Ohwi</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>hakkuensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>valida</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nees.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick, woody, with stolons. Culms tufted, 40–90 × 0.3–0.5 cm, trigonous, smooth. Leaves basal and cauline, longer than culms, flat, 4–13 mm wide, scabrid abaxially, glabrous adaxially; persistent sheaths dark brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence branches, long sheathed. Panicle compound; inflorescence branches usually single, rarely binate, ovate-triangular, 4–15 × 3–6 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches rigid, bluntly trigonous, lowest one 10–18 cm, upper ones gradually shorter, smooth; inflorescence axes trigonous, hairy; bractlets glumelike, ca. 1.5 mm, hairy abaxially. Spikes numerous, bisexual, androgynous, arising from several veined, abaxially hairy cladoprophylls, patent horizontally, 5–12 mm; male part of spike nearly as long as female part; male glumes pale brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, lanceolate, ca. 2.5 mm, membranous, apex acuminate, mucronate; female glumes ovate, ca. 2 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex obtuse, shortly awned. Utricles pale brownish white with brown spots and short lines, longer than glumes, elliptic, trigonous, inflated, 3–3.2 mm, smooth or upper part loosely hairy, with several raised veins, subsessile, apex attenuate into beak of medium length, beak ca. 1/3 length of utricle, hairy or glabrous laterally, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets dark brown at maturity, ovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Forest margins, grasslands, roadsides; 300–2500 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan, Hubei, Jiangxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Xizang, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Bhutan, India, Indonesia, Japan, Nepal, Thailand, Vietnam; Madagascar].</distribution>
</treatment>

