<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>15.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>deciduisquama</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 160. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>落鳞薹草 luo lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, up to 1 m high, ca. 3 mm thick, trigonous, smooth. Leaves basal and cauline, flat, 5–7 mm wide, scabrid abaxially, glabrous adaxially; persistent sheaths dark brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, ± as long as or slightly shorter than inflorescence branches, long sheathed. Panicle compound, ca. 20 cm; inflorescence branches single, oblong, 4–7 × 2.5–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, trigonous, subsmooth, lowest one 12–14 cm; inflorescence axes trigonous, loosely hairy; bractlets glumelike, oblong, 2.5–3.5 mm, apex emarginate, with awns ca. 2 mm. Spikes numerous, bisexual, androgynous, arising from cladoprophylls, distant, slightly patent, cylindric, 1–2 cm, terminal one to 3 cm; male part of spike as long as female part, with over 10 flowers; female part with 2–10 slightly distant flowers; male glumes not deciduous at maturity, pale brown, oblong, 3.5–4.5 mm, with 1 midvein, apex emarginate with mucro; female glumes deciduous at maturity, pale brown, oblong, 3–4 mm, papery, 3-veined at middle, apex emarginate, with awns up to 2 mm. Utricles pale yellowish brown, narrowly elliptic, trigonous, slightly inflated, ca. 5 mm, papery, many veined, sessile, apex attenuate into long beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, narrowly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, sessile, apex mucronate; style base thickened and conic; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Woods; 2300–2500 m. NW Yunnan (Gongshan).</distribution>
</treatment>

