<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>16.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>stramentitia</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott ex Boeckeler</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>40: 351. 1876</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>草黄薹草 cao huang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long, obliquely elongate, woody. Culms tufted, 30–75 cm, bluntly trigonous, smooth. Leaves basal and cauline, nearly as long as culms, flat, 1–2 mm wide; persistent sheaths dark brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence branches, long sheathed. Panicle compound, 20–30 cm, 3–5-branched; inflorescence branches single, triangular-ovate, 5–7.5 × 4–5 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches rigid, trigonous, scabrid on edges; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, hairy; bractlets glumelike, with long awns. Spikes numerous, bisexual, androgynous, arising from cladoprophylls, dense, obliquely patent, oblong, 10–12 mm; male part of spike longer than female part, with over 10 flowers; female part with over 10 flowers; male glumes pale yellow, oblong-lanceolate, 3–4 mm, papery, apex obtuse and mucronate; female glumes stramineous when dried, slightly shining, ovate-oblong, 2.5–3 mm, papery, 3-veined, margins hyaline, apex obtuse or rounded with short awns. Utricles brownish green, longer than glumes, oblong or ovate-oblong, trigonous, slightly inflated, ca. 3.5 mm, many veined, subsessile, apex contracted into long beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets broadly ovate, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands by woods; 100–1000 m. Guangxi, Guizhou, Yunnan [Bhutan, India, Indonesia (Java), Myanmar, Nepal, Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

