<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>19.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>subfilicinoides</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Horti Gothob.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 42. 1930</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>近蕨薹草 jin jue tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with thick fibers. Culms tufted, 50–90 × 0.25–0.3 cm, trigonous, glabrous. Leaves basal and cauline, longer than culms, flat, 7–12 mm wide, glabrous or scabrid along veins abaxially, prominently scabrid adaxially; persistent sheaths purplish red, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence branches, long sheathed. Panicle compound, 20–50 cm, 4–9-branched; inflorescence branches distant, binate, rarely single, lanceolate, 3.5–9 × 1.5–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 10–20 cm, obtusely trigonous, upper part pubescent; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, loosely hairy; bractlets glumelike, ca. 1 mm, loosely hairy, awned. Spikes numerous, bisexual, androgynous, arising from cladoprophylls, ovate or oblong, 5–10 mm; male part of spike thinner and shorter than female part, 4–6-flowered; female part 5–12-flowered; male glumes yellowish green, lanceolate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, with 1 midrib, apex acuminate; female glumes pale green at middle, white or pale brown laterally, ovate, 1.7–1.8 mm, membranous, glabrous, with 1 midrib, apex obtuse. Utricles pale brown or pale yellowish green, sometimes with brown spots and short lines, elliptic, 3–3.5 mm, patent, membranous, without veins abaxially, with 2–4 raised veins adaxially, glabrous or upper part scabrid, subsessile, apex attenuate into excurved beak of medium length, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, sessile, apex not mucronate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Evergreen forests, shady slopes, roadsides; 1200–2900 m. Hubei, Sichuan, Yunnan.</distribution>
</treatment>

