<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>20.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>continua</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. D. Hooker, Fl. Brit. India</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 717. 1894</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>连续薹草 lian xu tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rafflesiana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <variety_name>continua</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(C. B. Clarke) Küken thal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with thick fibers. Culms tufted, 60–90 × ca. 0.3 cm, trigonous, glabrous. Leaves basal and cauline, longer than culms, flat, 6–8 mm wide, scabrid along margins and abaxially, glabrous adaxially; persistent sheaths dark brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence, long sheathed. Panicle compound, ca. 30 cm, 5–9-branched; inflorescence branches single, sometimes binate, ovate-triangular, 3–8 × 1.5–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, lowest one to 14 cm, upper ones gradually shorter, trigonous, glabrous; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, densely hairy on edges; bractlets glumelike, ca. 1.5 mm, loosely hairy abaxially, with long scabrid awns. Spikes numerous, bisexual, androgynous, arising from cladoprophylls, patent, oblong-cylindric, 4–10 mm; male part of spike shorter than female part, oblong, densely 4–10-flowered; female part 3–9-flowered, slightly dense; male glumes pale brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, lanceolate, 1.7–2.5 mm, membranous, with 1 midrib, upper margins hairy, apex acuminate, mucronate; female glumes pale brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, ovate, 1.8–2.5 mm, membranous, glabrescent later, with 1 midrib, apex acute, awned or mucronate. Utricles pale brownish green with brown spots and short lines, elliptic, trigonous, 2.7–3 mm, membranous, upper part scabrid, with several raised veins adaxially, subsessile, apex attenuate into excurved long beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.7 mm, subsessile, apex not mucronate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Among shrubs on slopes; ca. 1100 m. S Yunnan [India, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, Myanmar, Philippines, Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

