<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>23.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>scaposa</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mag.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>113: t. 6940. 1887</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>花葶薹草 hua ting tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody. Culms lateral, 20–80 × 0.1–0.3 cm, trigonous, base with leafless pale brown sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaves tufted, longer or shorter than culms, elliptic to elliptic-linear, 10–35 × 2–5 cm, glabrous on both surfaces or scabrid or densely hairy abaxially, sometimes with transverse veins, base attenuate, apex acuminate; petiole up to 30 cm, glabrous, sometimes leaf base extending downward forming narrow wings; cauline leaves brown, spathelike, papery, glabrous. Involucral bracts spathelike, with blades, usually shorter than inflorescence branches. Panicle compound, 3- to several branched; inflorescence branches paniculate, single or binate, triangular-ovate, 2–3.5 × 1.5–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches rigid, trigonous, 4–8 cm, densely pubescent; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, densely pubescent; bractlets brownish white with deep brown spots, glumelike, lanceolate, 4–5 mm. Spikes 10–20, bisexual, androgynous, arising from flowerless utriculiform cladoprophylls, patent, oblong-cylindric, 5–14 mm; male part of spike linear-lanceolate, usually shorter than female part, fewer flowered; female part 2–7-flowered; male glumes pale brown, ovate-lanceolate, 3–3.5 mm, membranous; female glumes brown laterally, yellowish green with brown spots and 3 veins at middle, ovate, 2–2.5 mm, membranous, margins ciliate when young, apex acuminate. Utricles pale yellowish green with dense brown spots, elliptic, trigonous, 3–4 mm, papery, with 2 lateral veins abaxially, glabrous, subsessile, apex contracted gradually into beak of medium length, beak slightly shorter than 1/2 length of utricle, orifice emarginate. Nutlets brown at maturity, elliptic, trigonous, 1.5–2.2 mm; style base not or slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, watersides, shady slopes, cliffs, valleys; 200–1500 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hunan, Jiangxi, Sichuan, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Vietnam].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male part of spike 10–13 mm, much longer than female part</statement>
      <determination>23b. var. dolicostachya</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male part of spike less than 7 mm, usually shorter than female part.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves glabrous on both surfaces or scabrid abaxially; style base not thickened</statement>
      <determination>23a. var. scaposa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves densely hairy abaxially; style base slightly thickened</statement>
      <determination>23c. var. hirsuta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

