<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>25.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>densifimbriata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Tang &amp; F. T. Wang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>24: 240. 1986</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>流苏薹草 liu su tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody. Culms lateral, 30–80 × 0.12–0.25 cm, trigonous, densely hairy, rarely glabrous, base with pale brown sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaves tufted, usually shorter or rarely longer than culms, elliptic to narrowly lanceolate, 25–40 × 2.8–4.5 cm, glabrous on both surfaces or scabrid or densely hairy abaxially, base attenuate, margins densely ciliate, apex acuminate; petiole 2–20 cm, hairy; cauline leaves spathelike, lower part green and upper part pale brown, margins ciliate. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle compound, 2- to several branched; inflorescence branches subcorymbose, single or binate, triangular-ovate, 1.5–2.5 × 2–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 4–8 cm, densely hairy; inflorescence axes densely hairy; bractlets glumelike, oblong, 4–5 mm, membranous, densely hairy abaxially, apex obtuse. Spikes 4–12, bisexual, androgynous, patent, ovate to oblong, 5–10 mm; male part of spike oblong, longer than or equaling female part; female part 4–10-flowered; male glumes oblong-lanceolate, 3–4.5 mm, apex acuminate; female glumes pale green at middle, brownish white laterally with dense brown spots and short lines, ovate-oblong, 2.8–3 mm, papery, apex obtuse. Utricles pale yellowish white, sometimes with dense brown spots and short lines, slightly longer than glumes, obliquely patent, elliptic, trigonous, 3–3.5 mm, with 2 lateral veins abaxially, subsessile, apex contracted into beak of medium length, beak slightly shorter than 1/2 length of utricle, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Woods, shady slopes, valleys. Guangxi, Guizhou, Hunan.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves glabrous on both surfaces or scabrid abaxially</statement>
      <determination>25a. var. densifimbriata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves de nsely hairy abaxially</statement>
      <determination>25b. var. hirsuta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

