<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>adrienii</species_name>
    <species_authority>E. G. Camus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Lecomte, Fl. Indo-Chine</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 186. 1912</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>广东薹草 guang dong tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chienii</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>kwangtungensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>scaposa</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <variety_name>baviensis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Franchet.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome subwoody. Culms tufted, lateral, 30–50 × 0.1–0.2 cm, trigonous, densely hairy, base with pale brown leafless sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaves tufted, shorter than culms, narrowly elliptic to elliptic-linear, 25–35 × 2–3 cm, scabrid abaxially, glabrous adaxially, margins entire, apex acuminate; petiole 5–15 cm, glabrous; cauline leaves spathelike, lower part green, upper part pale brown, with dense brown spots and lines, margins ciliate and glabrescent later. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle compound, 2–6-branched; inflorescence branches subcorymbose, single or binate, slightly distant, triangular-ovate, 1.5–2 × 2–2.5 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 2–4 cm, densely hairy; inflorescence axes densely hairy; bractlets glumelike, 3–3.5 mm, densely hairy. Spikes 20 or less, bisexual, androgynous, patent, oblong-cylindric, 7–10 × 2–2.5 mm; male part of spike longer than female part, oblong, with more than 10 flowers; female part ± densely 3–10-flowered; male glumes brown, oblong, ca. 3 mm, membranous, apex obtuse; female glumes brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, ovate-oblong, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex obtuse. Utricles pale brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, elliptic, obliquely or horizontally patent, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, with 2 lateral veins abaxially, base obtuse, apex contracted into beak of medium length, beak slightly shorter than 1/2 length of utricle, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, ovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Evergreen forests, watersides, shady places; 500–1200 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hunan, Sichuan, Yunnan [Laos, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

