<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>27.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>liouana</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Inst. Bot. Natl. Acad. Peiping</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6(2): 62. 1949</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>刘氏薹草 liu shi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody. Culms tufted, lateral, 30–60 × 0.2–0.3 cm, trigonous, loosely pubescent when young, base with brown sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaves tufted, longer or shorter than culms, linear or linear-oblanceolate, sometimes narrowly elliptic, 20–40 × 1.4–4 cm, glabrous on both surfaces or scabrid abaxially, margins entire or ciliate, apex acuminate; petiole 4–20 cm, glabrous; cauline leaves yellowish brown with dense brown spots, spathelike. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle compound, 3–5-branched; inflorescence branches subcorymbose, single or binate, triangular-ovate, 2–3.5 × 2–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 4–6 cm, densely hairy or glabrous; inflorescence axes trigonous; bractlets pale yellow with dense brown spots, glumelike, lanceolate, 3–4 mm, densely hairy or glabrous. Spikes more than 10, bisexual, androgynous, 5–8 mm; male part of spike shorter than or equaling female part, circular or oblong; female part 3–10-flowered; male glumes pale yellowish brown or brown, lanceolate, 2–2.5 mm, membranous; female glumes pale yellowish brown or brown with dark brown spots and short lines, ovate or lanceolate, 2–2.5 mm, 1-veined, apex obtuse. Utricles pale brown with dense dark brown spots and short lines, ovate, rarely elliptic, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, papery, glabrous, with 2 lateral veins abaxially, subsessile, apex contracted into beak of medium length, beak ca. 1/4 length of utricle, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, ovate, trigonous, 1.5–2 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests; 300–1100 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hunan, Jiangxi.</distribution>
</treatment>

