<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>29.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>lingii</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Inst. Bot. Natl. Acad. Peiping</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6(2): 61. 1949</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>林氏薹草 lin shi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>sinocrispa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Raymond.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody. Culms tufted, lateral, flaccid, 15–40 × ca. 0.1 cm, trigonous, loosely hairy and then glabrescent, base with pale to deep brown sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaves tufted, narrowly elliptic to linear-elliptic, 12–30 × 2–2.5 cm, glabrous or scabrid along abaxial veins, base attenuate, margins densely replicate, apex acuminate; petiole 5–20 cm, subglabrous; cauline leaves pale greenish white, sometimes with brown spots and short lines, spathelike, loosely pubescent. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle simple, triangular-ovate, 1.5–3 × 2–3 cm, ca. 10-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, densely hairy; bractlets glumelike, 2.5–3 mm, glabrous. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, arising from flowerless utriculiform cladoprophylls, oblong, patent horizontally, 4–10 mm; male part of spike suborbicular to oblong; female part 3–10-flowered, nearly as long as male part; male glumes pale brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, oblong-lanceolate, 2.2–2.5 mm, membranous, with 1 midrib, apex obtuse; female glumes similar to male ones. Utricles brownish white with dense brown spots and short lines, ovate-elliptic, trigonous, obliquely or horizontally patent, ca. 3.5 mm, membranous, with 2 lateral veins abaxially, subsessile, apex contracted into long beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, ovate, trigonous, 1.5–1.8 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Woods, shady places. Fujian, Zhejiang.</distribution>
</treatment>

