<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>30.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>kucyniakii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Raymond</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Naturaliste Canad.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>82: 155. 1955</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>棕叶薹草 zong ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick, woody, with stolons. Culms loosely tufted, lateral, slender, 22–35 × 0.2–0.25 cm, trigonous, lower part smooth, upper part loosely pubescent, base with brown sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaf single, elliptic or elliptic-lanceolate, 22–42 × 4–10 cm, scabrid abaxially, glabrous adaxially, 7–14-veined, replicate, entire, base attenuate, apex caudate; petiole 7–10 cm, folded, glabrous; cauline leaves green, spathelike, loosely pubescent, margins brown, membranous. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle compound, several branched; inflorescence branches racemose, single or binate, often 1 or 2(or 3)-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, lowest one up to 8 cm, upper ones gradually shorter, scabrid; bractlets glumelike, ovate-lanceolate, 3–4 mm, loosely hairy. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, arising from flowerless utriculiform cladoprophylls, linear-cylindric, 25–40 × 3–4 mm; male part of spike nearly as long as female part, oblong; female part loosely many flowered; male glumes dark brown, oblong, 4.5–5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex obtuse; female glumes pale brown with dark brown spots and short lines, oblong, 4.5–5 mm, membranous, loosely hairy abaxially, 3-veined, apex acuminate. Utricles pale brown with dark brown spots and short lines, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 4 mm, membranous, with 2 lateral veins abaxially, subsessile, apex contracted into beak of medium length, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, obovate-oblong, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Wet grasslands in valleys; ca. 1300 m. SE Yunnan [Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

