<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>31.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>peliosanthifolia</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 162. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>扇叶薹草 shan ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous, woody. Culms lateral, 40–45 × ca. 0.2 cm, trigonous, loosely pubescent, base with brown sheaths. Leaves basal and cauline; basal leaves 2 or 3 tufted on rhizome node, narrowly elliptic, 20–35 × 3.8–7 cm, glabrous or scabrid on abaxial veins, replicate, base attenuate, apex acuminate; petiole 14–24 cm, folded, glabrous; cauline leaves pale greenish white with dense brown spots and short lines, spathelike, pubescent. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle compound, 10- or more branched; inflorescence branches racemose, binate or ternate, 1–3-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 2–10 cm, densely pubescent; bractlets glumelike, ovate-oblong, ca. 3.5 mm, densely pubescent abaxially. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, arising from flowerless utriculiform cladoprophylls, oblong, 5–10 mm; male part of spike slightly shorter than female part, with 10 or more flowers; female part 4–10-flowered; male glumes pale yellow laterally with dense spots and short lines, pale green at middle, ovate-lanceolate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acuminate; female glumes similar to male glumes, but loosely pubescent abaxially. Utricles pale yellowish white with brown spots and short lines, obliquely to horizontally patent, elliptic, trigonous, 3–3.2 mm, membranous, glabrous, with many raised veins, base subrounded, apex attenuate into an excurved long beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, elliptic, trigonous, 1.9–2 mm; style excurved, base not thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Streamsides. Guangxi.</distribution>
</treatment>

