<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>32.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>kwangsiensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 164. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>广西薹草 guang xi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody, with stolons. Culms lateral, 30–50 × ca. 0.15 cm, trigonous, loosely pubescent when young and glabrescent later, with brown sheaths at base. Leaves radical and cauline; radical leaves longer than culms, several ones forming a high shoot, leaf blades linear, flat, 5–7 mm wide, with dense white hairs abaxially, base covered with persistent brown sheaths; cauline leaves brown, spathelike, loosely hairy along veins. Involucral bracts spathelike. Panicle compound; inflorescence branches subcorymbose, single or terminal ones binate, 2–3 × 2–2.5 cm, 3–10-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 5–10 cm, loosely pubescent; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, densely hairy; bractlets glumelike, lanceolate, lowest one 5–10 mm, upper ones gradually shorter, terminal one awnlike, pale brown, loosely pubescent. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, obliquely or horizontally patent, 7–18 mm; male part of spike cylindric, longer than or equaling female part; female part 2–13-flowered; peduncles of spikes arising from flowerless utriculiform cladoprophylls, tenuous, lowest one 2–2.5 mm, upper ones gradually shorter, loosely pubescent; male glumes brown laterally, pale green at middle, lanceolate, 3.5–4 mm, loosely pubescent and glabrescent later, with 1 midrib, margins ciliate, membranous, apex obtuse; female glumes brown laterally, pale green at middle, oblong-lanceolate, 2.2–2.5 mm, membranous, loosely pubescent, with 1 midrib, apex obtuse. Utricles ovate-rhomboid, inflated trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, upper part with brownish red papillae, with many raised veins, hairy, subsessile, apex contracted into an excurved long beak of ca. 1/2 length of utricle, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, ovate-rhomboid, trigonous, ca. 1.8 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Among shrubs in shady valleys. Guangxi.</distribution>
</treatment>

