<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>33.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>oligostachya</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nees</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hooker’s J. Bot. Kew Gard. Misc.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 29. 1854</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>少穗薹草 shao sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rhizomatosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Steudel.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous, woody. Culms lateral, 20–80 × 0.1–0.2 cm, trigonous, glabrous, base with brown sheaths. Leaves radical and cauline; radical leaves shorter than culms, several ones forming a high shoot, leaf blades linear, flat, 2–5 mm wide, base covered with brown sheaths; cauline leaves brown, spathelike. Involucral bracts spathelike, with linear blades, shorter than inflorescence branches. Panicle compound, with 6–12 distant branches; inflorescence branches subcorymbose, single or binate, 3–5-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, erect, slightly scabrid; inflorescence axes loosely hairy on edges; bractlets glumelike, ca. 3 mm. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, patent, 4–10 mm; male part of spike nearly as long as or longer than female part; male glumes brown, lanceolate, 3–3.5 mm, glabrous; female glumes pale brown with dense purplish red spots and short lines, ovate to lanceolate, 2–3 mm, upper part loosely pubescent, margins hyaline, apex obtuse, mucronate. Utricles brownish green to purplish brown, patent, oblong, slightly inflated, trigonous, 2.5–4 mm, with several raised veins, hairy, apex contracted into excurved beak of medium length, beak ca. 1/3 length of utricle, orifice prominently 2-toothed. Nutlets elliptic, trigonous, 2–2.3 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands on slopes; 900–1200 m. Guangxi, Guizhou [India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Myanmar, Papua New Guinea, Philippines, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

