<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>34.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tsiangii</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Inst. Bot. Natl. Acad. Peiping</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6(2): 59. 1949</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>三念薹草 san nian tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>surculosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Raymond.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody, with stolons. Culms tufted, lateral, 40–60 × ca. 0.1 cm, trigonous, glabrous, base with brown sheaths. Leaves radical and cauline; radical leaves longer than culms, several ones forming a high shoot, leaf blades linear, flat, 5–7 mm wide, glabrous, margins entire or scabrid, base covered with brown sheaths; cauline leaves brown, spathelike, loosely pubescent and glabrescent later. Involucral bracts spathelike, with linear blades, shorter than inflorescence branches. Panicle compound, 6–10 cm, 3–6-branched; inflorescence branches subcorymbose, single or binate, 3–10-spiked, broadly ovate, ca. 2 × 2–3 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 3–5.5 cm, slightly scabrid; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, densely hairy and glabrescent later; bractlets pale brown laterally, pale green at middle, glumelike, lanceolate, 2.5–3 mm, loosely pubescent. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, obliquely or horizontally patent, 10–15 mm; male part of spike cylindric, longer than female part; female part 3–9-flowered; male glumes pale green with brown spots and short lines, lanceolate, 3–3.5 mm, with 1 midrib, apex acuminate; female glumes pale brown with brown spots and short lines, ovate-lanceolate, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, loosely pubescent and glabrescent later, with 1 midrib, margins ciliate, apex acute. Utricles brown, elliptic or broadly elliptic, obtusely trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, papery, glabrous, with several fine veins, apex contracted into long beak, beak nearly as long as utricle, orifice minutely 2-toothed. Nutlets elliptic or broadly elliptic, trigonous, 1.5–2 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Among shrubs on slopes. Guangdong.</distribution>
</treatment>

