<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>35.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>moupinensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nouv. Arch. Mus. Hist. Nat., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 10: 102. 1887</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>宝兴薹草 bao xing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Homalostachys</genus_name>
    <species_name>sinensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boeckeler.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous, woody. Culms 20–50 × 0.3–0.4 cm, stiff, trigonous, base with persistent brown sheaths. Leaves longer or shorter than culms, flat, 3–5 mm wide, pubescent and glabrescent later, papillose abaxially, scabrid adaxially, long sheathed, sheath mouth villous. Involucral bracts same as leaves, shorter than inflorescence, much longer than inflorescence branches. Panicle compound, 10–20 cm, 4–10-branched; inflorescence branches corymbose, simple, 5–12-spiked, 2–3 × 1.5–2 cm; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 6–8 cm, trigonous, loosely pubescent; inflorescence axes sharply trigonous, loosely pubescent; bractlets brown, glumelike, lanceolate, 3–4 mm, loosely pubescent. Spikes unisexual, male ones at upper part of inflorescence branches, female at lower part, arising from flowerless utriculiform cladoprophylls; male spikes oblong, 6–10 mm, many flowered, sometimes with few female flowers at base; female spikes oblong, 7–10 mm, densely many flowered, sometimes with few male flowers at top; male glumes brown, lanceolate, 2.5–3.5 mm, membranous, with 1 midrib, apex acuminate; female glumes brownish white with dense brown spots, lanceolate, 2.5–3.5 mm, with 1 midrib, margins narrowly hyaline, apex acuminate. Utricles brownish white with brown spots, obliquely patent, shorter than glumes, obovate, sometimes obliquely obovate, slightly inflated, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, papery, glabrous, 2-veined abaxially, apex contracted abruptly into short beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets yellowish white at maturity, obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.2 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Shady slopes, roadsides. Guizhou, Hubei, Sichuan, Yunnan.</distribution>
</treatment>

