<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>36.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tricephala</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boeckeler</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>58: 263. 1875</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>三头薹草 san tou tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome oblique. Culms tufted, 18–40 × ca. 0.1 cm, slender, trigonous, scabrid at upper part. Leaves longer or shorter than culms, flat, 4–8 mm wide, margins and veins scabrid; persistent sheaths brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, without sheaths, lowest one longer than inflorescence, others very short, setaceous. Panicle spicate, 1–4-branched; inflorescence branches subsessile, fewer spiked, sometimes with sterile spike at lower part. Spikes bisexual, androgynous, dense, ovate-globose, 5–8 × 4–7 mm, subsessile; male part of spike not prominent, usually not exserted from female part, 3–5-flowered; female part densely fewer flowered; male glumes yellowish white, lanceolate, 4.5–5 mm, membranous, upper part hairy, with 1 midrib, apex acuminate; female glumes yellowish white, lanceolate, 3–3.5 mm, densely hairy, with 1 midrib and several fine veins, apex acuminate, with short awns. Utricles yellowish white, slightly inflated, trigonous, 4.5–5 mm, membranous, densely hairy, with 2 lateral keels and several fine veins, subsessile, margins very narrowly winged, apex contracted into long beak, orifice minutely 2-toothed. Nutlets pale yellow at maturity, ovate, trigonous, ca. 3 mm; style base thickened and pyriform; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Forests; 700–1100 m. S Yunnan (Xishuangbanna) [Cambodia, Indonesia, Laos, Myanmar, Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

