<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>58.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>atrata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 976. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>黑穗薹草 hei sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome usually short. Culms densely tufted, 15–65 cm tall, trigonous, scabrous above, slightly inclined at apex, clothed at base with purple-red bladeless sheaths disintegrating into slightly reticulate fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 3–5 mm wide. Lower 1 or 2 involucral bracts leaflike, sheathless, upper ones setaceous or glumelike. Spikes 3–5, contiguous; terminal spike gynaecandrous, obovate or oblong; lateral spikes female, oblong, 10–15 × 5–6 mm, lower 2 with long peduncles, pendulous. Female glumes brown, dark brown, or purple-brown, ovate to narrowly ovate, 1-veined pale brownish costa forming a mucro at apex, apex acute to acuminate. Utricles brownish especially on upper part, nearly equaling or slightly shorter or longer than glume, elliptic or ovate, plano-convex, 3–3.5 mm, minutely papillose, without conspicuous veins except for 2 costas on edges, apex abruptly contracted into a conic short beak, orifice shallowly 2-toothed. Nutlets loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, 1.5–1.7 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Alpine frozen soil, thickets, alpine meadows. Jilin, Qinghai, Sichuan, Taiwan, Xinjiang, SE Xizang, NW Yunnan [Bhutan, India, Japan, Korea, Mongolia, Nepal, Russia; C Asia, Europe].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rhizome long, cree ping</statement>
      <determination>58d. subsp. longistolonifera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rhizome short.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles 4–4.5 mm</statement>
      <determination>58c. subsp. aterrima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles 3–3.8(–4) mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes ovate, apex acute; utricles sessile, apex abruptly contracted into a conic short beak</statement>
      <determination>58a. subsp. atrata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes lanceolate, apex long acuminate; utricles shortly stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a very short beak or beakles s, orifice emarginate</statement>
      <determination>58b. subsp. pullata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

