<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>64.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>caucasica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Steven</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Soc. Imp. Naturalistes Moscou</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 68. 1813</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>高加索薹草 gao jia suo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely or subloosely tufted, 25–70 cm tall, trigonous, scabrous above, clothed at base with dark purple, lustrous bladeless sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves as long as or shorter than culm, blades 3–8 mm wide. Lowest involucral bracts leaflike, slightly longer than inflorescence, remaining bracts setaceous, sheathless. Spikes 4–7; terminal spikes gynaecandrous, obovate or oblong, 15–25 × 5–6 mm; remaining spikes female, ovate or oblong to clavate, 1.5–3 × 0.6–0.8 cm, densely many flowered, with peduncle 4–5 cm, lowest 1 or 2 pendent on elongate peduncle. Female glumes dark purple-brown to purple-black, lanceolate, oblong-ovate, or lanceolate-elliptic, 3.2–3.8 mm, membranous, margins white hyaline, 3-veined yellowish costa forming a mucro at apex, apex acute to cuspidate. Utricles yellowish greenish, upper part ± stained with purple or ferruginous-yellow at length, obovate, obovate-elliptic, or compressed trigonous, 3–4 mm, faintly 3–5-veined at base or 7–9-veined abaxially, apex abruptly contracted into an erect short beak, orifice subtruncate or 2-toothed-emarginate. Nutlets loosely contained, obovate or elliptic, trigonous, 1.9–2.5 mm; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Alpine meadows and grasslands. Taiwan, Xinjiang [C Asia, SW Asia (Caucasus), Europe].</distribution>
  <discussion>No specimens have been seen by the present authors.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 4–8 mm wi de; utricles 3.5–4 mm, faintly 3–5-veined at base; nutlets obovate, ca. 2.5 mm</statement>
      <determination>64a. subsp. caucasica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 3–5 mm wide; utricles 3–3.5 mm, 5–9-veined abaxially; nutlets elliptic, 1.9–2.1 mm</statement>
      <determination>64b. s ubsp. jisaburo-ohwiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

