<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>66.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>globularis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 976. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>玉簪薹草 yu zan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome obliquely ascending, stoloniferous; stolons slender, clothed with red-brown leaf sheaths. Culms loosely tufted, 20–60 cm tall, slender, triquetrous, slightly scabrous on upper part, red-brown and bladeless sheathed at base; sheaths at membranous part usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves equaling or slightly shorter than culm, blades 1–2 mm wide, rather soft, glabrous, margins revolute, upper margin scabrous; sheaths rather long, hispidulous adaxially. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, linear, shorter than inflorescence, nearly not sheathed, upper involucral bracts scalelike, not sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4, male spike and uppermost female spike approximate, remaining spikes remote; terminal spike male, linear, 1–2 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, oblong, ovate, or subglobose, 0.5–1.2 cm, few flowered; lowermost spike very shortly pedunculate, upper ones sessile. Female glumes yellow-brown at middle, ovate, ca. 2 mm, membranous, 3-veined, sometimes 2 lateral veins indistinct, margins yellowish white, apex obtuse, muticous. Utricles green-brown, obliquely patent, longer than glume, broadly obovate or broadly elliptic, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, densely hispidulous, many veined, base broadly cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets dark brown, tightly enveloped, obovate or broadly obovate, trigonous, 1.8–2 mm, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands on mountain slopes, wet places in forests, swamps. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Russia; Europe].</distribution>
  <discussion>The stems and leaves of this species are good pasture for sheep, cows, and horses.</discussion>
</treatment>

