<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>67.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>ulobasis</species_name>
    <species_authority>V. I. Kreczetowicz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Komarov, Fl. URSS</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 608. 1935</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>卷叶薹草 juan ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>montana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <variety_name>manshuriensis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Komarov.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, ligneous. Culms densely tufted, 15–25 cm tall, slightly compressed triquetrous, smooth on lower part, slightly scabrous on upper part, red-brown and bladeless sheathed at base, sheaths eventually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves equaling or shorter than culm, blades 1–2.5 mm wide, ± stiff, flat, loosely pubescent on adaxial surface, scabrous on margins, long and red-brown sheathed; sheaths usually split at membranous side, eventually blade at base usually volute. Involucral bracts scalelike, ovate, hyaline on margins, basal part closing around stem, aristate at base. Spikes 2 or 3, rather congregate at top of culm; terminal spike male, lanceolate or clavate, 0.8–1.5 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, ovate, 0.8–1.2 cm, densely 10- or more flowered, sessile. Female glumes ferruginous, oblong, ca. 4 mm, membranous, 1-veined, costa pale brown, apex emarginate, mucronate or shortly awned. Utricles yellowish green, ferruginous on upper part and beak, obliquely patent, equaling or slightly shorter than glume, oblong-obovate, compressed trigonous, 4–4.5 mm, loosely white villous, distinctly many veined, base gradually narrowed to a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed to a short beak, orifice obliquely truncate or emarginate. Nutlets brown, rather tightly enveloped, ovate or oblong-ovate, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, base shortly stipitate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Lax forests and among shrubs on sunny mountain slopes, meadows. Heilongjiang, Nei Mongol [Korea, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
</treatment>

