<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>68.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chinganensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Litvinov</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sched. Herb. Fl. Ross.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 135. 1908</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>兴安薹草 xing an tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender, creeping or obliquely ascending, clothed with red-brown and bladeless sheaths. Culms tufted, 20–40 cm tall, slender, compressed triquetrous, smooth on lower part, scabrous on angles of upper part, red-brown sheathed at base. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 1–1.5 mm wide, flat, scabrous on upper surface and margins, sheathed; sheaths usually split at one side. Lowermost involucral bract leaflike, linear, upper ones scalelike, aristate, not sheathed. Spikes 2 or 3, congregated at top of culm, lowermost one slightly remote; terminal spike male, clavate or linear, 0.8–1.2 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, globose or broadly ovate, ca. 5 mm, few flowered, sessile. Female glumes brownish, broadly ovate, 2.2–2.5 mm, 1-veined, margins hyaline, apex acuminate. Utricles yellowish green, slightly pale brown at base and near apex, obliquely patent, slightly longer than or equaling glume, obovate, obtusely trigonous, 2.5–2.8 mm, herbaceous, densely hispidulous, not veined or indistinctly few veined at base, base cuneate, margins hyaline, apex abruptly contracted into a rather short beak, orifice obliquely truncate or emarginate. Nutlets yellowish, tightly enveloped, subelliptic or elliptic-obovate, obtusely trigonous, ca. 2 mm, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Forests on mountain slopes. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol [Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

