<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>70.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>vanheurckii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Müller Argovensis</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Van Heurck, Observ. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 30. 1870</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>鳞苞薹草 lin bao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender, clothed with dark brown, bladeless sheaths, stoloniferous. Culms tufted, 10–30 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, scabrid on upper part, brown sheathed at base, sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves slightly shorter than culm, blades 1–2 mm wide, flat, scabrous on upper surface and margins, sometimes slightly revolute on margins when dry, long sheathed. Involucral bracts scalelike, rarely lowermost one subulate, green, long aristate. Spikes 2 or 3, congregated at top of culm, sometimes lowermost one slightly remote; terminal spike male, linear or fusiform, 0.7–1.5 cm, nearly sessile; lateral spikes female, globose or ovate, 4–7 mm, few flowered, sessile. Female glumes brown laterally, ovate, ca. 2.5 mm, with a pale midrib, hyaline on upper margin, apex acuminate, mucronate. Utricle yellowish green, slightly brown on upper part, obliquely patent, nearly equaling glume, elliptic or obovate, plano-convex-trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, laxly hispidulous, not veined, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, hispidulous on margins of beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets tightly enveloped in utricle, broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.7 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Forests or grasslands on mountain slopes; ca. 1200 m. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol [Japan, N Korea, Mongolia, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
</treatment>

