<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>71.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pseudosupina</species_name>
    <species_authority>Y. C. Tang ex L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phyto tax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 177. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>高山薹草 gao shan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with slender stolons, clothed with brown bladeless leaf sheaths. Culms tufted, 5–8 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth on lower part and scabrous on angles of top, clothed with few yellow-brown or red-brown, bladeless sheaths at base, sheaths partly splitting into fibers. Leaves slightly longer than or shorter than culm, blades 0.5–1 mm wide, rather thin, flat or slightly revolute on margins, sheathed; sheaths membranous at one side, usually split. Involucral bracts yellowish brown, scalelike, lanceolate, awned at apex, not sheathed. Spikes 2 or 3, congregate at top of culm; terminal spike male, lanceolate, 7–8 mm, sessile; lateral spikes female, broadly ovate or subglobose, 5–6 mm, densely several flowered, sessile. Female glumes dark red-brown, elliptic or elliptic-ovate, ca. 3 mm, 1-costate, upper margins hyaline, apex acute or obtuse. Utricles greenish yellow, sometimes slightly brown, suberect or slightly obliquely patent, shorter than glume, broadly obovate or obovate, obtusely trigonous, 2–2.2 mm, leathery, shiny, glabrous, not veined, base cuneate, margins membranous, apex abruptly contracted into a very short beak, orifice truncate. Nutlets dark brown, tightly enveloped, broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm; style persistent, base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>● Mountain slopes; ca. 3700 m. Sichuan (Kangding).</distribution>
</treatment>

