<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>75.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>aridula</species_name>
    <species_authority>V. I. Kreczetowicz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mater. Gerb. Bot. Inst. Komaro va Akad. Nauk S.S.S.R.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 191. 1946</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>干生薹草 gan sheng tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long stoloniferous. Culms tufted, 5–20 cm tall, slender, compressed triquetrous, smooth on lower part and scabrous on angles of upper part, few red-brown and bladeless sheathed and rudimentary sheathed at base, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter or slightly longer than culm, blades 1–1.5 mm wide, scabrous on upper surface and margins, sometimes slightly involute on margins. Involucral bracts scalelike, lowermost long awned at apex, enclosing culm at base. Spikes 2 or 3, uppermost female spike and male spike approximate, lowermost female spike rather remote; terminal spike male, clavate, 1–1.5 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, globose or oblong, 5–8 mm, densely several to 10-flowered, sessile. Female glumes red-brown, ovate or broadly ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, with 1 midrib, margins white hyaline, apex acute. Utricles yellowish green, slightly brownish at maturity, first obliquely patent, later nearly horizontally divaricate, globose-obovate, obtusely trigonous, ca. 3 mm, smooth, shiny, nerveless, base broadly cuneate, margins white hyaline, apex abruptly contracted into a very short beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets dark brown, obovate or broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base cuneate, apex mucronate; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>● Alpine meadows, mountain slopes, ditch sides; 2000–3900 m. Gansu, Nei Mongol, Qinghai, Sichuan, Xizang.</distribution>
</treatment>

