<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>76.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>turkestanica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Regel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trudy Imp. S.-Peterburgsk. Bot. Sada</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 570. 1880</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>新疆薹草 xin jiang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>nitida</species_name>
    <species_authority>Host</species_authority>
    <variety_name>aspera</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Boeckeler) Kükenthal</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>obesa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Allioni</species_authority>
    <variety_name>aspera</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Boeckeler.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long, creeping or obliquely ascending. Culms tufted, 10–30 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, clothed with few red-brown and bladeless sheaths and rudimentary sheaths at base, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 1–3 mm wide, ± stiff, flat or revolute on margins, scabrous on upper surfaces and margins, rather shortly sheathed. Lowest involucral bract leaflike, shortly sheathed, upper ones scalelike, long awned at apex. Spikes 3–5, upper spikes congregated at top of culm, lowest spike rather remote; terminal spikes 1 or 2 male, lanceolate or lanceolate-clavate, 1–2.5 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, oblong or ovate, 1–1.5 cm, densely several to 12-flowered, shortly pedun-culate. Female glumes red-brown, oblong-ovate, ca. 4 mm, membranous, 1-veined, margins yellowish hyaline, apex acuminate. Utricles yellow-green, dark brown at maturity, yellow at base, obliquely patent, later nearly horizontally divaricate, almost equaling glume, subelliptic or elliptic-obovate, obtusely trigonous, 3.8–4 mm, leathery, smooth, indistinctly veined, base broadly cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a medium-sized to long beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets gray, elliptic or subobovate, trigonous, ca. 3 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>Mountain slopes, valleys, forests; 1000–2600 m. Gansu, Xinjiang [Afghanistan, Russia (W Siberia), Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Pakistan, Tajikistan, Uzbekistan].</distribution>
</treatment>

