<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>78.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>inanis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kunth</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 522. 1837</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>毛囊薹草 mao nang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short and thick, ligneous. Culms densely tufted, 10–50 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, clothed with few red-brown and bladeless sheaths, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves shorter or slightly longer than culm, blades 1–2 mm wide, scabrous and revolute on margins, sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, slender, longer than inflorescence, lower involucral bracts shortly sheathed, upper very shortly sheathed or almost not sheathed. Spikes 4–7, lowest spike inserted near base of culm or rather remote, remaining spikes congregated at top of culm; terminal spike male, narrowly cylindric or narrowly lanceolate, 1.5–4 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, sometimes with few male flowers at apex or branching bearing secondary spikes at base, female spikes oblong or oblong-cylindric, 0.8–2.5 cm, densely many flowered, lower spikes shortly pedunculate, upper subsessile. Female glumes yellowish brown, oblong or subovate, 2–3 mm, membranous, costate, apex acuminate. Utricles stramineous, sometimes brownish at base, obliquely patent, shorter than glume, broadly ovate or ovate, trigonous, 2–2.5 mm, membranous, densely white hispidulous, indistinctly veined, base abruptly contracted into a very short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets brown, tightly enveloped in utricle, obovate, broadly obovate, or subelliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex with torsional mucro; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Dense forests, riversides, mountain slopes; 2300–3500 m. Xizang, Yunnan [Bhutan, NE India, Kashmir, Nepal].</distribution>
</treatment>

