<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>79.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>setigera</species_name>
    <species_authority>D. Don</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14: 330. 1824</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>长茎薹草 chang jing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with slender, ligneous stolons. Culms hardly tufted, 8–35 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, red-brown and bladeless sheathed at base, rudimentary sheaths usuually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves longer or shorter than culm, blades 1–3 mm wide, flat, scabrous on margins, sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, linear, lower involucral bracts longer than inflorescence, sheathed, uppermost shorter than inflorescence, not sheathed. Spikes 3–6, congregated at top of culm, approximate; male spikes 1–4, inserted at top of culm, cylindric or oblong-lanceolate, 5–25 mm, nearly sessile; remaining spikes bisexual or female, oblong-cylindric, narrowly oblong, or oblong, 0.8–3 cm, slightly laxly many flowered, lower spikes pedunculate, upper spikes sessile or subsessile. Female glumes purple-brown, ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, costate, costa yellowish, apex acuminate. Utricles yellowish green, purple-brown flecked, obliquely patent, shorter than glume, obovate, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, laxly hispidulous, indistinctly veined, base gradually attenuate into a short stipe, apex attenuate into a short beak, orifice obliquely truncate and emarginate. Nutlets dark brown, tightly enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 1 mm, base very shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places at riversides, forests on mountain slopes, grasslands; 2300–4100 m. Xizang, Yunnan [Bhutan, India, Kashmir, Nepal, Pakistan].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>C ulms 25–35 cm tall; leaves longer or slightly shorter than culm; male spikes 2–4, congregated at top of culm, cylindric, 5–25 mm, remaining spikes bisexual, androgynous, oblong-cylindric or narrowly oblong, 2–3 cm; utricles 2.5–3 mm</statement>
      <determination>79a. var. setige ra</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms 8–15 cm tall; leaves shorter than culm; male spike 1, terminal, oblong- lanceolate, 6–8 mm, remaining spikes female, oblong, 0.8–1 cm; utricles ca. 2 mm</statement>
      <determination>79b. var. schlagintweitiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

