<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>80.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>lancisquamata</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Da i</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 181. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>披针鳞薹草 pi zhen lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous, stolons slightly thick and long, clothed with purple-brown sheaths. Culms tufted, 40–45 cm tall, rather slender, obtusely trigonous, scabrid on angles, few purple-brown and bladeless sheathed at base, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves slightly shorter or slightly longer than culm, blades 2–4 mm wide, canaliculate on midrib of upper surface, revolute on margins, scabrous on upper surface and margins, rather long sheathed, sheaths 5–6 cm and purple-brown at lower part of culm. Involucral bracts leaflike, lower 1 or 2 longer than inflorescence, shortly sheathed, upper ones linear, shorter than inflo-rescence, not sheathed. Spikes 6 or 7, rather congregated at top of culm, sometimes lowest one rather remote; uppermost spikes 2 or 3 male, sometimes with few female flowers at base, lanceolate or cylindric, 1.5–3 cm, subsessile; remaining spikes female or androgynous, cylindric, 4–5 cm, densely many flowered, lower spikes with slender peduncles, upper ones with short peduncles. Female glumes purple-brown or yellow-brown laterally, lanceolate, 6–8 mm, membranous, 1-costate, apex acuminate, long aristate, arista 2–4 mm. Utricles olivaceous and slightly red-brown at base and beak, obliquely patent, shorter than glume, elliptic or broadly elliptic, obtusely trigonous or plano-convex, ca. 3 mm, herbaceous, densely white hispidulous, indistinctly veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex abruptly narrowed into a ± long beak, orifice subtruncate or emarginate. Nutlets brown, tightly enveloped in utricle, orbicular-ovate or suborbicular, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style base deflexed, not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>● Riversides; ca. 2600 m. W Yunnan (Dali).</distribution>
</treatment>

