<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>83.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>maculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 128. 1846</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>斑点果薹草 ban dian guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender, ligneous. Culms tufted, 30–55 cm tall, slightly thin, triquetrous, smooth, few yellowish brown and bladeless sheathed at base. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 3–6 mm wide, flat, smooth, sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescences, sheathed, sheath rather long in lowermost part and short in upper part. Spikes 3 or 4, lowermost spike remote, others congregated at top of culm; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, (1.5–)2–6 cm, nearly sessile; lateral spikes female, oblong-cylindric to cylindric, (1–)2–4 cm, densely many flowered, lower spikes rather long pedunculate, upper shortly pedunculate. Female glumes yellowish brown, with short ferruginous striae, oblong-ovate or ovate, ca. 2 mm, membranous, 3-veined and green on veins, apex acute or obtuse, sometimes mucronate. Utricles yellow-brown, becoming dark purple, obliquely patent, longer than glume, broadly obovate or nearly broadly elliptic, trigonous, 2.2–2.5 mm, membranous, densely purple papillate, 3–5-veined, base gradually attenuate and cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a very short beak, orifice subtruncate or emarginate. Nutlets yellowish brown, tightly enveloped in utricle, broadly obovate or broadly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex with inflected mucro; style base not thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places at ditch sides in valleys, forests, grasslands at the foot of mountains; 400–1300 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Zhejiang [India, Indonesia, Sri Lanka].</distribution>
</treatment>

