<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>84.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>angustiutricula</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 182. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>狭果囊薹草 xia guo nang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, ligneous, without stolons. Culm tufted, 30–35 cm, rather thin, obtusely trigonous, smooth, brown and bladeless sheathed at base. Leaves shorter or slightly longer than culm, blades 3–6 mm wide, flat, scabrous on apex margin and veins, slightly long sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, rather shortly sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4, lowermost one remote, others approximate at top of culm; terminal spike male, narrowly cylindric, 2.5–5 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, narrowly cylindric, 1.5–3.5 cm, densely many flowered, lowermost spike slightly long pedunculate, upper ones shortly pedunculate or subsessile. Female glumes yellowish, with short red-brown striae, narrowly oblong, ca. 1.8 mm, membranous, 1-costate, costa green, apex obtuse, muticous. Utricles yellowish brown, obliquely patent, later nearly horizontally patent, slightly longer than glume, obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, membranous, densely purple-red glandular punctate, distinctly 5-veined, base cuneate or broadly cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex attenuate into a short beak, orifice subtruncate or emarginate. Nutlets yellowish white, tightly enveloped in utricles, obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.2 mm, apex with inflected mucro; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Wet places on mountain slopes; ca. 1600 m. Sichuan (Emei Shan, Mabian).</distribution>
</treatment>

