<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>86.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>truncatigluma</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 315. 1904</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>截鳞薹草 jie lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>gracilispica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome obliquely ascending, covered with dark brown fibrous remains of old leaf sheath. Flowering culms arising from axils of leaves, 10–30 cm tall, trigonous, slender, slightly scabrid. Leaves equaling to longer than culm, blade 3–10 mm wide, flat, scabrid on both surfaces, herbaceous. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, sheathed, sheath 6–9 mm. Spikes 4–6; terminal spike male, narrowly cylindric, 1–1.5 cm, ca. 1 mm thick, sessile or with peduncle 0.5–2 cm; lateral spikes female, cylindric, 20–50 × 2.5–3 mm, loosely flowered, uppermost female spike surpassing male spike, with peduncle enclosed in involucral bract sheath, lower female spikes spaced, with exserted peduncles, lowest peduncle 2–4(–6) cm. Female glumes dark yellow, broadly obovate, margins broadly hyaline, green costa projecting into a mucro 0.1–0.3 mm, apex truncate to rounded, often emarginate. Utricles olive-green, longer than glume, fusiform, obscurely trigonous, 3–6 × ca. 1 mm, membranous, minutely pubescent, many veined, base cuneate, stipitate, apex attenuate into a beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlet pale brown, tightly enveloped, fusiform, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, with faces excavated both at upper and lower parts, base stipitate, stipe 0.2–0.3 mm, apex with a distinct, stout, cylindric neck, neck ca. 0.5 mm, truncate or shallowly concave at top; style base slightly thickened, persistent; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Mar–May.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, grasslands on mountain slopes, streamsides; 500–1200 m. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan, Hunan, Jiangxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Malaysia, Philippines, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

