<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>87.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rhynchachaenium</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Publ. Bur. Sci. Gov. Lab.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>35: 5. 1905</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>喙果薹草 hui guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>hatusimana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>truncatigluma</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <subspecies_name>rhynchachaenium</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>(C. B. Clarke) Y. C. Tang &amp; S. Yun Liang.</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants densely tufted in small clumps. Rhizome short, clothed with hard, dark brown fibers. Culms very low, hidden by leaves, 5–10 cm tall. Leaves narrowly linear, very elongate, 15–28 cm, 2–3 mm wide, gradually tapering to long acute apex. Lower 2 or 3 involucral bracts leaflike, much surpassing inflorescence, up to 20 cm, shortly sheathing. Spikes 3–6, subfastigiate except lowest, erect; terminal spike male, linear, 1–2 cm, shorter than next female spike; lateral spikes female, shortly cylindric, 1–2 cm, sublaxly and contiguously few flowered, peduncle enclosed in sheath. Female glumes stramineous, oblong-elliptic, hard membranous, slenderly many veined besides obsoletely 3-veined costa, ciliolate, apex truncate-rounded, occasionally mucronate. Utricles upright, lageniform with weak constriction at middle, 2 × as long as glume, 5–6.5 mm, thickly membranous, wholly pubescent, slenderly many veined, base stipitate, apex gradually narrowed to erect short beak, orifice shallowly 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enclosed, ovate-rhomboid, ca. 4 mm, trigonous, base cuneate, apex with neck ca. 1 × 0.7 mm, and truncate at top; style short, base thickened; stigmas 3, short.</description>
  <distribution>Taiwan [Philippines, Vietnam].</distribution>
  <discussion>This species, which can be discerned at once by the short, slender culms concealed by the leaf tussocks, clearly differs from Carex truncatigluma by the larger (5.5–6.5 mm vs. 3–3.7 mm) utricles of thicker texture and the muticous (vs. cuspidate) subtending glumes.</discussion>
</treatment>

