<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>92.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>breviscapa</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. D. Hooker, Fl. Brit. India</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 736. 1894</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>短葶薹草 duan ting tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>laxisquamata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Tang &amp; F. T. Wang</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>lutchuensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>obtusobracteata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms 10–20 cm tall, trigonous. Basal sheaths dark brown, split into fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades 4–7 mm wide, flat, smooth, leathery. Involucral bracts leafy, much longer than inflorescence, sheathed. Inflorescence 3–5-noded; spikes many, 3–5 at each node; terminal spike male, linear, 17–45 × 1–1.5 mm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female or mostly with male part at apex, narrowly cylindric, 3–4.5 cm, ca. 3 mm thick, subloosely flowered, sessile or shortly pedunculate. Female glumes ovate-oblong, 2.5–3 mm, ciliate, apex rounded. Utricles green, longer than glume, rhombic-fusiform, trigonous, 3.5–5 mm, membranous, many veined, gla-brous or puberulent above, base cuneate, stipitate, apex gradually attenuate into a conic beak, beak ca. 1 mm, 2-toothed at orifice. Nutlet brown to dark brown, tightly enveloped, rhombic, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, faces excavated in both upper and lower parts, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex with distinct short neck ca. 0.3 mm, neck shallowly concave at top, neck and angles yellowish white; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. winter, fr. next spring.</description>
  <distribution>Forests; 400–1000 m. Fujian, Hainan, Taiwan [Indonesia, Japan, Malaysia, Myanmar, Philippines, Sri Lanka, Thailand, Vietnam; Australia].</distribution>
</treatment>

