<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>94.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>foraminata</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot .</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 285. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>穿孔薹草 chuan kong tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stout, covered with fibrous remains of old scales. Culms 40–70 cm tall, rather stout, trigonous, smooth, surrounded at base by dark brown bladeless sheaths, sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves longer than or equaling culm, blades 4–7 mm wide, flat, leathery, smooth, margins scabrid. Lower involucral bracts shortly leaflike, upper one bristlelike, shorter than subtending spike, sheath 2–5 cm. Spikes 4–6; terminal spike male, cylindric, 50–80 × 3–5 mm, with peduncle 4–6 cm; lateral spikes female, spaced, cylindric, 50–80 × 3–5 mm, densely flowered, ± nodding at apex, peduncle 2–4 cm, slightly exserted but upper ones enclosed in involucral bract sheath. Female glumes pale brown on both upper sides, oblong, 3–3.5 mm, costa pale green, with a distinct midrib, apex acute. Utricles shorter than glume, obovate, 2–2.5 mm (including stipe), prominently many veined, puberulent, base stipitate, apex shortly beaked, beak slightly recurved, emarginate at orifice. Nutlet stramineous, tightly enveloped, shortly oblong, 1.5–2 mm, with angles contracted at middle, base with short and bent stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a short cylindric beak; style base slightly thickened, most parts not persistent; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Forest margins on mountain slopes, shady places near rocks in valleys, ditch sides; 300–800 m. Anhui, Fujian, Guizhou, Jiangxi, Zhejiang.</distribution>
</treatment>

