<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>104.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tristachya</species_name>
    <species_authority>Thunberg</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Murray, Syst. Veg., ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14, 845. 1784</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>三穗薹草 san sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 20–45 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth. Basal sheath dark brown, split into fibers. Leaves shorter than or nearly equaling culm, blades 2–4(–5) mm wide, flat, margins scabrid. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than subtending spikes, sheathed, sheath 6–12 mm. Spikes 4–6, upper ones contiguous and fastigiate, sometimes lowest one distant; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 10–40 × 1–1.5 mm, subsessile, male glumes free or connate from base to above middle, filament of stamen threadlike or flat, free or connate; lateral spikes cylindric, 10–30(–35) × 2–3 mm, densely flowered; upper peduncles short and enclosed in involucral bract sheath, lowest one exserted. 2.5–3.5(–5.5) cm, erect, slender. Female glumes pale yellow laterally, elliptic or oblong, ca. 2 mm, costa green, apex obtuse, truncate, or acute, mucronate. Utricles green, longer than glume, erect, ovate-fusiform, trigonous, 3–3.2 mm, membranous, puberulent, many veined, base attenuate and stipitate, apex attenuate into a beak, orifice minutely 2-toothed. Nutlet pale brown, tightly enveloped, ovate, 2–2.5 mm, apex discoid-annulate; style base conically thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Mar–May.</description>
  <distribution>Waysides and grasslands on mountain slopes, wet places in forests and field margins, forests; 300–1100 m. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hainan, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male glumes free, filament of stamen threadlike, free</statement>
      <determination>104a. var. tristachya</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male glumes connate from base to abo ve middle, filament of stamen flat and connate</statement>
      <determination>104b. var. pocilliformis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

