<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>106.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>mitrata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Philom. Paris, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8, 7: 88. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>灰帽薹草 hui mao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms 10–30 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth. Basal sheaths brown. Leaves longer than culm, blades 1.5–2(–3) mm wide, flat, scabrid. Basal involucral bract bristlelike, shorter than inflorescence, shortly sheathed, sheath 3–4 mm. Spikes 3 or 4, upper ones contiguous, lowest one slightly spaced; terminal spike male, oblong-linear or linear, sessile or shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, cylindric, 5–15 × 2–3 mm, slightly densely flowered, upper ones subsessile, lowest one with peduncle enclosed in involucral bract sheath or shortly exserted. Female glumes pale brown, obovate-oblong, ca. 2 mm, green costa 1-veined, apex acute, usually mucronate or shortly awned. Utricles pale yellow-green, longer than or nearly equaling glume, ovate-fusiform, obtusely trigonous, 2–2.5 mm, membranous, sparsely puberulent or subglabrous, many veined, base attenuate and shortly stipitate, apex contracted into a conic beak, orifice truncate or emarginate. Nutlet tightly enveloped, ovate, 1.5–2 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex discoid-annulate; style base conically thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Sandy slopes, bamboo forests, grasslands on mountain slopes. Anhui, Hubei, Jiangsu, Sichuan, Taiwan, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male spike 1–1.7 cm, linear; female glume usually mucronate</statement>
      <determination>106a. var. mitrata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male spike shorter, oblong-linear; female glume shortly awned</statement>
      <determination>106b. var. aristata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

