<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>108.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>orthostemon</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Coll. Sci. Imp. Univ . Tokyo</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>30: 389. 1911</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>直蕊薹草 zhi rui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>breviculmis</species_name>
    <species_authority>R. Brown</species_authority>
    <variety_name>cupulifera</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Hayata) Y. C. Tang &amp; S. Yun Liang</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>orthostemon</species_name>
    <variety_name>cupulifera</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Hayata.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants densely tufted with short erect rhizome. Culms slender, 6–30 cm tall, ± recurved. Leaves shorter than to briefly overtopping culms, blades 2–5 mm wide; sheaths short, brownish, eventually disintegrating into brown fibers. Involucral bracts shortly sheathing (3–6 mm), lower 1 or 2 bladed and surpassing spikes. Spikes 2–4, subfastigiate or lowest spaced; terminal spike male, pale brownish, linear-oblong, several flowered; lateral spikes female, ovoid to oblong, 5–20 mm, laxly several flowered, subsessile or lower ones with short enclosed peduncle. Female glumes tinged with light brown, ovate, ca. 2 mm, costa ending in a short mucro at acute apex. Utricles much longer than glume, lanceolate-oblong, suberect, 3.5–4.5 mm, sparsely pubescent, slenderly many veined, base gradually narrowed to a shortly stipe, apex gradually attenuate into a short beak, orifice shallowly 2-lobed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, lanceolate-oblong, 2.5–3 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex annulate; style base dilated; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Grassy openings of mountain forests. Taiwan.</distribution>
  <discussion>This is a good species that can be readily separated from the widespread Carex breviculmis not only by its slender lanceolate-oblong (vs. obovate) utricles but by its subleathery (vs. herbaceous) leaves.</discussion>
</treatment>

