<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>109.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>breviculmis</species_name>
    <species_authority>R. Brown</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>242. 1810</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>青绿薹草 qing lü tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short or elongate and stoloniferous. Culms tufted, 8–40 cm tall, trigonous, scabrid above. Basal sheaths pale brown, split into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 2–3(–5) mm wide, flat, stiff, margins scabrid. Lowest involucral bract leafy, longer than inflorescence, shortly sheathed, sheath 1.5–2 mm, remaining bracts bristlelike, nearly sheathless. Spikes 2–5, upper ones contiguous, lower ones spaced; terminal spike male, oblong, 10–15 × 2–3 mm, subsessile, close to next female spike; lateral spikes female, oblong or oblong-ovate, subcylindric, 6–15(–20) × 3–4 mm, densely flowered, sessile or lowest one with peduncle 2–3 mm. Female glumes pale, oblong or obovate-oblong, 2–2.5 (excluding awn) × 1.2–2 mm, membranous, green costa 3-veined and excurrent into an awn 2–3.5 mm, apex truncate or rounded. Utricles pale green, nearly equaling glume, obovate, obtusely trigonous, membranous, densely puberulent above, several veined, base attenuate and shortly stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a conic beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlet chestnut-colored, tightly enveloped, ovate, ca. 1.8 mm, apex discoid-annulate; style base conically thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands on mountain slopes, waysides, ditch sides in valleys; 400–2300 m. Anhui, Fujian, Gansu, Guangdong, Guizhou, Hebei, Heilongjiang, Henan, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Jilin, Liaoning, Shaanxi, Shandong, Shanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Yunnan, Zhejiang [India, Japan, Korea, Myanmar, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rhizome short; culm slender</statement>
      <determination>109a. var. breviculmis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rhizome stoloniferous; culm much stouter</statement>
      <determination>109b. var. fibrillosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

