<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>113.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>subebracteata</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Kükenthal) Ohwi</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Coll. Sci. Kyoto Imp. Univ., Ser. B, Biol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 252. 1931</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>小苞叶薹草 xiao bao ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pisiformis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <variety_name>subebracteata</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Kükenthal</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Engler, Pflanzenr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>38(IV. 20): 477. 1909.</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with slender stolons. Culms tufted, 15–30 cm tall, slender, compressed trigonous, smooth. Basal sheaths pale brown or brown, split into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 1.5–2.5 mm wide, flat, scabrid adaxially and along margins. Involucral bracts bristlelike, shorter than subtending spike, sheathed, sheaths 5–7 mm. Spikes 2 or 3, spaced; terminal spike male, sometimes close to next female spike, narrowly cylindric or clavate, 12–18 × 2–3 mm, with peduncle 0.4–2.5 cm; lateral spikes female, cylindric or oblong, 6–12 × ca. 3 mm, rather densely flowered, with peduncle enclosed in involucral bract sheath or slightly exserted. Female glumes rusty colored, obovate or ovate, margins white membranous, green costa with distinct midrib excurrent into a scabrid mucro, apex acute. Utricles pale green, longer than or nearly equaling glume, obovate or broadly obovate, obtusely trigonous, 2–2.7 mm, sparsely puberulent, faintly few veined, base attenuate into a short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a conic beak, beak slightly recurved, emarginate abaxially and truncate adaxially at orifice. Nutlet tightly enveloped, broadly obovate, obtusely trigonous, 1.2–1.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex discoid-annulate; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places in forests. Heilongjiang, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
</treatment>

