<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>120.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>kiangsuensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>27: 109. 1929</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>江苏薹草 jiang su tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>conica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott ex Perry</species_authority>
    <variety_name>densa</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Kükenthal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 20–45 cm tall, slender, compressed trigonous, smooth, slightly scabrid above. Basal sheaths bladeless, dark brown, split into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 2–3 mm wide, flat, ± stiff, margins scabrid. Involucral bracts bristlelike, shorter than inflorescence, sheathed, sheath (3–)5–8 mm. Spikes 3 or 4, spaced; terminal spike male, oblong-elliptic or clavate, 12–25 × 3–5 mm, with peduncle 1–2 cm; lateral spikes female, oblong or narrowly cylindric, 8–15 × 2–3 mm, subdensely flowered, with peduncles enclosed in involucral bract sheath. Female glumes pale brown, diluted colored on margins, broadly ovate or obovate, 2.5–3 × ca. 1.8 mm, costa with distinct midvein excurrent into a mucro at apex, apex emarginate or ± acute. Utricles pale green, slightly shorter than glume, ovate-oblong, trigonous, 3–3.5 mm, glabrous, slenderly many veined, base attenuate into a short stipe, apex attenuate into a conic beak, orifice truncate. Nutlet tightly enveloped, oblong-ovate, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex discoid-annulate; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Forest margins on mountain slopes, waysides. Anhui, Jiangsu.</distribution>
</treatment>

