<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>123.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>planiscapa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Chun &amp; F. C. How</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 82. 1958</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>扁茎薹草 bian jing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 1 or 2 borne in a leaf axil, 8–18 cm tall, ca. 1 mm thick, compressed, soft and smooth. Leaves 2 × as long as culm or more, flat, 3.5–7 mm wide, soft, glabrous, scabrous on margins, with brown persistent sheaths. Involucral bracts sheathlike, blade scalelike. Spikes usually 1 or 2, androgynous, remote, cylindric, 5–10 mm, 2–3 mm thick; male part of spike 2 × as long as female part or more (rarely both parts equal), densely many flowered; female part few flowered; lateral spike usually borne from upper part of culm, peduncle short and compressed. Female glumes yellowish, broadly ovate or oblong, 1.5–2 mm, papery, green 1-costate and thinly few veined, margins narrowly membranous, apex obtuse. Utricles pale green, ovate-elliptic, compressed trigonous, 2–3 mm, papery, loosely pubescent on upper part, later glabrescent, 2-veined laterally and thinly few veined, base subrounded, margins ciliate, apex attenuate into an indistinct beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets dark brown at maturity, elliptic, trigonous, sides slightly concave, ca. 2 mm, base cuneate, nearly estipitate, apex attenuate, with a secund and short beak; style cylindric, brown granular-punctate, base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Sep–Dec.</description>
  <distribution>● On rocky mountain slopes in forests or grasslands at riversides; 1600–2800 m. Hainan (Wuzhi Shan).</distribution>
</treatment>

