<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>126.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chuana</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phyto tax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 167. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “chuiana” ].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>桂龄薹草 gui ling tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms brown, densely tufted, 10–20 cm tall, ca. 1 mm thick, slender, triquetrous, scabrous on angles, persistent sheathed at base. Involucral bracts leaflike, linear, blades ca. 1 mm wide, longer than subtending spike, sheathed. Spike single, rarely 2, androgynous, terminal spike ovoid, 5–8 mm, 4–6 mm wide, sometimes a lateral spike borne at base of culm, usually long pedunculate; male part of spike shorter than female part, densely few flowered; female part 3- or 4-flowered. Female glumes greenish, broadly ovate, 1.8–3 mm, membranous, several veined, apex acute and long awned. Utricle green, obliquely patent, longer than glume, obovate-elliptic, slightly inflated trigonous, ca. 5 mm, densely hispidulous, distinctly 2-veined laterally and thinly several veined, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish green at maturity, ovate, trigonous, 2.2–2.8 mm, base contracted into a slightly long stipe, apex not mucronate; style with a thickened, conic base, loosely pubescent; stigmas 3. Reduced rachilla sometimes present and setaceous. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>● Thickets or meadows on high mountains, Pinus forests or evergreen broad-leaved forests; 900–3000 m. S Sichuan (Yanbian), NW Yunnan.</distribution>
</treatment>

