<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>127.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>delavayi</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Philom. Paris, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8, 7: 29. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>年佳薹草 nian jia tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome ligneous, long and obliquely ascending. Culms loosely tufted, 10–30 cm tall, acutely triquetrous, slightly stiff, densely papillose, scabrous on angles, dark brown and persistent sheathed at base. Leaves longer than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat, scabrous on upper surface. Involucral bracts leaflike, linear, shorter than inflorescence, shortly sheathed. Spike single, terminal, or 2 or 3, lateral spikes borne at middle or lower part of culm, terminal spike broadly ovate or ovate-orbicular, 8–20 mm, 6–10 mm thick, lateral spikes rather small; peduncle filiform, rather long; male part of spike oblong-cylindric, densely several to many flowered; female part rather short, loosely 3–10-flowered. Female glumes stramineous laterally, green at middle, ovate or broadly ovate, ca. 4 mm, papery, 3-veined and thinly few veined, margins white hyaline, apex slightly recurved and long awned. Utricles brownish green, patent, slightly longer than glume, elliptic, ca. 5 mm, subleathery, glabrous, 2-veined laterally and thinly several veined, base attenuate, nearly estipitate, margins winged and ciliate, apex contracted into a short beak, orifice slightly patent 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish brown at maturity, broadly ovate, trigonous, slightly concave on sides, ca. 3.5 mm, base shortly stipitate or nearly estipitate, apex beakless; style base slightly thickened, conic; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>● Meadow thickets on high mountains, mixed forests, grasslands on gully sides; 1800–3700 m. SW Sichuan, NW Yunnan (Eryuan).</distribution>
</treatment>

