<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>131.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>caudispicata</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 170. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>尾穗薹草 wei sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome elongating. Culms loosely tufted, 10–30 cm tall, 1–1.5 mm thick, triquetrous, stiff, smooth. Leaves longer than or slightly shorter than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat, stiff, scabrous on both surfaces, dark brown and persistent sheathed. Involucral bracts linear, nearly equaling inflorescence, sheathed. Spikes 1 or 2(or 3), androgynous, oblong, 2–3 cm, ca. 5 mm thick; male part of spike slightly shorter than or equaling female part, both parts densely many flowered; lateral spike borne at middle of culm, with erect long peduncle. Female glumes pale green laterally, green at middle, ovate to broadly ovate, 4–4.5 mm, subleathery, 1-veined, margins white and narrowly membranous, apex acute. Utricles green, ovate, compressed trigonous, 5–5.5 mm, subleathery, loosely pubescent, then glabrescent, 2-veined laterally and thinly several veined, base cuneate, nearly estipitate, apex contracted into a short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets dark brown at maturity, obovate, compressed trigonous, 3–3.5 mm, base abruptly contracted to a short stipe, apex beakless; style base thickened, trigonous-conic, loosely pubescent; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>● Dry grasslands on mountain slopes, Pinus forests, rock crevices on ditch sides, on rocks in mixed forests; 1200–2800 m. C and SE Yunnan (Kunming, Yanshan).</distribution>
</treatment>

