<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>133.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pterocaulos</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hooker’s Icon. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>35: t. 3467. 1947</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>翅茎薹草 chi jing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slightly short. Culms tufted, 40–45 cm tall, 1.2–1.5 mm thick, stiff, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part of angles. Leaves longer than culm, flat, blades 10–11 mm wide, stiff, slightly scabrous on veins of lower surface and margins, glabrous, few sheaths brownish, persistent at base. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, shortly sheathed. Spikes single, terminal, sometimes 1 or 2 lateral spikes borne on middle or lower part of culm, remote, not well developed; terminal spike ovate, 2.5–3 cm, 8–10 mm thick; male part of spike slightly shorter than or equaling female part, oblong, densely many flowered; female part densely many flowered. Female glumes pale greenish laterally, green at middle, ovate or broadly ovate, 4.5–5.5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, thinly several veined on both sides, apex acute or acuminate. Utricles greenish, longer than glume, obovate-oblong, trigonous, 6–6.5 mm, thickly papery, several veined, pubescent on veins, base attenuate into a short stipe, margins densely hispidulous, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets brown at maturity, obovate-elliptic, trigonous, 4–4.5 mm, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex beakless; style base thickened, conic; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Oct–Nov.</description>
  <distribution>Forests in ravines; ca. 1200 m. SE Yunnan (Yanshan) [Myanmar].</distribution>
</treatment>

