<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>134.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>callitrichos</species_name>
    <species_authority>V. I. Kreczetowicz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Komarov, Fl. URSS</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 613. 1935</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>羊须草 yang xu cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome elongate, creeping or obliquely ascending. Culms loosely tufted, 2–6 cm tall, hair-shaped, obtusely trigonous, smooth; sheaths red-brown, persistent at base. Leaves 5–6 × as long as culm, blades 0.2–0.8(–1) mm wide, hair-shaped, soft, glabrous, rarely loosely pubescent. Involucral bracts spathelike, 7–10 mm, smooth, acute at apex, membranous on margins of sheath mouth, without distinct involucral bract blade. Spikes 2–4, remote; terminal spike male, cylindric, 5–8 mm, 1–1.5 mm thick, few flowered; lateral spikes 1–3, female, linear, 5–7 mm, loosely 1–3-flowered; peduncle short, usually not exserted from involucral bract sheath; rachis tortuous. Female glumes ferruginous or pale ferruginous laterally, green at middle, lanceolate, 3–4 mm, 1-veined, margins broadly white hyaline, apex acuminate or acute, mucronate. Utricles greenish, shorter than glume, obovate, obtusely trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, pubescent, distinctly 2-veined laterally and obscurely thinly several veined, base abruptly contracted to a bent and short stipe, apex rounded and very shortly beaked, orifice emarginate or truncate, usually brownish. Nutlets brown at maturity, oblong-obovate, trigonous, 2.3–2.5 mm, base contracted into a short stipe, apex rounded and shortly beaked; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Pinus forests, mixed forests, mountain slopes; 800–1000 m. Hebei, Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
  <discussion>The stems and leaves may be used for making paper and rope.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male spike few flowered, male glumes acute at apex, female spike 1–3-flowered</statement>
      <determination>134a. var. callitrichos</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Male spike 3- or 4-flowered, male glumes acuminate at apex, female spike 1- or 2-flowered</statement>
      <determination>134b. var. nana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

