<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>135.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>humilis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Leysser</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Halens.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>175. 1761</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>低矮薹草 di ai tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 2–5 cm tall, subcylindric, smooth, brown and persistent sheathed at base. Leaves 3–5 × as long as culm, flat, blades 1–2 mm wide, soft or slightly stiff, loosely pubescent. Involucral bracts reddish brown, spathelike, with broad white hyaline margins at sheath mouth, involucral bract blades setaceous. Spikes 2–5, remote; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 1–1.4 cm, ca. 2 mm thick, many flowered; lateral spikes 1 or 2, female, ovate or oblong, 5–7 mm, loosely 2–7-flowered; peduncles short, enclosed in sheath or lowermost one slightly exserted; rachis tortuous. Female glumes red-brown laterally, green at middle, ovate, ca. 4 mm, 1-veined, margins broadly white hyaline, base enclosing rachis, apex acute. Utricles greenish, slightly shorter than glume, obovate-oblong, trigonous, 3–3.2 mm, membranous, loosely ferruginous punctate, densely pubescent, 2-veined laterally, not distinctly thinly veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex subrounded and shortly beaked, beak purple-red, truncate at orifice. Nutlets dark brown at maturity, elliptic or obovate-oblong, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, base attenuate into a short stipe, apex with bent short beak; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Pinus or Xylosma forests, sunny places on mountain slopes, mountains near the sea; 100–1000 m. Anhui, Hebei, Liaoning, Shanxi [Japan, Russia; Europe].</distribution>
  <discussion>This species is cultivated in grasslands and used as feed for domestic animals.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves soft, 1–1.5 mm wide; spikes 2 or 3, female spikes 2–4-flowered</statement>
      <determination>135a. var. humilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves slightly stiff, ca. 2 mm wide; spikes 4 or 5, female spikes 4–7-flowered</statement>
      <determination>135b. var. scirrob asis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

