<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>137.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pseudohumilis</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Y. L. Chang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 172. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>似矮薹草 si ai tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 3–5 cm tall, slender, hair-shaped, triquetrous, smooth, brown and persistent sheathed at base. Leaves longer than or equaling culm, flat, blades 1.2–2 mm wide, slightly stiff, glabrous, scabrous on upper surface and margins, triquetrous and revolute at apex. Involucral bracts brown, spathelike, involucral bract blades awn-shaped and slightly scabrous. Spikes 2 or 3, basal one radicicolous, remaining spikes approximate; terminal spike male, obovate-oblong, 7–7.5 mm, 3–5-flowered; lateral spikes 1 or 2, female, oblong, 7–8 mm, ca. 3 mm thick, loosely 4–6-flowered; peduncles slender, hair-shaped, basal one 2.5–2.7 cm, upper rather short, ca. 10 mm, enclosed in involucral bract sheath; rachis tortuous. Female glumes brown laterally, green at middle, oblong, papery, 1-veined, margins white hyaline, apex subrounded, scabrous shortly awned. Utricles yellowish brown, narrowly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, densely pubescent, 2-veined laterally, not distinctly thinly veined, base attenuate into a stipe, apex attenuate into a short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish brown at maturity, narrowly elliptic, trigonous, 2.2–2.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex beakless; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>● Grasslands in valleys; ca. 3000 m. NW Yunnan (Lijiang).</distribution>
</treatment>

