<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>138.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>quadriflora</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Kükenthal) Ohwi</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Geobot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 74. 1932</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>四花薹草 si hua tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>digitata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <subspecies_name>quadriflora</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>Kükenthal</subspecies_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Engler, Pflanzenr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>38(IV. 20): 497. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>digitata</species_name>
    <variety_name>pallida</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Meinshausen.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, obliquely ascending. Culms densely tufted, lateral, 15–30 cm tall, not exceeding 1 mm thick, triquetrous, scabrous at upper part, purple-red sheathed at base. Leaves shorter than culm, nearly equaling culm after fruiting, blades 2–4 mm wide, soft, flat, smooth, purple-red and persistent sheathed. Involucral bracts red-brown, spathelike, membranous on margins, truncate at apex, involucral bract blade awn-shaped. Spikes 2 or 3, remote; terminal spike male, shorter than adjacent female spike, linear, 4.5–10 mm, 1–2 mm thick; lateral spikes 1 or 2, female, linear, 1–1.5 cm, 2–2.5 mm thick, loosely 2–4(–6)-flowered; peduncles filiform, 1–3 cm, soft; rachis tortuous. Female glumes ferruginous laterally, green at middle, obovate-oblong, ca. 3 mm, 1-veined, margins broadly white hyaline, apex rounded, mucronate. Utricles yellowish green, longer than glumes, obovate, obtusely trigonous, subplano-convex, 4–5 mm, loosely pubescent, 2-veined laterally, not distinctly thinly veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex rounded and shortly beaked, beak ferruginous, truncate at orifice. Nutlets pale ferruginous at maturity, obovate, trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, base contracted into a short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak; style short, base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Xylosma or Pinus forests; 800–1400 m. Hebei, Heilongjiang, Liaoning [Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

