<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>140.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>erythrobasis</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 240. 1908</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>红鞘薹草 hong qiao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>hallaisanensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>pedunculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Muhlenberg ex Willdenow</species_authority>
    <variety_name>erythrobasis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot) T. Koyama.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, lateral, 12–25 cm tall, slender, compressed triquetrous, slightly scabrous, with purple-red or dark purple and bladeless sheaths at base. Involucral bracts spathelike, involucral bract sheaths green and slightly purple-red or dark purple, lower involucral bracts with short blade, upper blades setaceous. Spikes 3 or 4, lowermost one remote, borne from base of culm, remaining spikes approximate; terminal spike male, usually taller than adjacent female spike, cylindric, 7–10 mm; lateral spikes female, oblong, 2–3 mm, loosely 10- or more flowered; peduncles slightly stiff, lowermost one rather long, others short, slightly exserted from involucral bract sheath. Female glume pale brown laterally, green at middle, oblong, 2.5–3 mm, 3-veined, membranous, apex rounded or truncate, with awn 0.8–1 mm. Utricles yellowish, slightly longer than glume, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 4 mm, papery, loosely pubescent, 2-veined laterally, base attenuate into a long stipe, apex contracted into a short beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets yellowish, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, base stipitate, apex contracted into a short beak; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Broad-leaved or Pinus koraiensis forests; 200–800 m. S Jilin (Changbai Shan) [Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

