<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>141.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>yuexiensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>S. W. Su &amp; S. M. Xu</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Bot. Res., Harbin</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8(3): 78. 1988</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>岳西薹草 yue xi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 20–35 cm tall, triquetrous, slightly scabrous. Leaves nearly equaling culm, linear, blades 0.5–1.5 mm wide, soft, smooth, yellow-brown and persistent sheathed at base. Involucral bracts spathelike, yellowish abaxially, white and hyaline adaxially, with setaceous involucral bract blade. Spikes 3 or 4, lowermost one remote, others approximate; terminal spike male, oblong, ca. 1 cm, not exceeding or slightly exceeding adjacent female spike; lateral spikes 2 or 3, female, uppermost one approximate to male spike, oblong, 1–1.5 cm, 3.5–4 mm thick, loosely several flowered; peduncles slightly scabrous, only lowermost one exserted from sheath, others enclosed in sheath. Female glumes yellowish brown laterally, green at middle, oblong, ca. 5 mm, 1-veined, margins white membranous, apex rounded, mucronate. Utricles yellowish green, shorter than glume, obovate-oblong, ca. 3.2 mm, papery, densely pubescent, 2-veined laterally and thinly several veined, base attenuate into a short stipe, apex contracted into a short beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets obovate-oblong, ca. 2.5 mm, base attenuate, nearly estipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a long beak exserted from utricle; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Mountain slopes, roadsides. SW Anhui (Taihu, Yuexi).</distribution>
</treatment>

