<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>145.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>capilliculmis</species_name>
    <species_authority>S. R. Zhang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 498. 2005</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>丝秆薹草 si gan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>filamentosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>K. T. Fu</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Tsinling.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(1 ): 445. 1976,</place_in_publication>
      <other_info>not Petrie (1916).</other_info>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long and thick, obliquely ascending. Culms loosely tufted, 15–20 cm tall, slender, filiform, obtusely trigonous, scabrous on angles. Leaves shorter than culm, elongate after flowering, flat, blades 1–2.5 mm wide, soft, sheaths dark brown, persistent. Involucral bracts spathelike, involucral bract sheaths long, with short blade. Spikes 2 or 3, lowermost one remote or nearly borne at base of culm, others approximate; terminal spike male, linear, 7–10 mm, 1.5–2 mm thick, few flowered; lateral spikes 1 or 2, female, oblong or narrowly oblong, 7–10 mm, 2–3 mm thick, loosely few flowered; peduncles slender, filiform, long exserted from involucral bract sheath; rachis straight or tortuous. Female glumes purple-brown laterally, green at middle, ovate-oblong, 3–3.8 mm, papery, 1-veined, scabrous on vein, margins white hyaline, apex acute, mucronate. Utricles pale greenish, slightly longer than glume, obovate-oblong, obtusely trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, papery, densely pubescent, 2-veined laterally, not thinly veined, base contracted into an incurved long stipe, apex abruptly contracted into an indistinctly recurved, short beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets brown at maturity, obovate-oblong, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, base attenuate, stipitate, apex rounded with a recurved short beak; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>● Picea and Abies forests, thickets, alpine meadows; 1100–4300 m. S Gansu, E Qinghai, Shaanxi (Taibai Shan), SW and W Sichuan, NW Yunnan.</distribution>
</treatment>

