<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>148.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>macrosandra</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Franchet) V. I. Kreczetowicz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mat er. Gerb. Bot. Inst. Komarova Akad. Nauk S.S.S.R.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 189. 1946</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>大雄薹草 da xiong tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>lanceolata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <variety_name>macrosandra</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Franchet</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nouv. Arch. Mus. Hist. Nat., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3, 9: 169. 1897</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>pediformis</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Mey er</species_authority>
    <variety_name>macrosandra</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Franchet) C. B. Clarke.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome ligneous. Culms densely tufted, 30–80 cm tall, triquetrous, 1–1.5 mm thick. Leaves slightly shorter than or equaling culm, flat, blades 3–5 mm wide, rigid, stiff, scabridulous on both surfaces, slightly revolute on margins, base attenuate into a stipe; stipe stiff, rigid, glabrous; sheaths brown, persistent, eventually disintegrating into fibers. Involucral bracts brown-red, spathelike, obliquely truncate at mouth of involucral bract sheath, without involucral bract leaf. Spikes 4–7, rather remote; terminal spike male, cylindric, 4–8 cm, 3–4 mm thick, densely many flowered, peduncle 4–5 cm, taller than adjacent female spike; lateral spikes female, linear-cylindric, 2.5–3.5 cm, ca. 3 mm thick, densely many flowered, peduncles slender, rather long exserted from involucral bract sheath. Male glumes 8–8.5 mm, apex truncate; female glumes brown or brown-red laterally, green at middle, oblong, 3.5–3.8 mm, hispidulous on upper part, 1-veined, scabrous on vein, margins broadly white hyaline, apex rounded, mucronate. Utricles green, obovate-oblong, obtusely trigonous, 2.5–3.1 mm, thickly papery, densely hispidulous, not distinctly veined laterally, thinly several veined, base attenuate into a curved stipe, apex contracted into a curved short beak, orifice truncate. Nutlets brown at maturity, obovate-oblong or obovate, trigonous, 1.8–2 mm; style erect or bent, base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Mar–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Sunny mountain slopes; 700–1000 m. Hubei (Yichang), Sichuan.</distribution>
</treatment>

