<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>149.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>shuchengensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>S. W. Su &amp; Q. Zhang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phyto tax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>27: 465. 1989</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>舒城薹草 shu cheng tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome ligneous, obliquely ascending. Culms 30–45 cm tall, 2–2.5 mm thick, obtusely trigonous, smooth. Leaves longer than culm, flat, blades 6–10 mm wide, stiff, rigid, margins scabrous; basal sheaths dark brown, persistent, usually disintegrating into fibers. Involucral bracts red-brown, spathelike, margins white hyaline, apex acute, without distinct involucral bract leaf. Spikes 5 or 6, remote; terminal spike male, clavate, 7–8 cm, 5–7 mm thick, densely many flowered, peduncle rather long, taller than adjacent female spike; lateral spikes 4 or 5, female, cylindric, 3.5–5 cm, ca. 5 mm thick, densely many flowered, laxly several flowered at base, peduncles usually not exserted or slightly exserted from involucral bract sheath at lower part. Female glumes red-brown laterally, green at middle, narrowly oblong, 4–4.5 mm, papery, 3-veined, margins broadly white hyaline, apex acute. Utricles yellowish green, shorter than glume, elliptic, obtusely trigonous, ca. 3 mm, laxly pubescent, 2-veined laterally and thinly several veined, base attenuate into a short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets obovate-oblong, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base gradually narrowed, shortly stipitate, apex rounded and tortuously beaked; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Shady places at forest margins on mountain slopes. Anhui (Shucheng).</distribution>
</treatment>

