<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>150.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>shaanxiensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Tang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 174. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>陕西薹草 shan xi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 30–35 cm tall, rather slender, ca. 1.5 mm thick, soft, smooth. Leaves shorter than culm, flat, blades 1–2 mm wide, soft, brownish and persistent sheathed at base. Involucral bracts spathelike, greenish sheathed, with involucral bract leaf at apex. Spikes 3 or 4, lowermost one remote or nearly basal, others approximate; terminal spike male, cylindric, 1.4–1.6 cm, ca. 2 mm thick, densely many flowered, sometimes with 1–3 female flowers at base; lateral spikes female, linear-cylindric, 1.7–3 cm, ca. 2 mm thick, sometimes 1–3-branched at base with branches arising from flowered utriculiform cladoprophylls, sometimes with a few male flowers at apex; peduncles filiform, very long exserted from involucral bract sheath. Female glumes brownish laterally, green at middle, oblong, ca. 2 mm, papery, 3-veined, margins narrowly white hyaline, apex truncate or emarginate, mucronate. Utricles greenish, equaling or slightly longer than glume, narrowly elliptic, obtusely trigonous, 2–2.5 mm, papery, densely pubescent, 2-veined laterally, not thinly veined, base gradually narrowed to a short stipe, apex attenuate into a short beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets brown at maturity, narrowly elliptic, 1.8–2 mm, trigonous; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>● Grasslands on mountain slopes, wet places in valleys; 2800–3200 m. S Gansu, Shaanxi (Taibai Shan).</distribution>
</treatment>

