<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>153.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>huolushanensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Bot. Yunnan.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 145. 1990</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>火炉山薹草 huo lu shan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stout, stoloniferous. Culms densely tufted, 15–40 cm tall, ca. 1.5 mm thick, slender, obtusely trigonous. Leaves shorter than culm, flat, blades 1–3 mm wide, soft, margins scabrous, base dark brown and persistent sheathed. Involucral bracts spathelike, sheaths brownish, with linear involucral bract leaf at apex. Spikes 3 or 4; terminal spike male, cylindric, 2–2.5 cm, ca. 3 mm thick, densely many flowered, peduncle slender, 3.5–4 cm, taller than adjacent female spike; lateral spikes 2 or 3, female, remote, cylindric, 1–4 cm, 2–3 mm thick, many flowered, loosely several flowered at lower part, densely many flowered at upper part, peduncles slender, soft, rather long exserted from involucral bract sheath. Female glumes dark purple-brown laterally, green at middle, oblong, 4–5 mm, papery, scabrous abaxially, 3-veined, margins broadly white hyaline, apex truncate or emarginate, mucronate. Utricles greenish, shorter than glume, oblong or obovate-oblong, obtusely trigonous, ca. 4 mm, 2-veined laterally and not thinly veined, hispidulous on veins and margins, base gradually narrowed to a stipe, apex contracted into a short beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets brownish at maturity, obovate-oblong, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, base nearly estipitate, apex rounded; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Thickets on high mountains; 3900–4000 m. SW Sichuan (Yanyuan).</distribution>
</treatment>

