<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>157.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>obovatosquamata</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. T. Wang &amp; Y. L. Chang ex P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 175. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>倒卵鳞薹草 dao luan lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 20–40 cm tall, ca. 1 mm thick, slender, triquetrous, smooth. Leaves slightly shorter than or equaling culm, flat, soft, smooth, blades 1.3–2.2 mm wide, plicate at upper part, linear, dark brown and persistent sheathed at base. Involucral bracts spathelike, sheaths long, involucral bract leafy at apex, linear, longer than peduncle. Spikes 3 or 4, remote, lowermost one basal; terminal spike male, cylindric, 1.5–2.5 cm, ca. 3 mm thick, densely many flowered; lateral spikes 2–4, female, cylindric, 2–3 cm, ca. 3.5 mm thick, densely many flowered; peduncles slender, filiform, soft, very long exserted from involucral bract sheath. Female glumes dark purple-brown, green at middle, obovate-oblong or oblong, 3.5–4.8 mm, papery, 3-veined, narrowly white hyaline margined at upper part, apex subrounded, mucronate. Utricles green, slightly longer than glume, obovate-oblong, obtusely trigonous, 4.2–5 mm, papery, densely white pubescent, indistinctly 2-veined laterally, not thinly veined, base gradually narrowed to a short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice obliquely split, 2-toothed. Nutlets brown at maturity, obovate-oblong, trigonous, 2.5–3.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex nearly beakless; style erect or slightly bent, base inflated; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>● Thickets or meadows on high mountains, grasslands at Abies forest margins; 3400–4300 m. E Xizang, NW Yunnan (Dêqên).</distribution>
</treatment>

