<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>160.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>lanceolata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Narr. Exped. China Japan,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>326. 1857</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>大披针薹草 da pi zhen tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stout, obliquely ascending. Culms densely tufted, 10–35 cm tall, ca. 1.5 mm thick, slender, compressed triquetrous, scabrous on upper part. Leaves shorter than culm when young, eventually elongating, equaling or longer than culm, blades 1–2.5 mm wide, flat, soft, margins slightly scabrous, base purple-brown and persistent sheathed, sheaths eventually disintegrating into fibers. Involucral bracts spathelike, sheath green and brownish lined, brownish abaxially, white and membranous at sheath mouth and adaxially, lower 1 or 2 involucral bract blades setaceous, remaining blades mucro-shaped. Spikes 3–6, remote; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 5–15 mm, 1.5–2 mm thick, shorter than or equaling adjacent female spike; lateral spikes 2–5, female, oblong or oblong-cylindric, 1–1.7 cm, 2.5–3 mm thick, loosely or subdensely 5–10-flowered, or loosely 2- or 3-flowered; peduncles usually not exserted from involucral bract sheath, lowermost one slightly exserted; rachis slightly or distinctly flexuose. Female glumes purple-brown laterally, green at middle, lanceolate, obovate-lanceolate, obovate, or obovate-oblong, 5–6 mm, papery, 3-veined, margins broadly white hyaline, apex acute, mucronate. Utricles greenish, shorter than glume, obovate-oblong, obtusely trigonous, ca. 3 mm, papery, densely pubescent, 2-veined laterally and convexly several veined, base abruptly contracted into a long stipe, apex rounded, shortly beaked, orifice truncate. Nutlets obovate-elliptic, trigonous, 2.5–2.8 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex with recurved and short beak; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, grasslands at forest margins, dry grasslands on sunny slopes, mountain slopes, thickets, watersides, field margins, on rocks; 100–2300 m. Anhui, Gansu, Guizhou, Hebei, Heilongjiang, Henan, Hubei, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol, Ningxia, Shaanxi, Shandong, Shanxi, Sichuan, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea, Mongolia, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms shorter than 10–35 cm tall; female spikes only loosely 2- or 3-flowered; rachis dist inctly flexuose</statement>
      <determination>160c. var. laxa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms 10–35 cm tall; female spikes loosely or slightly densely 5–10-flowered; rachis slightly flexuose.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes lanceolate or obovate-lanceolate; utricles 2-veined later ally and convexly several veined</statement>
      <determination>160a. var. lanceolata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes obovate or obovate-oblong; utricles only 2-veined laterally</statement>
      <determination>160b. var. subpediformis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

