<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>162.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>infossa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Z. P. Wang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Nanjing Univ., Nat. Sci. Ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1962(2): 52. 1962</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>隐匿薹草 yin ni tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms up to 30 cm tall, slender, triquetrous, shortly bracteate or bractless sheathed at base, sheaths dark purple, sometimes disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 2.5–3 mm wide, soft, both surfaces or abaxial side scabrous. Involucral bract leaflike, longer than spike, shortly sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4; terminal spike male, lower than or surpassing adjacent female spike, narrowly obovate or sublinear, ca. 5 mm, shortly pedunculate, lower spikes remote; lateral spikes female, oblong, 0.8–2 cm, laxly 3- or 4-flowered, rarely 5- or 6-flowered, slightly long pedunculate. Female glumes pale, greenish at middle, oblong or oblong-ovate, ca. 3.5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex mucronate or shortly awned. Utricles gray-green, nearly erect, longer than glume, elliptic or obovate-elliptic, trigonous, 5–6 mm, brown punctate, pubescent, 2-veined laterally and indistinctly thinly several veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe and apex into a short or long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets broadly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 3.5 mm, base with tortuous stipe, apex concave; style short, base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>● Mountain slopes, forests, gully sides. Anhui, Jiangsu.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Terminal male spike rather short, lower than adjacent female spike, lowermost female spike not basal; utricles shortly beaked at apex</statement>
      <determination>162a. var. infossa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

