<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>163.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>alba</species_name>
    <species_authority>Scopoli</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Carniol., ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 2: 216. 1772</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>白鳞薹草 bai lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous. Culms tufted, 15–30 cm tall, rather slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth; sheaths leafless at base. Leaves rather shorter than culm, blades flat, ca. 1 mm wide, eventually involute on margins, soft, brown sheathed at base. Involucral bracts brown-green, sheathlike, ca. 1 cm, hyaline on margins, without involucral bract leaf. Spikes usually 3, rarely 2 or 4, slightly approximate; terminal spike male, usually not surpassing adjacent female spike, linear, 1–1.5 cm; lateral spikes usually 2, rarely 1 or 3, female, oblong or subovate, 5–10 mm, loosely 2–6-flowered, peduncles slender. Female glumes stramineous or yellow-brownish, broadly ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, not hyaline margined, green 1-veined, apex acute. Utricles yellow-green, brownish yellow at maturity, obliquely patent, slightly longer than glume, broadly obovate or elliptic-obovate, obtusely trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, leathery, glabrous, shiny, several slightly concave veined, base obtusely rounded, margins hyaline, apex contracted into a short beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets dark brown, tightly enveloped in utricle, obovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, brownish yellow and slightly convex on angles, tuberculate on surface; style base thickened and globose; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>On rocks of mountain slopes, sandy areas, swamps. Xinjiang [Russia; WC Europe].</distribution>
</treatment>

