<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>164.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>ussuriensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Komarov</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trudy Imp. S.-Peterburgsk. Bot. Sada</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 443. 1901</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>乌苏里薹草 wu su li tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>alba</species_name>
    <species_authority>Scopoli</species_authority>
    <subspecies_name>ussuriensis</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>(Komarov) Küken thal.</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous, stolons slender. Culms loosely tufted, 20–40 cm tall, obtusely trigonous, smooth, bladeless sheathed at base. Leaves nearly equaling height of culm, blades ca. 0.5 mm wide, slightly revolute on margins, slightly soft, yellow-brown sheathed. Involucral bracts sheathlike, up to 2 cm, broadly membranous on margin of sheathing mouth, without involucral bract leaf. Spikes 2 or 3, slightly remote; terminal spike male, usually surpassing adjacent female spike, lanceolate-linear, 1–2 cm; lateral spikes female, oblong, 0.5–1 cm, very loosely 2–4-flowered; rachis flexuose; peduncles slender, up to 3 cm. Female glumes yellowish, ovate or subelliptic, ca. 3 mm, membranous, 1-veined, basal part enclosing rachis, margins broadly hyaline, apex hard mucronate. Utricles yellow-green, dark brown at maturity, suberect, nearly equaling glume, obovate, indistinctly trigonous, ca. 3 mm, subleathery, not shiny, glabrous, several slightly concave veined, base broadly truncate or subrounded, apex abruptly narrowed to a short beak, orifice truncate. Nutlets rather tightly enveloped in utricle, obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3, slender. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Needle-leaved forests, shady and wet places. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol, Shaanxi [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

