<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>167.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>vaginata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Tausch</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 557. 1821</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>少花薹草 shao hua tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender stoloniferous. Culms 20–50 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, leafy at lower part. Leaves much shorter than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide or wider, flat, slightly soft; sheaths brown, sometimes purplish red. Involucral bracts with long sheath and rather short blade. Spikes 2–4, usually 3, rather remote; terminal spike male, subclavate, 1–1.5 cm; lateral spikes female, oblong-cylindric or oblong, 1–2.5 cm, loosely several flowered; peduncles long and erect. Female glumes ferruginous-brown, broadly ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, green 3-veined, margins hyaline, apex obtuse or acute. Utricles yellow-green, obliquely patent, longer than glume, ovate, inflated trigonous, 4–6 mm, subleathery, glabrous, indistinctly veined, base broadly cuneate, apex abruptly narrowed into a short or medium-sized beak, orifice emarginate or 2-toothed. Nutlets rather loosely enveloped in utricle, obovate, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, base shortly stipitate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, thickets, grasslands, grassland margins. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Mongolia, Russia; Europe].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 3–5 mm wide; utricles ca. 4 mm</statement>
      <determination>167a. var. vaginata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades much wider; utricles 5–6 mm</statement>
      <determination>167b. var. petersii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

