<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>168.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>siderosticta</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hance</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 89. 1873</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>宽叶薹草 kuan ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome elongate. Flowering culms and vegetative culms spaced; flowering culms clothed by bladeless sheaths at base, pale brown, without leaves. Leaf blades of vegetative culms oblong-lanceolate, 10–20 × 1–2.5 cm, sometimes with white stripes, midvein and 2 lateral veins rather distinct, sometimes ciliate, glabrous adaxially, sparsely pilose on veins abaxially or on both surfaces. Flowering culms up to 30 cm tall; involucral bract sheaths inflated above and spathelike, 2–2.5 cm, with blade 5–10 mm. Spikes 3–6(–10), single or binate at each node, androgynous, or terminal spike usually male, linear-cylindric, 1.5–3 cm, loosely flowered; peduncles 2–6 cm, usually exserted. Female glumes elliptic-oblong to lanceolate-oblong, 4–5 mm, hyaline-membranous laterally, sparsely rusty punctate, green costa 3-veined, apex obtuse. Utricles obovate or elliptic, trigonous, 3–4 mm, glabrous or pilose, slenderly and prominently many veined, base attenuate into a very short stipe, apex contracted into a short beak or beakless, orifice truncate. Nutlet tightly enveloped, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style persistent, base not thickened, slightly exserted from utricle; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Needle-leaved and broad-leaved mixed forests and forest margins or broad-leaved forests, rather dry grasslands; 1000–2000 m. Anhui, Hebei, Heilongjiang, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Jilin, Liaoning, Shaanxi, Shandong, Shanxi, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricle glabrous; leaf blade margin glabrous</statement>
      <determination>168a. var. siderosticta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricle pilose; leaf blade margin ciliate</statement>
      <determination>168b. var. pilosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

