<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>174.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>glossostigma</species_name>
    <species_authority>Handel-Mazzetti</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Anz. Akad. Wiss. Wien, Math.-Naturwiss. Kl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>59: 140. 1922</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>长梗薹草 chang geng tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>dayunshanensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Ling &amp; Y. Z. Huang</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>exerta</species_name>
    <species_authority>K. L. Chu</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>ferruspiculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>K. L. Chu</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>mandarinorum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Raymond.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather stout and elongate. Flowering and vegetative culms spaced; sub-basal sheaths of flowering culms bladeless; blades of vegetative culms leathery to papery, broadly linear, 20–40 × 1–2.5 cm, glabrous or pilose on veins of both surfaces or abaxially, midvein and 2 lateral veins prominent. Flowering culms 30–40 cm tall, with spikes at nodes of upper 2/3 of culm; involucral bract sheaths inflated above and spathelike, glabrous or shortly pilose, blades much shorter to ca. 1/2 length of sheath, ligule indistinct. Spikes androgynous, single to 5-nate at each node, linear-cylindric, 2–3 cm, pedunculate; peduncle 2–15 cm, slender, often exserted; male part 1/4–1/2 length of spike, mostly distinctly shorter than female part, rather densely flowered; female part with 8–15 flowers, utricles sparse at maturity. Female glumes pale brown, ovate-elliptic, ca. 2.5 mm, rusty punctate, midvein distinct, many lateral veins indistinct, apex obtuse. Utricles slightly longer than glume, ovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, prominently many veined, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, beak bent downward, 1/8–1/4 length of utricle, subtruncate at orifice. Nutlet tightly enveloped, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Wet and shady places in forests; 800–1500 m. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hunan, Jiangxi, Zhejiang.</distribution>
</treatment>

