<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>181.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>urelytra</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Jap. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 204. 1934</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>扁果薹草 bian guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, rigid, 20–60 cm tall, trigonous, subsmooth, occasionally 1-leaved at middle, clothed at base with purple or dark brown sheaths disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 3–5 mm wide, flattish or with ± revolute margins, with purple-brown veins. Lower involucral bracts equaling or shorter than subtending spike, long sheathing, upper involucral bracts shortly sheathing, blades setaceous. Spikes 7–10 at 5–7 nodes, middle ones 2- or 3-nate, rarely 4-nate, upper ones ± contiguous, lower one spaced, all androgynous, with male part 1/3–2/5 length of spike, cylindric to oblong-cylindric, 2–5 cm, male part 1–2 mm wide, female part 3–4 mm wide, densely many flowered, peduncles exserted. Female glumes yellow-brown, ovate to lanceolate-ovate, 3–4 mm (excluding awn), membranous, margins pale hyaline, 1-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous awn 1–3 mm, apex acute. Utricles erect, yellowish green with brown flecks or turning brown, longer than glume, lanceolate, flattened trigonous, 6–7 mm, thinly membranous, sparsely puberulent, faintly veined, base contracted, upper margins serrulate, apex gradually tapering into a beak, orifice deeply 2-lobed. Nutlets elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, base stipitate; stigmas 3, persistent.</description>
  <distribution>● Forest floors on high mountains. Taiwan.</distribution>
  <discussion>No specimens have been seen by the present authors.</discussion>
</treatment>

