<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>185.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>perakensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. D. Hooker, Fl. Brit. India</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 720. 1894</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>霹雳薹草 pi li tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>dunnii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>prainii</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke (1904)</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <other_info>not Kükenthal (1903)</other_info>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>setulifolia</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>tatewakiana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>tonkinensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stout, woody. Culms central, 30–120 cm tall, ca. 2 mm thick near base, trigonous, with several nodes, clothed at base with shortly bladed or bladeless dark purple-red sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves basal or cauline, some overtopping culm, blades broadly linear, 4–12 mm wide, stiff, flattish, leathery; cauline leaves rather long, sheathing, dark brown, membranous, pale greenish and black-brown veined abaxially. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, long sheathing, upper involucral bracts glumelike. Inflorescence an interrupted panicle, 30–40 cm, with 3–6 partial panicles, partial panicles 2–5 cm, lower ones single or binate, upper ones binate or occasionally ternate, each bearing 3–7 sessile spikes, lower ones with long peduncles; spikes bisexual, androgynous, lanceolate or oblong-lanceolate, 1.5–3 cm, male part 1/3–1/2 length of spike. Female glumes pale or slightly brown, broadly ovate to oblong, 2.2–4.5 mm, membranous, 1-veined costa excurrent into a short awn 1–1.5 mm, apex acute to subobtuse. Utricles longer than glume, obovate-elliptic or ovate-fusiform, trigonous, 4.5–6 mm, herbaceous, hispidulous above, many veined, gradually tapering at both ends, beak conic, 1–2 mm, hispidulous or glabrescent, obliquely truncate at hardly 2-toothed orifice. Nutlets dark brown, tightly enveloped, obovate-elliptic, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, faces concave; style erect, sparsely hispidulous, base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>Shady and moist places in forests; 700–1800 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan, Sichuan, Taiwan, Yunnan [Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

