<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>186.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>morii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon. Pl. Formosan.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 135. 1916</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>森氏薹草 sen shi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms 70–120 cm tall, acutely trigonous, several nodose, smooth, clothed at base with brown or chestnut-brown sheaths ± disintegrating into fibers. Leaves basal and a few upper spaced on culm, usually shorter than culm, blades broadly linear, 4–9 mm wide, flattish, leathery. Involucral bracts leaflike, lower 2 overtopping inflorescence, remaining bracts much shorter, lower involucral bract sheaths 3–5 cm. Inflorescence paniculate, interrupted, with 3–6 partial panicles, partial panicles binate or ternate, 3–9 cm, some further branched, bearing 3–14 spikes; peduncles exserted; spikes androgynous, oblong or ovate-oblong, 1–2 cm, male part shorter than female part, subdensely flowered, sessile or shortly pedunculate. Female glumes light brown, ovate to ovate-elliptic, 2.8–3 mm, thinly membranous, margins broadly whitish, faintly many veined, green 3-veined costa projecting beyond apex forming a short mucro, apex acute. Utricles pale brownish, longer than glume, suberect, fusiform, lanceolate-elliptic, compressed trigonous, 4.5–6.5 mm, herbaceous, hispidulous on upper 1/2–2/3, finely many veined, attenuate at both ends, beak ca. 1 mm, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, rhomboid-elliptic, trigonous, 3.5–4 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Tropical forests; 500–1000 m. Taiwan.</distribution>
  <discussion>No specimens have been seen by the present authors.</discussion>
</treatment>

