<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>204.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chrysolepis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet &amp; Savatier</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl. Jap.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 571. 1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>黄花薹草 huang hua tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chrysolepis</species_name>
    <variety_name>odontostoma</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Kükenthal) Ohwi</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>gokwanensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>odontostoma</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, stolons elongate. Culms subloosely tufted, 10–35 cm tall, slender, erect or ± curved, subsmooth, clothed at base with yellow-brown to dark brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades linear, 1.5–3 mm wide, flattish or slightly curved. Lower involucral bracts with sheaths 1–1.5 cm, lowest with a setaceous blade, upper glumelike. Spikes 2–5, upper ones close together, lower 2 or 3 somewhat distant, erect, with long peduncles; terminal spike male, linear-clavate, 10–30 × ca. 5 mm; lateral spikes female, linear-cylindric, 1–3 × 0.5–0.8 cm, subloosely to subdensely many flowered, mostly with short peduncles enclosed in involucral bract sheaths. Female glumes reddish or purplish brown, ovate-lanceolate or obovate, somewhat shiny, upper margins ciliate, green 1-veined costa ending in a mucro, apex acute. Utricles stained with reddish brown above, longer than glume, erect to erect-patent, ovate-lanceolate, compressed trigonous, 4–7 mm, faintly veined, wholly pubescent, margins subdensely hispidulous, beak rather long, deeply lobed at orifice. Nutlets tightly enveloped, elliptic-oblong; style beaklike, base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Rather dry grasslands in forests. Taiwan [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

