<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>208.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>brachyathera</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Jap. J. Bot .</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 190. 1934</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>垂穗薹草 chui sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody, rather thick, usually stoloniferous. Culms loosely tufted, 30–60 cm tall, slender, trigonous, scabrous above, clothed at base with brown or dark brown sheaths ± disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 1.5–2.5 mm wide, slightly stiff, flattish or flattish plicate. Lowest involucral bract leaflike, shorter than spike, sheathing 3–5 cm, upper ones setaceous. Spikes 3–5, upper spikes contiguous to closely contiguous, suberect, lowest one very remote and pendent on long exserted, filiform peduncle; terminal spike male or rarely with a few female flowers at base, clavate to linear-clavate, 2–3 cm; lateral spikes female, narrowly cylindric, 2.5–4.5 × ca. 0.5 cm, sublaxly many flowered, peduncles exserted, filiform. Female glumes deep chestnut-brown with pale upper margin, oblong, thinly herbaceous, greenish 1-veined costa forming a straight scabrous awn ca. 1 mm, apex truncate or shallowly emarginate. Utricles slightly longer than glume, erect, ovate-fusiform, trigonous, 4.5–5 mm, membranous, densely hispid except at very base, nearly nerveless except for 2 costas on edges, gradually attenuate at both ends, base shortly stipitate, apex rather long beaked, orifice obliquely truncate, 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, ovate-elliptic, compressed trigonous, 2–2.5 mm, base shortly stipitate; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Sandy grasslands at high elevations. Taiwan.</distribution>
</treatment>

