<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>211.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>setosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ill. Gen. Carex</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 108. 1862</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>刺毛薹草 ci mao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome elongate or rarely short, oblique. Culms 15–45 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, clothed at base with brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades greenish, linear, 2–4 mm wide, slightly stiff, margins scabrous. Involucral bracts setaceous, sheathing for 1–2 cm, or spathaceous. Spikes 3–7; terminal spike male, cylindric, 3–4 × ca. 0.4 cm, slightly laxly flowered; peduncles slender, 2.5–5.5(–13) cm, scabrous above. Female glumes ferruginous, oblong, 3–3.5 mm, scabrous adaxially, margins very narrowly white hyaline, green 1-veined costa excurrent into a short mucro, apex subrounded or emarginate. Utricles stramineous-green or ferruginous above, equaling glume, narrowly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 4 mm, hirsute, ferruginous punctate or not, base gradually attenuate into a short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a beak, orifice obliquely truncate, 2-toothed. Nutlets stramineous, tightly enveloped, oblong or obovate, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, base shortly stipitate; style erect, base slightly thickened or not; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Subalpine meadows in thickets, grassy areas on mountaintops, sandy areas at streamsides of hills; 1400–3700 m. Gansu, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hunan, Qinghai, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Xizang, Yunnan [Bhutan, India (Sikkim), Kashmir, Nepal].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles ferruginous punctate</statement>
      <determination>211b. var. punctata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles not ferruginous punctate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucral bracts setaceous</statement>
      <determination>211a. var. setosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucral bracts spathaceous</statement>
      <determination>211c. var. mianxianica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

