<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>214.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>fulvorubescens</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Coll. Sci. Imp. Univ. Tokyo</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>30: 283. 1911</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>茶色薹草 cha se tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms 10–35 cm tall, erect, trigonous, scabrous, clothed at base with purple-brown sheaths eventually disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades linear, 1.5–5 mm wide, flattish plicate, ± stiff. Lower involucral bracts setaceous, sheathing, upper involucral bracts glumelike, sheathless. Spikes 4–9, subfastigiate; terminal spike male, rarely gynaecandrous, linear or linear-cylindric, 1–12 cm; lateral spikes female or androgynous, linear, 1–10 cm, subdensely many flowered. Female glumes dark brown or golden brown, lanceolate-ovate, 2–5 mm, membranous, upper margins ciliate, apex acute. Utricles longer than glume, erect, linear-oblong or lanceolate, compressed trigonous, 4–8 mm, membranous, sparsely pubescent, ciliate on margins, finely many veined, base gradually attenuate into a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed to a long curved beak, orifice deeply 2-toothed. Nutlets ovate-oblong, ca. 1.5 mm, base with a long, filiform stipe 2–3 mm; style slender, base not markedly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Sandy or rocky slopes in montane regions. Taiwan.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves rather narrow, 1.5–3 mm wide; male spike 2–4 cm, female spikes 1–3 cm; female glumes dark brown</statement>
      <determination>214a. subsp. fulvorubescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves rather broad, 3–5 mm wide; male spike up to 12 cm, female spikes up to 10 cm; female glumes golden brown</statement>
      <determination>214b. subsp. longistipes</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

