<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>215.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>makinoensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Philom. Paris, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8, 7: 47. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>牧野薹草 mu ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>shimadae</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>shimadae</species_name>
    <variety_name>longibracteata</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Hayata</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>warburgiana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 20–80 cm tall, slender, trigonous, rigid, subsmooth but scabrous below inflorescence, clothed at base with dark brown or purple-brown sheaths eventually disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades linear, 2–5 mm wide, ± stiff, plicate. Lowest involucral bract with a leaflike blade, remaining bracts nearly bladeless or with a short setaceous blade. Spikes 3–7, upper spikes approximate, lower 2 or 3 distant; terminal spike male, purple-brown, linear-cylindric, 4–10 × ca. 0.25 cm; lateral spikes female or androgynous, cylindric or linear-cylindric, 3–7 × 0.4–0.6 cm, subloosely many flowered, erect, with rather short mostly enclosed peduncle. Female glumes dark brown to chestnut-brown, sometimes light brown, ovate or ovate-oblong, membranous, upper margins ciliate, pale 3-veined costa forming a mucro at apex, apex acute. Utricles longer than glume, lanceolate, compressed trigonous, suberect, 4–6 mm, membranous, sparsely hirsute on upper half, finely many veined, apical beak short, orifice sharply 2-lobed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, elliptic or oblong, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, contracted at both ends, base stipitate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands on low mountains or near the seacoast. Taiwan [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

