<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>221.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>graminiculmis</species_name>
    <species_authority>T. Koyama</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Jap. J. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 170. 1956</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>禾秆薹草 he gan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, woody, with 1 or 2 rather long stolons, brown. Culms 60–70 cm tall, erect, rigid, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, clothed at base with brown-yellow sheaths disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves ca. 1/2 length of culm, blades linear, 1.5–5 mm wide, flattish, revolute, margins scabrous, apex long acuminate. Basal involucral bracts leaflike, slightly shorter than or equaling inflorescence, shortly sheathing, 1.5–2.5 cm, remaining bracts setaceous, very shortly sheathing. Spikes 9–21, approximate, subfastigiate, disposed in a panicle, rarely spicate; upper 7–11 spikes male, castaneous-red, sessile or sometimes lower 1 or 2 slightly shortly pedunculate; terminal spike oblong-elliptic, 15–20 × 3–9 mm, densely many flowered; remaining spikes female, oblong, obovate, or obovate-oblong, 8–25 × 3–8 mm, declined, densely many flowered, sometimes loosely flowered at base. Female glumes red-brown or castaneous, ovate or broadly rhomboid-elliptic, 4–4.5 × 2–2.3 mm, lustrous, densely hirsute on upper part and along margins, margins broadly white hyaline, costa green, 3-veined, veins scabrous, apex acute. Utricles brown-purple or castaneous, longer than glume, obovate-elliptic, compressed, (4.2–)5–6 × 2–3 mm, thinly membranous, densely hirsute, 5–7-veined, base subabruptly contracted into a very short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a very short beak, orifice broadly white hyaline, obliquely truncate, entire. Nutlets light yellow, loosely enveloped, oblong, trigonous, ca. 2.5 × 1 mm, slightly convex on faces, base cuneate, attenuate into a stipe ca. 0.8 mm, apex abruptly contracted into a mucro; style up to ca. 3 mm, slightly curved; stigmas (2 or)3.</description>
  <distribution>● Shanxi (Wutai Shan).</distribution>
</treatment>

