<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>224.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>cranaocarpa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1939: 184. 1939</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>鹤果薹草 he guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome oblique, woody. Culms tufted, 50–80 cm tall, obtusely trigonous, smooth, scabrous above, clothed at base with brown sheaths eventually disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 2–3 mm wide, flat, margins scabrous, apex long acuminate. Involucral bracts reduced to shortly bladed, shorter than inflorescence, sheathing 1–2 cm. Spikes 4–9; upper 3–5(–7) male, approximate, cylindric, 1–2 cm, sessile; remaining spikes female, rarely with male flowers at apex, cylindric or oblong, 2–3.2 × ca. 0.4 cm, densely many flowered, with slender, scabrous peduncles 1.5–5 cm. Female glumes castaneous, elliptic-lanceolate or broadly ovate, 5–5.5 mm, scabrous on 2 lateral veins of costa, margins broadly white hyaline. Utricles stramineous below, purple-brown above, longer and broader than glume, elliptic-lanceolate, compressed trigonous, 7–8 mm, papery, densely papillose, conspicuously veined abaxially, faintly veined adaxially, base contracted, apex gradually narrowed into a beak, orifice obliquely truncate, white hyaline. Nutlets brown, loosely enveloped, oblong, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, base with short stipe 0.5–0.8 mm; style long and erect, hispidulous, base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jul–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>● Rock crevices, sunny slopes, roadsides; 1500–3000 m. Hebei, Nei Mongol, Shaanxi.</distribution>
</treatment>

