<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>227.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>karoi</species_name>
    <species_authority>Freyn</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Oesterr. Bot. Z.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>40: 303. 1890</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>小粒薹草 xiao li tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>capillaris</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <variety_name>parvirostris</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Kükenthal</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>karoi</species_name>
    <variety_name>parvirostris</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>( Kükenthal) Á. Löve et al.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>licentii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>selengensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>K. V. Ivanova</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>takenakae</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nakai.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 10–40 cm tall, rather slender, lower part smooth, upper part scabrous, clothed at base with sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves nearly basal, shorter than culm, blades 1–2 mm wide, slightly stiff, base plicate and gradually flattened distally, margins scabrous; sheaths 1–2 cm. Lowest involucral bracts leaflike, surpassing subtending spike, upper involucral bracts with setaceous blade, uppermost usually sheathlike. Spikes 3 or 4(–6), single in an involucral bract sheath, lower remote and upper contiguous; terminal spike gynaecandrous, female part shorter than male part, or sometimes male, surpassing uppermost female spike, oblong-obovate or clavate, 4–10 mm; lateral spikes female, oblong or shortly cylindric, 4–15 mm, densely many flowered; peduncles slender, lower ones rather long and upper short. Female glumes yellowish, broadly ovate or suborbicular, ca. 1.5 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex obtuse, muticous. Utricles yellowish green, obliquely patent, slightly longer than glume, broadly obovate or suborbicular, inflated trigonous, 1.5–2 mm, membranous, inconspicuously veined, base broadly cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a very short beak or nearly beakless, slightly scabrous on margins, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlets loosely enveloped, broadly elliptic or obovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.2 mm, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places in thickets, riversides, swamps. Hebei, Liaoning, Nei Mongol, Shanxi [Mongolia, Russia].</distribution>
</treatment>

