<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>228.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tenuiformis</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Acad. Int. G éogr. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 104. 1902</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>细形薹草 xi xing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>koreana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Komarov.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 20–40 cm tall, rather slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, slightly scabrous at upper part, closed at base with brownish or red-brown sheaths, old sheaths usually disintegrated into fibers. Leaves slightly shorter than culm, blades 2–2.5 mm wide, flat, rather soft, scabrous on margins, rather long sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, usually shorter than subtending spike, sheathed, rather long. Spikes 3, rather remote; terminal spike male, lanceolate or broadly linear, 1.2–1.7 cm, conspicuously longer than adjacent female spike; lateral spikes female, broadly linear or oblong-linear, 1.5–2 cm, loosely 10- to more flowered; peduncle slender, up to 6 cm, slightly scabrous, slightly pendent or erect. Female glumes ferruginous, elliptic or obovate-oblong, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, green 1-veined, margins broadly hyaline at upper part, apex obtuse or acute. Utricles yellowish green, suberect, longer than glume, oblong-lanceolate, compressed trigonous, 3.5–4.5 mm, membranous, nerveless or 2-veined laterally, gradually tapering to a short stipe at base and a long beak at apex, beak scabrous on margins, obliquely truncate at orifice, slightly ferruginous. Nutlets rather loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, apex mucronate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, grasslands on forest margins or in thickets, sometimes on mountain slopes. Heilongjiang, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
</treatment>

