<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>229.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>capillaris</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 977. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>细秆薹草 xi gan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, without stolons. Culms densely tufted, 15–40 cm tall, rather slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, with brown sheaths at base, old sheaths usually disintegrated into fibers. Leaves much shorter than culm, 1/3–1/2 height of culm, blades 1.5–2 mm wide, flat, rather soft, scabrous on margins, shortly sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, linear, shorter than subtending spike, with rather long sheath. Spikes 3 or 4, rather remote, slightly pendulous; terminal spike male, sometimes with 2 or 3 female flowers at base or apex, narrowly lanceolate, 0.5–1 cm, not surpassing uppermost female spike; lateral spikes female, narrowly oblong, 0.8–1.5 cm, loosely 6–10-flowered; peduncles slender, longest up to 5 cm, smooth or slightly scabrous. Female glumes early deciduous, yellow-brown or brown, obovate, ca. 2.5 mm, membranous, green 3-veined, with veins and midrib convex, margins broadly white hyaline, apex obtuse or acute and mucronate. Utricles dark yellow-green or brown-green, suberect, longer than glume, ovate-oblong or narrowly ovate, obtusely trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, membranous, nerveless, base gradually attenuate into a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed into a ± long beak, beak slightly scabrous on margins, white hyaline and obliquely truncate or emarginate at orifice. Nutlets yellowish, tightly enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Alpine grasslands and meadows, mountain slopes, streamsides, watersides. Gansu, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol, Qinghai, Shaanxi, Shanxi [Japan, Korea, Russia; Europe, North America].</distribution>
</treatment>

