<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>230.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chlorostachys</species_name>
    <species_authority>Steven</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Soc. Imp. Naturalistes Moscou</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 68. 1813</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>绿穗薹草 lü sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 10–30(–50) cm tall, slender, subrigid, obtusely trigonous, smooth, bearing many leaves at lower part. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 2–2.5 mm wide, flat, rather soft, smooth, slightly scabrous distally, sheaths short. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, upper involucral bracts setaceous, 5–15 mm, sheathed. Spikes 3–6, single in an involucral bract sheath, lower remote, longest space up to 6 cm, upper approximate; terminal spike male, oblong-lanceolate, 6–10 mm; lateral spikes female, cylindric or oblong, 8–18 mm, loosely (6–)8–10(–12)-flowered; peduncles slender, usually pendulous. Female glumes brownish yellow or stramineous, obovate or subelliptic, ca. 2 mm, membranous, 1-veined, early deciduous, apex rounded, muticous. Utricles yellow-green or brown at maturity, obliquely patent, longer than glume, ovate-fusiform, obovate-fusiform, or subelliptic, obtusely trigonous, 2–3 mm, membranous, shiny, nerveless, base abruptly constricted into a short stipe, apex abruptly narrowed to a very short beak not up to 0.5 mm, orifice obliquely truncate, white hyaline on margins. Nutlets brown, subloosely enveloped, broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base estipitate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Thickets on mountain slopes, grasslands, riversides, lakeshores, wet places in ravines; 1100–3200 m. Gansu, Hebei, Nei Mongol, Qinghai, Shanxi, Sichuan, Xinjiang, Xizang [Japan, Korea, Russia (European part, Siberia)].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikes rem ote, longest space up to 6 cm, upper spikes approximate; utricles ovate-fusiform or obovate- fusiform, ca. 3 mm, beak short</statement>
      <determination>230a. var. chlorostachys</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikes approximate; utricles subelliptic, 2–2.5 mm, nearly beakless</statement>
      <determination>230b. var. conferta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

