<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>231.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>ledebouriana</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Meyer &amp; Treviranus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Imp. Naturalistes Moscou</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36(1): 540. 1863</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>棒穗薹草 bang sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>capillaris</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <variety_name>ledebouriana</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(C. A. Meyer &amp; Treviranus) F. Schmidt.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 10–15 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, sheaths usually disintegrated into fibers. Leaves basal, ca. 1/2 height of culm or rather longer, blades 1–2 mm wide, flat, midrib and 2 lateral veins conspicuous, upper margins scabrous, sheaths rather short, usually dehiscent at lateral plane. Lower 2 or 3 involucral bracts leaflike, longer than subtending spike, rather long sheathed, upper sheath-shaped, nearly bladeless. Spikes 4–6, rather approximate; terminal spike male, oblanceolate or clavate, 6–10 mm, with short peduncle; lateral spikes female, ovate or oblong, 5–12 mm, loosely few to several flowered, with slender peduncle, erect or slightly pendulous. Female glumes yellowish brown, ovate, ca. 1.5 mm, membranous, 1-veined, margins white hyaline, apex obtuse. Utricles greenish yellow and yellowish brown at maturity, obliquely patent, longer than glume, ovate or oblong, obtusely trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, nerveless, base acute or obtuse, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice truncate and white hyaline on margins. Nutlets dark brown, tightly enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base acute, apex mucronate; style short; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Marsh meadows, wet places on mountain slopes; ca. 2400 m. Xizang [N Mongolia, Russia].</distribution>
</treatment>

