<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>235.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>wenshanensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 179. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>文山薹草 wen shan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, with slender stolons. Culms hardly tufted, rather robust, 50–60 cm tall, obtusely trigonous, smooth, clothed below with dark brown and long sheaths. Leaves longer than or equaling culm, blades 4–5 mm wide, flat, smooth on both surfaces, margins scabrous; lower sheaths 12–15 cm. Involucral bracts leaflike, upper sublinear, lower sheathed, upper with short sheaths or nearly sheathless. Spikes 7–10 or more, lower sometimes ramified, androgynous or lower spikes female, female part much longer than male part, cylindric or oblong-cylindric, 2–5 cm × ca. 8 mm, lower 2 spikes pedunculate, others sessile. Female glumes stramineous at middle, red-brown on sides, ovate, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, 1–3-veined, apex acute and aristate, arista scabrous on both margins. Utricles yellow-green, nearly horizontally patent, longer than glume (excluding length of arista), obovate, trigonous, ca. 4 mm, membranous, ferruginous punctate, glabrous, inconspicuously veined, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a long beak, beak ca. 2 mm, shortly 2-toothed at orifice. Nutlets brown, brownish yellow on angles, tightly enveloped, broadly obovate or ovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base stipitate; style base bent, persistent; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Evergreen broad-leaved forests on mountain ridges; ca. 2400 m. SE Yunnan (Wenshan).</distribution>
</treatment>

