<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>237.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>nitidiutriculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37. 186. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>亮果薹草 liang guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather slender, ligneous. Culms tufted, 25–70 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, clothed with red-brown bladeless or shortly bladed sheaths at base. Leaves basal, shorter or longer than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, with 2 distinct lateral veins, smooth, scabrous on upper margins; sheaths red-brown, splitting at membranous part. Involucral bracts leaflike, usually longer than subtending spike, sheathed, with liguliform or semiorbicular ligule at mouth of sheath. Spikes 5–8; terminal 1 or 2 spikes male, oblong or narrowly cylindric, 1–3 cm; remaining spikes androgynous, female part longer than male part, cylindric or lanceolate, (1.5–)3–6 cm, densely many flowered; peduncles slender, lowest peduncle 5–11 cm, upper ones rather short. Female glumes cinereous-green at middle, brownish on sides, ovate, ca. 2.5 mm (excluding length of arista), membranous, 3-veined, apex mucronate or aristate. Utricles yellowish green, brownish near base, much longer than glume, obliquely patent, elliptic or obovate-elliptic, obtusely trigonous or plano-convex, 6–7 mm, shiny, 7-veined abaxially, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a long beak, spinulose on margins of beak. Nutlets pale yellow, rather tightly enveloped, obovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests on mountain slopes, wet places in fields, ravines; 2000–2300 m. C and E Yunnan (Fumin, Kunming, Shizong).</distribution>
</treatment>

