<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>243.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>metallica</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 239. 1908</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>锈果薹草 xiu guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pachinensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, without stolons. Culms densely tufted, 15–50 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, clothed at base with sheaths splitting into fibers. Leaves slightly longer or sometimes slightly shorter than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat, margins scabrous; sheaths usually splitting at membranous part. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, sheathed, upper blades setaceous, sheathless. Spikes 5–8; terminal spike gynaecandrous, rarely male, clavate-cylindric; lateral spikes female or sometimes with a few male flowers at base, usually 1 or 2 spikes exserted from an involucral bract sheath, cylindric, 2.5–4.5 cm, densely many flowered; peduncles slender, gradually shorter upward. Female glumes yellowish white, ovate-lanceolate, ca. 4.8 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex mucronate. Utricles stramineous, longer than glume, suberect, elliptic, plano-convex, ca. 7 mm, membranous, red-brown punctate, slightly shiny, inconspicuously 5-veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed to a long beak, scabrous on margins of upper part and beak, orifice shallowly 2-toothed. Nutlets stramineous, very loosely enveloped, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base shortly stipitate; style slender; stigmas 3. Fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Fujian, Taiwan [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
</treatment>

