<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>247.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>hirtiutriculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32: 181. 1994</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>糙毛薹草 cao mao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slightly elongate, ligneous, with long stolons. Culms 45–60 cm tall, rather slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, eventually disintegrating into fibers at base. Leaves slightly longer than culm, blades ca. 5 mm wide, relatively stiff, with 2 conspicuous lateral veins, base plicate and flattened distally, upper surface and margins scabrous; sheaths up to 10 cm, sometimes eventually splitting. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, long sheathed. Panicle rather narrow and loose, longest up to 40 cm, with 10–20 or more spikes, lowermost 1 or 2 partial panicles remote, with slender peduncle, upper peduncles rather short; spikes androgynous, male part longer than female part, only with few female flowers, narrowly cylindric, 1.5–2.5 cm, with medium-sized peduncle. Female glumes brown-yellow, ovate, ca. 3.5 mm, membranous, green 1-veined, apex acute, muticous. Utricles greenish, longer than glume, suberect, oblong-lanceolate, trigonous, ca. 5 mm, ferruginous punctate, loosely hispidulous, abaxially distinctly 2-veined laterally, base abruptly contracted into a stipe, apex gradually narrowed to a medium-sized beak, orifice obliquely truncate, brownish on margins. Nutlets brownish yellow, tightly enveloped, oblong, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, base very shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests on mountain slopes; ca. 2300 m. Yunnan (Jingdong: Wuliang Shan).</distribution>
</treatment>

