<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>251.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>finitima</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ill. Gen. Carex</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 44. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>亮绿薹草 liang lü tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, ligneous. Culms tufted, 25–80 cm tall, slightly thick, obtusely trigonous, smooth, bearing rather many leaves at base. Leaves shorter than or equaling culm, blades 4–8 mm wide, flat, scabrous on veins of upper surface and margins of top; lower sheaths up to 6 cm, reddish brown. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than or slightly shorter than inflorescence, sheathed, sheathing mouth concave. Spikes 4–7, lowermost spaced up to 10 cm, uppermost 2 ± contiguous; terminal spike male, linear, 1–5.5 cm; remaining spikes female, linear-cylindric, 2–12 cm, loosely many flowered; peduncles slender, slightly pendulous. Female glumes brownish yellow, ovate, ca. 3.5 mm, membranous, 1-veined, margins white hyaline, upper margin praemorse, apex acute, mucronate or muticous. Utricles brownish green, suberect, longer than glume, elliptic-lanceolate, trigonous, 5–7 mm, membranous, glabrous, shiny, 2 lateral veins elevated, base attenuate, shortly stipitate, apex gradually narrowed to a long beak, beak ca. 2.5 mm. Nutlets tightly enveloped, narrowly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, streamsides, roadsides, grasslands at watersides; 2000–3000 m. S Gansu, Sichuan, Taiwan, Yunnan [Bhutan, India, Indonesia (Sumatra), Nepal, New Guinea].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms 40–80 cm tall; leaves slightly shorter than or equaling culm; male spike 2–5.5 cm, female spikes 5–10 cm; utricles 6–7 mm</statement>
      <determination>251a. var. finitima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms 25–35 cm tall; leaves much shorter than culm; male spike 1–2.5 cm, female spikes 2–4(–5) cm; utricles ca. 5 mm</statement>
      <determination>251b. var. attenuata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

