<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>253.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>bostrychostigma</species_name>
    <species_authority>Maximowicz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Acad. Imp. Sci. Saint-Pétersbourg</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31: 118. 1886</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>卷柱头薹草 juan zhu tou tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome elongate, ligneous, clothed with sheaths eventually disintegrating into dark brown fibers. Culms densely tufted, 20–50 cm tall, slightly slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth. Leaves shorter than or nearly equaling culm, blades 3–4 mm wide, flat, scabrous on 2 lateral veins of adaxial surface and costa of abaxial surface, sheathed. Lowermost 1 or 2 involucral bracts leaflike, upper ones setaceous, slightly scabrous, sheathed. Spikes 5–8, solitary in an involucral bract sheath; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 2–4 cm, peduncle slender; lateral spikes female, space up to 6 cm, rather short near top, narrowly cylindric, 2–4 cm, loosely many flowered; peduncles rather short and thin, enclosed in involucral bract sheath. Female glumes brownish yellow, ovate-lanceolate, 4.5–5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, 2 lateral veins inconspicuous, costa scabrous, margins broadly white hyaline, apex acute. Utricles yellowish green, suberect, longer than glume, narrowly lanceolate, trigonous, ca. 7 mm, membranous, base attenuate, apex gradually narrowed to a long beak, orifice obliquely truncate, white hyaline on margins, sometimes shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets yellow-brown, tightly enveloped, narrowly oblong, trigonous, ca. 3.5 mm, base shortly stipitate; style much longer than utricle; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Meadow moors, watersides, wet places at roadsides; 200–1000 m. Jilin, Liaoning, Shaanxi, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

