<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>256.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>subtumida</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Kükenthal) Ohwi</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Geo bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 75. 1932</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>肿胀果薹草 zhong zhang guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>ischnostachya</species_name>
    <species_authority>Steudel</species_authority>
    <variety_name>subtumida</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Kükenthal</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>27: 109. 1929.</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short or elongate. Culms 45–75 cm tall, slightly thick, triquetrous, smooth, few purple-brown and bladeless sheathed at base. Leaves slightly shorter than culm, blades 6–7 mm wide, flat, subrigid, with 2 conspicuous lateral veins on upper surface, scabrous on veins of both surfaces and margins; sheaths long, lowermost ones purple-brown and usually splitting later. Involucral bracts leaflike, much surpassing subtending spike, lower ones slightly long sheathing, upper ones shortly sheathing, uppermost nearly not sheathing. Spikes 4–6, lowest 1 or 2 remote, upper 3 or 4 contiguous at apex of culm; terminal spike male, linear, 2.5–3 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, long cylindric, 3.5–7 cm, densely many flowered, lowest 1 or 2 with long peduncle, upper ones subsessile. Female glumes yellowish or brownish yellow, ovate, ca. 1 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acuminate. Utricles brown-green, horizontally patent later, much longer than glume, elliptic-obovate, obtusely trigonous, 3.2–3.5 mm, membranous, many veined, base rounded, apex abruptly contracted into a rather short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets stramineous, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, sessile, apex mucronate; style not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Ravine sides, watersides, roadsides on mountain slopes; 800–1000 m. Anhui, Jiangsu, Jiangxi.</distribution>
</treatment>

