<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>257.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>nemostachys</species_name>
    <species_authority>Steudel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>29: 23. 1846</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>条穗薹草 tiao sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick and short, ligneous, stoloniferous. Culms 40–90 cm tall, thick, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part, sheaths at base eventually disintegrating into yellow-brown fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades 6–8 mm wide, rather stiff, plicate near base and flattened distally, distinctly 2-veined laterally, scabrous on veins and margins. Involucral bracts longer or shorter than culm, lower ones leaflike, upper one setaceous, not sheathed. Spikes 5–8, contiguous at top of culm; terminal spike male, linear, 5–10 cm, subsessile; lateral spikes female, cylindric, 4–12 cm, densely many flowered, subsessile or with short peduncle at lower part. Female glumes pale, narrowly lanceolate, 3–4 mm, membranous, green 1–3-veined, apex aristate, scabrous on margins of awn. Utricles brown, patent, slightly shorter than glume (including length of awn), ovate or broadly ovate, obtusely trigonous, ca. 3 mm, membranous, hispidulous, few veined, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a slender, recurved beak, orifice obliquely truncate, sometimes minutely 2-toothed. Nutlets brownish yellow, loosely enveloped, broadly obovate or subelliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.8 mm; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Sep–Dec.</description>
  <distribution>Streamsides, moors, shady and wet places in forests; 300–1600 m. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Guizhou, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Bangladesh, Cambodia, India, Japan, Myanmar, Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

