<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>261.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>brownii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Tuckerman</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Meth. Caric.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21. 1843</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>亚澳薹草 ya ao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>nipposinica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 30–60 cm tall, medium thick, triquetrous, smooth, clothed with bladeless brown sheaths at base, few sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 3–4 mm wide, flat, rather stiff, sheathed. Involucral bracts longer than culm, leaflike, lowest sheath long, upper ones rather short. Spikes 3 or 4, rather remote; terminal spike male, linear, 1–2 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, oblong or oblong-cylindric, 1–3 cm, densely many flowered, lowest long pedunculate, upper ones rather shortly pedunculate. Female glumes pale, lanceolate-ovate, ca. 2.8 mm, membranous, 1–3-veined, apex acuminate, with an awn. Utricles brown-green, obliquely patent, horizontally patent at maturity, slightly longer than glume, broadly obovate, inflated trigonous, ca. 3 mm, membranous, glabrous, many veined, base broadly cuneate, estipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets pale brown, yellowish on angles, slightly loosely enveloped, nearly broadly elliptic or broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; stigmas 3, short. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Ditch sides, forests, wet places in low-lying lands; 400–1700 m. Anhui, Gansu, Henan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Shanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Zhejiang [Indonesia, Japan, Korea; Australia, Pacific islands (New Zealand)].</distribution>
</treatment>

