<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>263.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>transversa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Narr. Exped. China Japan,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>324. 1857</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>横果薹草 heng guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>brownii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Tuckerman</species_authority>
    <variety_name>transversa</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Boott) Küken thal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 30–60 cm tall, acutely triquetrous, clothed with purple-brown bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves shorter than or slightly longer than culms, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat, rather soft; sheaths rather long. Involucral bracts longer than subtending spike, leaflike, sheathing portion ca. 1/2 length of subtending peduncle. Spikes 3–5, upper 2 or 3 slightly contiguous, lower ones rather remote; terminal spike male, narrowly cylindric, 1–1.5 cm, with peduncle; lateral spikes female, broadly cylindric or suboblong, 2–3 cm, densely many flowered, with rather long peduncle. Female glumes pale and hyaline laterally, ovate, 4–5 mm, membranous, green 1–3-veined, apex acuminate, with a long awn. Utricles brown-green, obliquely patent, longer than or as long as glume (including length of awn), ovate or elliptic-ovate, slightly inflated trigonous, 5–6.5 mm, membranous, glabrous, conspicuously several veined, base broadly cuneate, apex gradually attenuate into a long beak, orifice obliquely truncate or minutely 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish, subloosely enveloped, broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, base stipitate, apex mucronate; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, grasslands, wet places; 500–800 m. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
</treatment>

