<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>264.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>oedorrhampha</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1939: 659. 1939</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>肿喙薹草 zhong hui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tumida</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott (1858)</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <other_info>not Beilschmid (1850).</other_info>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, ligneous. Culms loosely tufted, rather thick, triquetrous, smooth, with several yellowish brown bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves longer than culm, blades 3–6 mm wide, flat, plicate proximally, with 2 distinct lateral veins, scabrous on both surfaces and margins, long sheathed; sheaths up to 15 cm. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than subtending spike, lower sheaths rather long and upper sheaths rather short. Spikes 5 or 6, upper 3 or 4 approximate, lower 2 slightly remote; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 6–14 cm, with short peduncle or subsessile; lateral spikes female, cylindric, (3–)5–14 cm, densely many flowered, upper 2 with very short peduncle, lower ones with slightly long peduncle. Male glumes pale yellow, narrowly lanceolate, (5–)7–9 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acuminate, with a long awn, awn ca. 1/2 length of glume and hispidulous along margins; female glumes pale yellow, ovate, ca. 2.8 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex attenuate, with a long awn, awn as long as or longer than 1/2 length of glumes and hispidulous along margins. Utricles brownish green, obliquely patent, slightly longer than glume, elliptic or obovate, obtusely trigonous, 2.8–3 mm, membranous, 3–5-veined abaxially, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex contracted into a medium-sized to long beak, orifice subtruncate or emarginate. Nutlets yellow or brownish yellow, rather tightly enveloped, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Mar–May.</description>
  <distribution>Mountain slopes, open forests, canals, shady and wet areas; 700–2000 m. Guangdong, Yunnan [Bhutan, India (Sikkim), Indonesia, Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

