<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>268.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>confertiflora</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts, n.s.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 418. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>密花薹草 mi hua tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>olivacea</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <variety_name>angustior</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Kükenthal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, stoloniferous. Culms 60–95 cm tall, acutely triquetrous, winged on 3 angles, medium thick, clothed with bladeless or shortly bladed sheaths at base, and with 1 or 2 leaves on upper part. Leaves slightly shorter than culm, uppermost leaf usually longer than culm, blades 8–12 mm wide, flat, with 2 distinct lateral veins, smooth on both surfaces, scabrous on margins, sheathed, lower sheaths usually dehiscent. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than subtending spike, upper involucral bracts narrow, nearly not sheathed. Spikes 4–6, ± contiguous at upper part of culm; terminal spike male, cylindric or narrowly cylindric, 4–8 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, cylindric, (2–)3.5–8 cm, densely many flowered, lower 1 or 2 spikes shortly pedunculate, upper spikes nearly sessile. Female glumes ferruginous, narrowly oblong or narrowly oblong-ovate, 3–3.5 mm, membranous, green 1-veined, apex attenuate, awned. Utricles ferruginous, slightly shorter than glume, horizontally patent at maturity, ovate or subobovate, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, membranous, glabrous, several veined abaxially, base broadly cuneate, apex attenuate into a short beak, beak straight or slightly recurved, obliquely truncate or sometimes shortly 2-toothed at orifice. Nutlets brown at maturity, rather loosely enveloped, subobovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base estipitate, apex with torsional mucro; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Wet areas in forests, watersides or grasslands among shrubs; 1800–2700 m. Guizhou, Hubei, Yunnan [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

