<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>271.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>harrysmithii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Horti Gothob.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 40. 1930</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>哈氏薹草 ha shi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, without stolons. Culms loosely tufted, 15–20 cm tall, slender, compressed triquetrous, smooth, clothed with yellowish brown and bladeless sheaths at base, sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 1–2 mm wide, flat, smooth, long sheathed. Lowest involucral bracts leaflike, linear, longer than subtending spike, not sheathed or shortly sheathed (2–3 mm), upper involucral bracts setaceous, not sheathed. Spikes 2, congregate at top of culm, androgynous, ovate or oblong, 5–10 mm, densely many flowered, with few male flowers at top of spike, shortly pedunculate or subsessile. Male glumes yellow-brown, narrowly lanceolate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, green 1-veined, apex acuminate; female glumes yellowish, narrowly ovate, 1.5–2 mm, membranous, green 1-veined, apex acuminate, mucronate or aristate. Utricles stramineous, obliquely patent, longer than glume, obovate-elliptic or narrowly elliptic, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, membranous, smooth, nerveless, base acute, apex abruptly contracted into a medium-sized to long beak, orifice truncate or emarginate, membranous, hyaline. Nutlets rather tightly enveloped, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; style rather short, base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>● Mountain slopes; ca. 2500 m. W Sichuan.</distribution>
</treatment>

