<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>272.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>agglomerata</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 269. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>团穗薹草 tuan sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>agglomerata</species_name>
    <variety_name>rhizomata</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Y. C. Yang.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather long, ligneous, stoloniferous. Culms 20–60 cm tall, slightly slender, acutely triquetrous, scabrous on angles, purple-brown and bladeless sheathed, sheaths eventually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves shorter than or equaling culm, blades 2–6 mm wide, scabrous and sometimes slightly revolute on margins, reddish brown sheathed. Lowest involucral bract leaflike, longer than subtending spike, upper involucral bracts awn-shaped, shorter than subtending spike, not sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4, congregate at top of culm; terminal spike gynaecandrous, clavate-oblong, ca. 1.5 cm, rarely male, narrowly oblong, subsessile; lateral spikes 2 or 3, female, oblong, 1–1.5 cm, densely many flowered, subsessile. Male glumes brownish yellow, lanceolate-ovate, ca. 4 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acuminate, aristate; female glumes brownish yellow, ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, 1-veined, scabrid on veins, apex acuminate, shortly aristate. Utricles yellowish green, obliquely patent, nearly horizontally patent at maturity, longer than glume, ovate or narrowly ovate, slightly inflated trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, membranous, glabrous, distinctly 2-veined laterally, other veins obscure, base obtusely rounded, apex attenuate into a slightly long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish, rather loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests on mountain slopes, wet places in valleys; 1200–3200 m. Gansu, Qinghai, Shaanxi, Sichuan.</distribution>
</treatment>

