<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>277.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>aphanolepis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet &amp; Savatier</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl. Jap.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 580. 1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>匿鳞薹草 ni lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>japonica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Thunberg</species_authority>
    <variety_name>aphanolepis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Franchet &amp; Savatier) Kükenthal</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>japonica</species_name>
    <variety_name>humilis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Franchet.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender and long stoloniferous. Culms 15–30 cm tall, slightly slender, triquetrous, scabridulous, brownish sheathed at base. Leaves longer than or nearly equaling culm, blades 3–8 mm wide, flat, soft, scabrous on margins, ± long sheathed, basal sheath ± disintegrated into fibers. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, not sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4, upper spikes approximate, lower spikes rather remote; terminal spike male, linear, 1–3 cm, shortly pedunculate or nearly sessile; lateral spikes female, globose-oblong or oblong, 0.8–1.7 cm, ca. 5 mm wide, densely many flowered, upper spikes sessile, lower spikes shortly pedunculate. Male glumes brown, lanceolate-oblong, ca. 4 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acuminate; female glumes green at middle, pale laterally, ovate or narrowly ovate, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acuminate, mucronate. Utricles yellowish, obliquely patent, longer than glume, elliptic, inflated trigonous, ca. 4 mm, thickly papery, slightly shiny, obscurely veined, base broadly cuneate or obtusely rounded, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets brown, rather loosely enveloped, elliptic or obovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, apex muticous; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3, rather short.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, wet places at forest margins. Anhui, Jiangsu [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
</treatment>

