<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>279.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>mollicula</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ill. Gen. Carex</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 192. 1867</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>柔果薹草 rou guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous. Culms densely tufted, 15–30 cm tall, acutely triquetrous or sometimes narrowly winged on angles, scabrous on upper angles, with few bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves longer than culm, blades 4–8 mm wide, flat, rather soft, distinctly 2-veined laterally on upper surface, sheathed, sheaths brown at base of culm. Involucral bracts longer than subtending spike, upper involucral bracts sublinear, lower involucral bracts leaflike, nearly not sheathed. Spikes 3–5, usually congregate at top of culm, distances short; terminal spike male, linear or subclavate, 1–2 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, oblong-cylindric, 1.5–2.5 cm, densely many flowered, very shortly pedunculate or nearly sessile. Male glumes pale, narrowly oblong, ca. 4 mm, green 1-veined, apex mucronate; female glumes brownish yellow, oblong-ovate or subovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acuminate, sometimes mucronate. Utricles yellow-green or stramineous, obliquely patent, eventually nearly horizontally patent, much longer than glume, oblong-ovate or lanceolate-ovate, inflated trigonous, ca. 4 mm, membranous, glabrous, obscurely veined, usually rugose, base obtusely rounded, apex attenuate into a medium-sized or rather long beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets rather loosely enveloped, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base acute or slightly obtuse, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, thickets, wet areas, riversides, ditch sides. Taiwan, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
</treatment>

