<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>288.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>planiculmis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Komarov</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trudy Imp. S.-Peterburgsk. Bot. Sada</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 448. 1901</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>扁秆薹草 bian gan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick and slightly elongate, with slender stolons. Culms tufted, 30–45 cm tall, rather thick, compressed triquetrous, winged on 2 angles and 1 angle obscure, scabrous on angles, few bladeless sheathed at base. Leaves slightly shorter than culm, blades 5–10 mm wide, flat, rather soft, scabrous on veins and margins, ± long sheathed; sheaths brownish yellow, eventually split on membranous part. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, longer than subtending spike, upper involucral bracts awn-shaped, usually shorter than subtending spike, scabrous on veins and margins, not sheathed. Spikes 4–6, lowest one rather remote, others contiguous at top of culm; terminal spike male, sometimes with some female flowers at apex, narrowly cylindric, 2.5–3.5 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, cylindric, 1.5–4.5 cm, densely many flowered and slightly loosely flowered at base, lowest one rather long pedunculate, upper spikes shortly pedunculate. Female glumes brownish yellow or yellowish, ovate or oblong-ovate, ca. 2.5 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acuminate, mucronate. Utricles yellowish green, obliquely patent, more divergent at maturity, longer than glume, ovate or narrowly ovate, obscurely trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, membranous, shiny, glabrous, 5-veined abaxially, base subrounded, apex attenuate into a medium-sized to long and recurved beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets brown, slightly loosely enveloped, obovate or subelliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Streamsides, ditch sides, wet places in forests; 1100–1900 m. Hebei, Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning, Shaanxi [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

