<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>290.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chinensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Retzius</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Observ. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 42. 1783</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>中华薹草 zhong hua tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, obliquely ascending, woody. Culms tufted, 20–55 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, clothed at base with brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades light green, linear, 3–9 mm wide, leathery, margins scabrous. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, long sheathing. Spikes 4 or 5, distant; terminal spike usually male, rarely gynaecandrous, narrowly cylindric, 2.5–4.2 cm, peduncle 2.5–3.5 cm; lateral spikes female, usually with several male flowers at apex or base, subdensely flowered, peduncles erect, slender. Female glumes pale, oblong-lanceolate, rarely obovate-oblong, ca. 3 mm, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous long awn, apex truncate or sometimes emarginate or acuminate. Utricles yellow-green, longer than glume, obliquely patent, rhomboid or obovate, subinflated trigonous, 3–4 mm, membranous, sparsely puberulent, many veined, base gradually narrowed into a stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a beak of medium length, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, rhomboid, trigonous, faces concave, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, beak annulate at orifice; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>● Shady places in valleys, rocky streamsides and grasslands; 200–1700 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Guizhou, Hunan, Jiangxi, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Yunnan, Zhejiang.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Terminal spike male; female glumes oblong-lanceolate</statement>
      <determination>290a. var. chinensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Terminal spike gynaecandrous; female glumes obovate-oblong</statement>
      <determination>290b. var. longkiensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

