<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>295.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>simulans</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 310. 1904</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>相 仿薹草 xiang fang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick, woody, rigid. Culms lateral, 30–70 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, scabrous above, clothed at base with dark brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades pale green, linear, 3–5 mm wide, flat, revolute, upper margins scabrous, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, long sheathing. Spikes 3 or 4, distant; terminal spike male, cylindric, 3–6 cm; lateral spikes mostly female, sometimes bearing few to many male flowers at apex, cylindric, 1.5–4.5 cm, slightly or rather densely flowered; peduncles erect. Female glumes brown or white, ovate-lanceolate or oblong-lanceolate, 5–5.5 mm, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous awn at emarginate apex. Utricles green, slightly longer than glume, obliquely patent, ovate (excluding beak), 6–8 mm (including beak), subleathery, glabrous, many veined, base contracted, apex abruptly contracted into a scabrous long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets loosely enveloped, ovate, trigonous, ca. 5 mm (including beak), not constricted on angles at middle, base shortly stipitate, apical beak erect, ca. 1 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Mar–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Roadsides, slopes, forests, streamsides. Hubei, Sichuan, Zhejiang.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes brown, shortly awned at apex; female spikes slightly densely flowered</statement>
      <determination>295a. var. simulans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes white, long awned a t apex; female spikes rather densely flowered</statement>
      <determination>295b. var. densiflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

