<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>298.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>macrandrolepis</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 241. 1908</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “macran drolepsis” ].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>和平菱果薹草 he ping ling guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>sharyotensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender, horizontal, with slender stolons. Culms slender, 13–14 cm tall, 0.3–0.7 mm thick, trigonous, smooth, clothed at base with dark brown sheaths eventually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves equaling or slightly longer than culm, blades green, linear, 2–3 mm wide, flattish plicate, scabrous adaxially, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts leaflike, sheathing. Spikes 3 or 4, distant; terminal spike male, pale brownish, linear or linear-oblong, 10–30 × 1.5–2.5 mm, much surpassing uppermost female spike; lateral spikes female, oblong, 10–15 × ca. 4 mm, subloosely 5–10-flowered; peduncles erect, upper 1 or 2 short and enclosed, lower 1 or 2 exserted. Female glumes pale, usually brownish margined, obovate-elliptic or obovate, 3.8–4 mm, membranous, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a straight short awn, apex rounded or shallowly emarginate. Utricles pale greenish, longer than glume, erect, patent, rhomboid, trigonous, 5–6 mm, thinly leathery, slightly shiny, sparsely hirsute to glabrescent, obscurely few veined or nearly nerveless except for 2 costas on edges, cuneate at both ends, apical beak conic, obliquely truncate at sharply 2-toothed orifice. Nutlets tightly enveloped, obovate, ca. 2.5 mm, trigonous with angles shallowly constricted at middle, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex obtuse; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands at low elevations. Taiwan [WC Japan, S Korea].</distribution>
</treatment>

