<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>299.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tatsutakensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon. Pl. Formosan.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 133. 1916</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>锐果薹草 rui guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>taihokuensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms lateral, slender, 10–30 cm tall, trigonous, erect, smooth, clothed at base with 2–4 purplish or dark brown, bladeless or shortly bladed sheaths disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves surpassing culm, blades broadly or narrowly linear, 2.5–8 mm wide, flattish, soft or subrigid. Spikes 2–4, all or occasionally except lowest one subfastigiate; terminal spike male, pale brownish, linear, 5–10 mm, surpassed by next female spike, few or several flowered; lateral spikes female or rarely with a few male flowers at apex, suberect, oblong, 7–12 × ca. 5 mm, subloosely 3–7-flowered, sessile or subsessile. Female glumes pale, lanceolate to lanceolate-oblong, 3–4 mm, membranous, glaucous green 3-veined costa projecting beyond apex forming a short erect awn or cusp, apex subacute. Utricles light green, longer than glume, erect-patent, rhomboid or rhomboid-ovate, trigonous, 6–7 mm, papery, glabrous to sparsely hirsute, faintly several veined, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex truncate and narrowed to a slender beak ca. 2 mm, beak scabrous on edges, 2-toothed at orifice. Nutlets tightly enveloped, ovate or oblong-ovate, ca. 3 mm, trigonous with shallowly concave sides; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Wet grasslands on mountain slopes. Taiwan.</distribution>
</treatment>

