<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>300.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>longerostrata</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Meyer</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg Divers Savans</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 220. 1831</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>长嘴薹草 chang zui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short or long creeping, obliquely ascending, woody. Culms tufted, slender, 15–50 cm tall, compressed trigonous, slightly scabrous above, clothed at base with light green sheaths when young, finally becoming dark brown, disintegrating into fibers. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, shorter than inflorescence, sheathing. Spikes usually 2, rarely 3; terminal spike male, brownish, clavate, 1–2.5 cm, densely flowered; lateral spikes female, ovate or oblong, 1–1.7 cm, 6–10-flowered; peduncles scarcely exserted from sheath. Female glumes light ferruginous, narrowly elliptic or lanceolate, ca. 6.5 mm, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous long awn at truncate or obtuse apex, or apex awnless. Utricles green or pale brown, slightly longer than glume, obliquely patent, obovate, obtusely trigonous, 7–8 mm (including beak), membranous, sparsely hirsute or glabrous, many veined, base contracted, apex abruptly contracted into a scabrous long beak, orifice deeply 2-lobed with long teeth. Nutlets tightly enveloped, obovate, obtusely trigonous, ca. 3 mm, faces concave at base, base shortly stipitate; style persistent, base slightly thickened, curved or erect; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Grassy slopes, mountain thickets, watersides, forests, grasslands, on cliffs; 400–2500 m. Hebei, Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning, Shaanxi, Shanxi, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East, Kamchatka)].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rhizome short, oblique; utricles sparsely hirsute; style base curved</statement>
      <determination>300a. var. longerostrata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rhizome long creeping.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles glabrous; style erect</statement>
      <determination>300c. var. hoi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles sparsely hirsute or pubescent; style curved.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes aristate</statement>
      <determination>300b. var. pallida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes acuminate</statement>
      <determination>300d. var. exaristata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

