<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>306.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>manca</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott ex Bentham</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Hongk.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>402. 1861</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>弯柄薹草 wan bing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick and short, woody. Culms lateral, 30–70 cm tall, trigonous, slender, smooth, clothed at base with bladeless sheaths. Leaves longer than culm, rarely shorter, blades broadly linear, 2–10 mm wide, flat, leathery, base plicate, upper margins scabrous, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, long sheathing. Spikes 2 or 3, distant; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, (1–)4–5 cm, with peduncles ca. 5 cm; lateral spikes female, oblong-cylindric, 2–3 cm, slightly densely flowered, with short peduncles. Female glumes stramineous, oblong-lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a mucro. Utricles yellow-green, longer than glume, obliquely patent, rhomboid-elliptic, trigonous, 6–8 mm, subleathery, sparsely pubescent, slender, many veined, base shortly stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a smooth long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets yellow-brown, tightly enveloped, ovate, ca. 2.5 mm, trigonous with angles constricted at middle, faces concave at base, base curved stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a cylindric curved beak; style base thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>● Anhui, Guangdong, Hubei, Taiwan.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades shorter than culm</statement>
      <determination>306d. subsp. wichurae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades longer than culm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 2–3 mm wide; nutlets trigonous, sometimes with 1 angle constricted at midd le</statement>
      <determination>306b. subsp. jiuhuaensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 3–8 mm wide.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Nutlets with apical beak curved</statement>
      <determination>306a. subsp. manca</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Nutlets with apical beak short and erect</statement>
      <determination>306c. subsp. takasa goana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

