<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>308.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>heudesii</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Acad. Int. Géogr. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 12. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>长安薹草 chang an tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome obliquely ascending, thick. Culms lateral, 30–45 cm tall, slender, obtusely trigonous, smooth, clothed at base with pale brown or dark brown bladeless sheaths. Leaves longer than culm, blades light green, broadly linear, 7–18 mm wide, leathery, flat, revolute, upper margins scabrous, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, shorter than subtending spike, scabrous margined, long sheathing. Spikes 3 or 4; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 1.5–4 cm, loosely many flowered, long pedunculate; lateral spikes 2 or 3, mostly female, sometimes bearing a few male flowers at apex, cylindric, 3–6 mm, loosely flowered, with erect peduncles 4.5–5 mm. Female glumes yellow-white, ovate-lanceolate, 4–5 mm, green 3-veined costa ending in an awn at acuminate apex. Utricles pale brown or brown-olivaceous, longer than glume, horizontally patent at maturity, ovate-orbicular, inflated trigonous, 4.5–6 mm, papery, slightly scabrous, many veined, apex abruptly contracted into a cylindric long beak, orifice deeply 2-lobed. Nutlets dark black, loosely enveloped, obovate, ca. 2 mm, trigonous with angles constricted at middle, faces concave at base, base curved stipitate; style base thickened, oblique, persistent; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Rock crevices, moist places in forests; 1100–2000 m. Gansu, Hubei, Shaanxi, Sichuan.</distribution>
</treatment>

