<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>310.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>thibetica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nouv. Arch. Mus. Hist. Nat., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 10: 103. 1887–1888</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>藏薹草 zang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick, woody, rigid. Culms lateral, 35–50 cm tall, obtusely trigonous, smooth, clothed at base with brown bladeless sheaths. Leaves surpassing culm, blades pale green, broadly linear, 5–17 mm wide, leathery, upper margins scabrous, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, shorter than subtending spike, long sheathing. Spikes 4–6; terminal spike male, narrowly cylindric, 3–6 cm, pedunculate; lateral spikes androgynous, male part usually equaling female part, cylindric, 4–7 cm, densely flowered, with slender, scabrous peduncles. Female glumes light yellow-brown, ovate-lanceolate, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a mucro. Utricles yellow-brown, longer than glume, obovate, subinflated trigonous, 5–6 mm (including beak), membranous, glabrous or sparsely hispid, many veined, base gradually narrowed, apex abruptly contracted into a cylindric long beak, beak slightly curved, deeply 2-lobed at orifice. Nutlets castaneous, tightly enveloped, obovate, ca. 2 mm (excluding beak), trigonous with angles constricted at middle, base curved stipitate, apical beak slender, slightly curved; style persistent, base hardly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests, shady and moist places or rock crevices along valleys, cliffs along streamsides; 800–2200 m. Chongqing, Guangxi, Guizhou, Henan, Hubei, Hunan, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Yunnan, Zhejiang.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades ca. 5 mm wide only; lateral spikes 2–3 cm</statement>
      <determination>310c. var. minor</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 6–17 mm wide; lateral spikes 4–7 cm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lateral spikes many flowered</statement>
      <determination>310a. var. thibetica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lateral spikes 6- or 7-flowered</statement>
      <determination>310b. var. pauciflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

