<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>312.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>harlandii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ill. Gen. Carex</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 87. 1860</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “har landi” ].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>长囊薹草 chang nang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>anomocarya</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>chlorocystis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boeckeler</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>harlandii</species_name>
    <variety_name>liuguensis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>S. Yun Liang &amp; D. Y. Liu</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>harlandii</species_name>
    <variety_name>xiuningensis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>S. W. Su.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome thick and short, woody. Culms lateral, 30–90 cm tall, trigonous, stiff, smooth. Sterile leaves longer than culm, blades broadly linear, 1–2.2 cm wide, flat, leathery, base plicate, upper margins scabrous, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, sheathing. Spikes 3 or 4, distant; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 4.5–8 cm, pedunculate; lateral spikes mostly female, with several male flowers at apex, uppermost spike contiguous with male spike, remaining spikes distant, cylindric, 4.5–9 × 0.9–1.3 cm, densely flowered, with short peduncles. Female glumes pale green, ovate-oblong or oblong, 3–3.5 mm, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous awn. Utricles yellow-green or green, much longer than glume, obliquely patent, elliptic-rhomboid, 9–10 mm (including beak), papery, glabrous, many veined, base gradually narrowed, apex abruptly contracted into a long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets yellow-brown, tightly enveloped, rhomboid-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 7 mm, constricted on angles at middle, faces concave at base, base curved stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a slender and erect beak, orifice annulate; style base broadly conic; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, thickets, moist places and on rocks along streamsides, grasslands, slopes. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hainan, Hubei, Jiangxi, Zhejiang [Indonesia, Myanmar, Thailand, N Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

