<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>318.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>laticeps</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke ex Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nouv. Arch. Mus. Hist. Nat., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3, 9: 178. 1897</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>弯喙薹草 wan hui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>cavaleriei</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>hancei</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, woody, rigid, stoloniferous. Culms 30–40 cm tall, slender, trigonous, sparsely pubescent, clothed at base with brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades gray-green, linear, 3–5 mm wide, flat, revolute, pubescent, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts shortly bladed, pubescent, long sheathing. Spikes 2 or 3, distant, peduncles pubescent; terminal spike male, clavate, 1.5–2.5 cm, with peduncles 4–9 mm; lateral spikes 1 or 2, female, oblong or oblong-cylindric, 2–2.5 × 1–1.4 cm, densely flowered. Female glumes yellow-white, ovate-lanceolate, 5–6 mm, green 1-veined costa excurrent into an awn. Utricles brown-green, longer than glume, ovate, trigonous, 7–8 mm (including beak), pubescent, many veined, apex abruptly contracted into a cylindric beak ca. 3 mm, orifice deeply 2-lobed with long acute teeth. Nutlets black at maturity, tightly enveloped, ovate, 3–4 mm, trigonous with angles constricted at middle, faces concave at base, base with short curved stipe, apex with short curved beak; style base thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Mar–Apr.</description>
  <distribution>Forested slopes, roadsides, streamsides. Anhui, Fujian, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Zhejiang [Japan, Korea].</distribution>
</treatment>

