<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>329.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>brevicuspis</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 277. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>短尖薹草 duan jian tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, stout. Culms 20–55 cm tall, trigonous, rigid, smooth, clothed at base with dark brown sheaths disintegrating into parallel fibers. Leaves surpassing culm, blades broadly linear, 5–10 mm wide, flattish, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts leaflike but much shorter than inflorescence, sheathing. Spikes 4 or 5, distant; terminal spike male, linear, 2.5–4 cm, with peduncle ca. 4 cm; lateral spikes mostly female, sometimes with several male flowers at apex, narrowly cylindric, 3.7–7 × 0.9–1 cm, densely flowered, lowest peduncle 5–7.5 cm, smooth. Female glumes pale or yellow-brown, linear-lanceolate, green 3-veined costa ending at apex. Utricles brownish green, longer than or nearly equaling glume, obliquely patent, ovate or obovate (excluding beak), 6–7 mm (including beak), herbaceous, pubescent above, many veined, contracted at both ends, apex abruptly contracted into a linear beak ca. 3 mm, orifice 2-lobed with sharp teeth. Nutlets black-purple, tightly enveloped, ovate, ca. 2 mm, trigonous with angles constricted at middle, faces concave at base, base curved stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a cylindric beak ca. 1 mm, beak slightly annulate at orifice, rarely beak absent; style base en-larged; stigmas 3. Fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>● Forested slopes, streamsides; 500–700 m. Anhui, Fujian, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangxi, Shaanxi, Taiwan, Zhejiang.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms long; nutlets with beak</statement>
      <determination>329a. var. brevicuspis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms short; nutlets without beak</statement>
      <determination>329b. var. basiflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

