<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>338.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pilosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Scopoli</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Carniol., ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 2: 226. 1772</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>毛缘薹草 mao yuan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long stoloniferous, slender. Culms 30–60 cm tall, compressed trigonous, usually loosely pilose, clothed at base with purple-red bladeless sheaths, sparsely pilose. Leaves shorter than culm, blades broadly linear, 5–8 mm wide, sparsely pilose on veins and margins. Involucral bracts leaflike, usually pilose, shorter than inflorescence, sheathing 2–5 cm. Spikes 3 or 4, distant; terminal spike male, oblong or linear-clavate, 2–3 cm, with long peduncle much overtopping next spike; lateral spikes female, narrowly cylindric, 2–4 cm, loosely 8–12-flowered; peduncles usually smooth, lowest one up to 12 cm. Female glumes purple or ferruginous, ovate or elliptic, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a mucro, apex slightly obtuse. Utricles light green, becoming yellow, longer than glume, ovate or subelliptic, swollen trigonous, 4–5 mm, membranous, glabrous or sparsely pilose, many veined, base contracted into a short stipe, apex abruptly contracted into a long conic beak, beak curved, obliquely truncate, emarginate, orifice purple-red, 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, obovate, obtusely trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May. 2n = 44.</description>
  <distribution>Forests. Heilongjiang, Liaoning [Japan, Korea; Europe].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles and peduncles glabrous</statement>
      <determination>338a. var. pilosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles and peduncles sparsely pilose</statement>
      <determination>338b. var. auriculat a</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

