<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>346.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rhynchophysa</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Meyer</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Fischer &amp; Avé- Lalle mant, Index Sem. Hort. Petrop.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9 (suppl.): 9. 1844</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>大穗薹草 da sui tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>bullata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Schkuhr</species_authority>
    <subspecies_name>laevirostris</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>(Blytt ex Fries) Fries</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>bullata</species_name>
    <variety_name>laevirostris</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Blytt ex Fries</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>laevirostris</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Blytt ex Fries) Andersson.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather thick, stoloniferous. Culms 60–100 cm tall, stout, triquetrous, smooth on lower part, scabrid on upper part, clothed with brown or reddish brown sheaths at base. Leaves longer than culm, blades 8–15 mm wide, flat, slightly stiff, with short and transverse septate nodes, sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than culm, lowermost involucral bract shortly sheathed, upper involucral bracts not sheathed. Spikes 7–11; terminal 3–7 spikes male, rather approximate, narrowly cylindric, 1.5–4.5 cm, sometimes with few female flowers at base, subsessile; remaining spikes female, cylindric, 3–7.5 × 1–1.5 cm, densely many flowered, sometimes with a few male flowers at apex, shortly pedunculate. Female glume brownish or yellowish brown, oblong-lanceolate, ca. 4.2 mm, membranous, costate, upper margins white hyaline, apex acute, muticous. Utricles yellow-green, horizontally patent in maturity, longer than glume, ovoid or broadly ovate, inflated trigonous, 6.5–7 mm, membranous, slightly nitid, glabrous, several veined, base subrounded, shortly stipitate, apex abruptly narrowed to a slightly long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets loosely enveloped in utricle, obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base shortly stipitate; style slender, flexuose, base not thickened; stigmas 3, rather shorter than style. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places in swamps, at riversides, or at lakesides. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Xinjiang [Japan, Korea, Mongolia, Russia; Europe].</distribution>
</treatment>

