<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>347.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>vesicaria</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 979. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>胀囊薹草 zhang nang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous, stolons branched. Culms 30–100 cm tall, ± stiff, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part, with red-brown and bladeless sheaths at base, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves slightly shorter than culm, blades 2–5 mm wide, flat, ± stiff, with transverse septate nodes between veins, sheathed. Involucral bracts leaflike, lowermost shortly sheathed, upper not sheathed. Spikes 4–6, remote; terminal 2 or 3 spikes male, approximate, linear-cylindric, 2–3.5 mm, subsessile; remaining spikes female, oblong or oblong-cylindric, 3–7 × 1–1.5 cm, densely many flowered, shortly pedunculate. Female glumes pale ferruginous or ferruginous, narrowly ovate or ovate-lanceolate, ca. 3.2 mm, membranous, 3-veined, yellow-green between veins, margins white hyaline, apex acuminate and muticous. Utricles yellowish green, obliquely patent, longer than glume, ovate or conic-ovate, inflated trigonous, 6–8 mm, subleathery, slightly nitid, glabrous, several veined, base rounded, shortly stipitate, apex attenuate into a short beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets rather loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, 1.7–2 mm, base stipitate; style slender, usually flexuose, base not thickened; stigmas 3, rather short. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places at riversides, at lakesides, in swamps, or in meadows. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Mongolia, Russia; Europe, North America].</distribution>
  <discussion>This plant is used as forage and for making paper.</discussion>
</treatment>

