<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>349.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>idzuroei</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet &amp; Savatier</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl. Jap.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 583. 1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>马菅 ma jian</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pseudovesicaria</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. Léveillé &amp; Vaniot.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with slender and branched stolons. Culms laxly tufted, 30–60 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, clothed with long sheaths at base. Leaves usually shorter than culm at lower part and longer than culm at upper part, blades 4–9 mm wide, flat, 2 lateral veins distinct, with shortly transverse septate nodes between veins, purple-brown long sheathed at base. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than spike, usually not sheathed. Spikes 4 or 5; terminal 1 or 2 spikes male, linear-cylindric, 2–4 cm, pedunculate; remaining spikes female, oblong, 2–3 × 1–1.2 cm, subdensely many flowered, sessile at upper spikes, shortly pedunculate at lowermost spike. Female glumes dark yellow, lanceolate-ovate, 5–6 mm, membranous, green 3-veined, apex acuminate, mucronate. Utricles yellow-brown, obliquely patent, much longer than glume, oblong-ovate, inflated trigonous, 9–12 mm, thinly leathery, glabrous, several veined, base rounded, shortly stipitate, apex gradually narrowed to a long beak, orifice slightly long 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish brown, rather loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 4 mm, base shortly stipitate; style thickened at lower part, persistent, slightly stiff; stigmas 3, rather short. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Riversides, lakesides, wet places. Fujian, Jiangsu, Zhejiang [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

