<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>351.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pamirensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Zhurn. (St. Peters burg)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 191. 1907</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>帕米尔薹草 pa mi er tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with rather thick stolons. Culms 60–90 cm tall, triquetrous, stout, stiff, smooth on lower part, scabrous on upper part, with red-brown and bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves nearly equaling culm, blades 3–10 mm wide, flat, usually plicate at base, with transverse septate nodes between veins, scabrous on veins and margins. Involucral bracts leaflike, longer than spike, not sheathed or lower involucral bract shortly sheathed. Spikes 4 or 5; terminal 1–3 male, approximate, clavate or narrowly cylindric, 2–4 cm, subsessile; remaining spikes female, rather remote, oblong or shortly cylindric, 2.5–3 × 0.6–1.5 cm, densely many flowered, shortly pedunculate. Female glumes red-brown, lanceolate or narrowly lanceolate, 4.2–5 mm, membranous, costate, apex subacute. Utricles stramineous or dark chestnut-brown, obliquely patent, slightly longer than or nearly equaling glume, oblong-ovate, inflated trigonous, 5–5.5 mm, glabrous, shiny, thinly 5-veined, base rounded, very shortly stipitate, apex gradually narrowed to a short beak, orifice emarginate. Nutlets broadly ovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base shortly stipitate; style slender, base bent; stigmas 3, rather short. Fl. and fr. Jul–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Alpine wetlands, damp alpine grasslands; 2400–3700 m. Gansu, N Sichuan, Xinjiang [Afghanistan, India (Sikkim), Kazakhstan, Russia].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 5–10 mm wide; female spikes 1.2–1.5 cm wide</statement>
      <determination>351a. subsp. pamirensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 3–4 mm wide; female spikes 0. 6–0.8 cm wide</statement>
      <determination>351b. subsp. angustispicata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

