<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>353.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rostrata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Stokes</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Withering, Bot. Arr. Brit. Pl., ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 2: 1059. 1787</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>灰株薹草 hui zhu tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>ampullacea</species_name>
    <species_authority>Goodenough.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with long and slightly stout stolons. Culms loosely tufted, 40–100 cm tall, rather stout, obtusely trigonous, smooth, bladeless sheathed at base, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades gray-green, 2–5 mm wide, flat, ± stiff, with transverse septate nodes between veins, scabrid on margins. Involucral bracts leaflike, lower involucral bracts longer than spike, shortly sheathed or not sheathed, upper involucral bracts not sheathed. Spikes 3–6; terminal 2–4 spikes, rarely only 1 spike, male, approximate, linear-cylindric, 1–3.5 cm, sessile or subsessile; remaining spikes female, lower spikes remote, cylindric, 3–6 × 0.7–0.8 cm, densely many flowered, subsessile or lower spikes shortly pedunculate. Female glumes ferruginous or pale ferruginous, oblong-lanceolate, 3.5–4 mm, membranous, green costate, margins white hyaline, apex acute or obtuse. Utricles yellowish green, slightly longer than or equaling glume, obliquely patent, eventually slightly divergent, ovate or broadly ovate, inflated trigonous, ca. 4 mm, membranous, glabrous, shiny, 4–6-veined abaxially, base subrounded, shortly stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a medium-sized beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets brown, very loosely enveloped, broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base shortly stipitate; style slender, flexuose, base not thickened; stigmas 3, rather short. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Swamps or meadows in high mountain regions; ca. 2400 m. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol [Korea, Mongolia, Russia; Europe, North America].</distribution>
</treatment>

