<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>356.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>riparia</species_name>
    <species_authority>Curtis</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Londin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: t. 60. 1783</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>泽生薹草 ze sheng tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stout. Culms 60–150 cm tall, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part, clothed with brown or reddish brown sheaths at base. Leaves equaling or longer than culm, blades 10–15 mm wide, flat, ± stiff, with distinct and transverse septate nodes between veins, rather long sheathed. Involucral bracts leafy, lowermost involucral bract longer than inflorescence, nearly not sheathed or lower involucral bracts shortly sheathed. Spikes 5–10, lower spikes remote and upper spikes approximate; terminal 3–6 spikes male, oblong-cylindric or cylindric, 2–6 cm, subsessile; remaining spikes female, cylindric, 3–6 × ca. 1 cm, densely many flowered, sometimes with male flowers at top, upper spikes subsessile, lower spikes slightly long pedunculate. Female glumes brown, lanceolate, ca. 6 mm, 3-veined, apical margins hispidulous, apex acuminate, mucronate. Utricles fuscous-green, obliquely patent, nearly equaling glume, elliptic-ovate, obtusely trigonous, 5–6 mm, leathery or slightly corky, glabrous, several veined, base cuneate, apex gradually narrowed to a slightly broad and short beak, orifice slightly divergent and shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets rather loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, slightly concave on 3 sides; style stiff, persistent, base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Damp places at riversides, at lakesides, or in swamps. Xinjiang [Russia (W Siberia); SW Asia (Iran)].</distribution>
</treatment>

