<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>359.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rugulosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Herb. Boissier, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 4: 58. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>粗脉薹草 cu mai tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>riparia</species_name>
    <species_authority>Curtis</species_authority>
    <variety_name>rugulosa</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Kükenthal) Kükenthal</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>smirnovii</species_name>
    <species_authority>V. I. Kreczetowicz.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with rather thick stolons. Culms 50–80 cm tall, obtusely trigonous, smooth on lower part, scabrid on upper part, clothed with red-brown and bladeless sheaths at base, remnant sheaths usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves nearly equaling culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat, stiff, sheathed. Involucral bracts leafy, lowermost involucral bract equaling or slightly longer than inflorescence, upper involucral bracts rather short, shortly sheathed. Spikes 4–6; terminal 2 or 3 spikes male, distance between spikes short, narrowly lanceolate, 1–3.5 cm, nearly sessile; remaining spikes female, remote, cylindric or oblong-cylindric, 2–4 × ca. 1 cm, densely many flowered, laxly flowered at base, with ca. 1 cm peduncle. Female glumes pale ferruginous laterally, ovate, 3.5–4 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acute. Utricles brown-green or brown-yellow, obliquely patent, longer than glume, elliptic or ovate-elliptic, obtusely trigonous, 5–6 mm, corky, glabrous, several veined abaxially, base rounded, apex abruptly contracted into a slightly broad and short beak, orifice half-rounded concave and shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets slightly tightly enveloped, elliptic or ovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, base shortly stipitate; style slightly long, flexuose, persistent, base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>Riversides, grasslands at lakesides, strands. Hebei, Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol [N Japan, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

