<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>361.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>songorica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Karelin &amp; Kirilov</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Imp. Nat uralistes Moscou</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 525. 1842</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>准噶尔薹草 zhun ga er tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with long and rather thick stolons. Culms 30–50 cm tall, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part, clothed with red-brown and bladeless sheaths at base, remnant sheaths usually disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat or slightly plicate, with distinctly transverse septate nodes between veins, sheathed. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence, lowermost involucral bract shortly sheathed, upper involucral bracts not sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4; terminal 1 or 2 spikes male, approximate, narrowly clavate, 1.5–2 cm, nearly sessile; remaining spikes female, remote, cylindric, 2–4 × 0.5–0.6 cm, densely many flowered and laxly flowered at base, shortly pedunculate, lowermost peduncle ca. 1 cm. Female glumes brown laterally, brownish at middle, ovate, ca. 3 mm, 3-veined, apex acuminate. Utricles orange or ferruginous, usually brown flecked, obliquely patent, longer than glume, ovoid or broadly ovoid, biconvex, 3–4 mm, leathery, shiny, thinly several veined abaxially, base rounded, apex abruptly contracted into a slightly broad and short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets elliptic or ovate-elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; style base flexuose, not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Salt grasslands; below 100–3000 m. Xinjiang [Afghanistan, India, NW Mongolia, Russia; SW Asia (Iran)].</distribution>
</treatment>

