<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>362.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>tangiana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Jap. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 656. 1936</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>唐进薹草 tang jin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with rather thick, stiff stolons. Culms 30–40 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, scabrid on upper part, clothed with red-brown and bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves slightly longer than or equaling culm, blades 2–3 mm wide, flat, stiff, scabrous on margins, rather long sheathed. Involucral bracts leafy, lowermost involucral bract longer than inflorescence, upper involucral bracts shorter than inflorescence, nearly not sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4; terminal 1 or 2 spikes male, approximate, narrowly cylindric or lanceolate, 1.2–2.5 cm, sessile; remaining spikes female, remote, cylindric, 2.5–3.5 × 0.5–0.6 cm, densely many flowered, lowermost one shortly pedunculate, upper ones nearly sessile. Female glumes brown-yellow, ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, 3-veined, brownish yellow between veins, apex acuminate, shortly aristate, scabrous on margins of awn. Utricles stramineous, obliquely patent, slightly longer than glume, elliptic or broadly ovate, subplano-convex, slightly inflated, 3.5–4 mm, leathery, glabrous, slightly shiny, indistinctly veined, base subrounded or broadly cuneate, apex abruptly narrowed to a short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed, teeth straight. Nutlets rather loosely enveloped, subobovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, base stipitate; style rather long, base not thickened, slightly recurved; stigmas 3, rather short. Fl. and fr. May–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Damp places in valleys, ditch sides, roadsides; 500–1000 m. Gansu, Hebei, Heilongjiang, Henan, Jilin, Liaoning, Shaanxi, Shanxi.</distribution>
  <discussion>Based on its original description, Carex purpureovaginalis Q. S. Wang (J. Wuhan Bot. Res. 5: 343. 1987, “purplevaginalis”) is very difficult to distinguish from C. tangiana. We have not seen the type specimen and so cannot make a provisional determination here.</discussion>
</treatment>

