<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>368.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pseudophyllocephala</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32: 187. 1994</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “pseudo-phyllocephala ”].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>假头序薹草 jia tou xu tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, without stolons. Culms tufted, 12–15 cm tall, slender, triquetrous, clothed with brown and shortly bladed sheaths at base. Upper leaves longer than culm, lower leaves shorter than culm, blades 2–5 mm wide, flat, scabrous on veins and margins, slightly shortly sheathed, upper and lower sheaths ± overlapping. Involucral bracts leaflike, congregated at top of culm, longer than inflorescence, scabrous on veins of adaxial surface and margins, smooth on abaxial surface, rather shortly sheathed. Spikes 4 or 5, congregated at top of culm; terminal spike male, linear, 1–1.5 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, narrowly oblong, 0.7–1.5 cm, several to 15-flowered, shortly pedunculate. Female glumes brown-yellow, orbicular-ovate, ca. 2 mm, membranous, 1-veined, apex acute, sometimes mucronate. Utricles yellow-green, yellow-brown in maturity, obliquely patent, longer than glume, lanceolate or broadly lanceolate, trigonous, ca. 2.5 mm, membranous, glabrous or sometimes laxly ciliate on margins near beak, abaxially distinctly 2-veined laterally, base cuneate, apex gradually narrowed to a rather short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets brown-yellow, tightly enveloped, lanceolate, ca. 2 mm; style rather short, base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Jul.</description>
  <distribution>● Thickets on mountain slopes, damp places at forest margins. Hunan.</distribution>
</treatment>

