<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>369.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>phyllocephala</species_name>
    <species_authority>T. Koyama</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Geobot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>16: 40. 1955</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>密苞叶薹草 mi bao ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short and slightly thick, ligneous, without stolons. Culms 20–60 cm tall, rather stout, obtusely trigonous, clothed with reddish brown and bladeless sheaths at lower part. Leaves contiguously disposed, longer than culm, blades 8–15 mm wide, ± stiff, revolute on margins with distinctly transverse septate nodes between veins on abaxial surface, slightly long sheathed; sheaths ± overlapping, distinctly ligulate, reddish. Involucral bracts leaflike, congregated at top of culm, longer than inflorescence, rather shortly sheathed. Spikes 6–10, congregated at top of culm; terminal spike male, linear-cylindric, 1–2.5 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, sometimes with few male flowers at apex, narrowly cylindric, 2–3 cm, densely many flowered, pedunculate. Female glumes green at middle, pale laterally, very shortly ferruginous striate, broadly obovate, ca. 1.8 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acute, mucronate. Utricles grass-green, very shortly ferruginous striate, obliquely patent, longer than glume, broadly obovate, trigonous, 2.8–3.5 mm, membranous, densely white hispidulous, distinctly 2-veined laterally, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a rather short beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, sessile; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>Damp places in forests, roadsides, valleys; 500–1000 m. Fujian [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

