<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>371.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>hebecarpa</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Meyer</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg Divers Sav ans</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 223. 1831</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>蔬果薹草 shu guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome stoloniferous. Culms 30–50 cm tall, triquetrous, slender, scabrous on upper part, clothed with reddish brown and bladeless sheaths. Upper leaves longer than culm, blades 2–5 mm wide, flat, scabrous on veins of adaxial surface, rather long sheathed; sheaths often overlapping, laxly pubescent on surface. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence, rather long sheathed, pubescent on outside. Spikes 5 or 6, upper spikes approximate, lower spikes rather remote; terminal spike male, linear, ca. 2 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, narrowly cylindric, 1.5–4 cm, laxly many flowered, lower spikes long pedunculate, upper spikes rather shortly pedunculate; peduncles scabrous. Female glumes pale, shortly ferruginous striate, broadly ovate, 1.8–2 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acute, mucronate. Utricles red-brown, obliquely patent, subdistichous, easily deciduous in maturity, longer than glume, obovate-elliptic, obtusely trigonous, ca. 3 mm, submembranous, densely white hispidulous, distinctly 2-veined laterally, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a medium-sized beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped in utricle, elliptic, trigonous, ca. 2 mm; style short, early deciduous; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. May–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>Damp places in valleys of mountain regions, in forests, or at roadsides. Fujian, Guangdong, Hunan, Taiwan [Bhutan, India, Nepal].</distribution>
</treatment>

