<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>379.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>miyabei</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet var. maopengensis S. W. Su</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Anhui Univ., Nat. Sci. Ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20(3): 107. 1996</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>毛果薹草 mao guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long stoloniferous, rather thick. Culms 30–60 cm tall, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part, with reddish brown and bladeless sheaths at base, sheaths later splitting into reticulate fibers adaxially. Leaves longer than culm, blades 3–5 mm wide, flat, rather stiff, scabrous on margins and adaxial surface. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, not sheathed, sometimes lowermost one shortly sheathed. Spikes 5 or 6; terminal 2–4 spikes male, approximate, linear, 1.5–3 cm, ca. 2 mm thick, usually with 1–3 female flowers; remaining spikes female, distance 4–6 cm between 2 spikes, cylindric, 2–6 cm, 4–5 mm thick, densely many flowered, lax at base of spike, upper spikes shortly pedunculate, lower ones long pedunculate, slightly scabrous. Female glumes dark red-brown laterally, brownish at middle, lanceolate, 3.5–5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, margins white hyaline, apex mucronate or aristate. Utricles obliquely patent, broadly obovate, trigonous, 3–4 mm, membranous, white pubescent, pubescence rather dense on upper part, indistinctly veined, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a rather long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, broadly obovate, trigonous, ca. 2 mm, apex curved mucronate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3, ± long.</description>
  <distribution>● Wet places at roadsides. Anhui.</distribution>
  <discussion>Carex miyabei var. miyabei occurs in Japan and Korea. It has male spikes usually without 1–3 female flowers; upper female spikes nearly sessile; female glumes oblong-ovate, without mucro or muticous at apex; and utricles hispidulous.</discussion>
</treatment>

