<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>381.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>latisquamea</species_name>
    <species_authority>Komarov</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trudy Imp. S.-Peterburgsk. Bot. Sada</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 447. 1901</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>宽鳞薹草 kuan lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>villosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <variety_name>latisquamea</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Komarov) Küken thal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, shortly stoloniferous. Culms laxly tufted, 30–75 cm tall, triquetrous, laxly pubescent, with brown, pubescent, and bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves equaling culm, blades 3–6 mm, flat, with transverse septate nodes between veins, laxly pubescent, lower ones long sheathed. Involucral bracts leafy, lowermost one nearly equaling inflorescence, upper ones shorter than inflorescence, shortly sheathed. Spikes 3 or 4, slightly remote; terminal spike male, narrowly lanceolate or linear, 1–2 cm, shortly pedunculate; lateral spikes female, oblong or oblong-ovate, 1–2.5 cm, slightly densely more than 10-flowered, lower spikes shortly pedunculate, upper one subsessile. Female glumes yellowish brown laterally, green at middle, broadly ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acuminate, mucronate. Utricles green-brown, obliquely patent, longer than glume, ovate, obtusely trigonous, 5–6 mm, subleathery, raised several veined, base broadly cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex gradually narrowed to a short beak, orifice long and recurved 2-toothed. Nutlets slightly tightly enveloped, obovate, trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, apex recurved mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places in lax forests or in meadows. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Liaoning [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East)].</distribution>
</treatment>

