<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>386.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>drymophila</species_name>
    <species_authority>Turczaninow ex Steudel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Pl. Glumac.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 238. 1855</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>野笠薹草 ye li tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long stoloniferous. Culms 60–70(–100) cm tall, obtusely trigonous, rather stout, smooth or scabrous on upper part, clothed with red-brown and bladeless sheaths at base, sheaths split into reticulate fibers on margins. Leaves shorter than culm, blades 4–6(–10) mm wide, flat, glabrous, only pubescent on membranous part of sheaths, or laxly pubescent on abaxial surface, scabrous on margins, rather long sheathed. Involucral bracts leafy, lower 1 or 2 involucral bracts longer than inflorescence, slightly long sheathed, upper involucral bracts usually shorter than inflorescence, shortly sheathed; male spikes with setaceous or scalelike involucral bract at base. Spikes 5–7, lower spikes remote, upper spikes approximate; terminal 2 or 3 spikes male, fasciated or narrowly lanceolate, 2–4 cm, subsessile; remaining spikes female, oblong-cylindric or cylindric, 3–5 cm, slightly laxly many flowered, rather lax at base, lowermost peduncle 6–7 cm, erect or slightly pendulous, upper peduncles rather short. Female glumes pale ferruginous laterally, greenish at middle, narrowly ovate or lanceolate, 4–4.5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, margins white hyaline, apex acuminate or slightly acute, shortly aristate. Utricles olivaceous, obliquely patent, longer than glumes, ovate-orbicular, inflated trigonous, 5–7 mm, herbaceous, distinctly several veined, base subrounded, very shortly stipitate, apex gradually narrowed to a slightly broad and ± long beak, beak brownish hispid on margins, strict and rather long 2-toothed at orifice. Nutlets loosely enveloped, obovate, trigonous, ca. 3 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex mucronate; style base not thickened; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Wet grasslands in forest regions, wet places at lakesides or riversides, in swamps or meadows. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Mongolia, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms 60–70 cm tall; leaf blades 4–6 mm wide, glabrous or only pubescent on membranous part of sheaths; utricle hispid on margins of beak</statement>
      <determination>386a. var. drymophila</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms up to 100 cm tall; leaf blades 5–8(–10) mm wide, usually laxly pubescent on abaxial surface; utricle hispid on upper part and margins of beak</statement>
      <determination>386b. var. abbreviata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

