<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>403.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>cryptocarpa</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Meyer</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg Divers Sava ns</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 226. 1831</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>隐果薹草 yin guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>lyngbyei</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hornemann</species_authority>
    <subspecies_name>cryptocarpa</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>(C. A. Meyer) Hultén</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>lyngbyei</species_name>
    <subspecies_name>prionocarpa</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>(Franchet) Kitagawa</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>prionocarpa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome with stout stolons. Culms 30–120 cm tall, stout, slightly smooth, clothed at base with reddish purple, lustrous, bladeless sheaths. Leaves shorter than culm, blades broadly linear, 5–10 mm wide, flat, margins slightly involute. Involucral bracts leaflike, lower 2 or 3 surpassing inflorescence. Spikes 5–7, remote; upper 2 or 3 spikes male, fusiform or clavate, 6–7 cm; remaining spikes female, usually with male flowers at apex, cylindric, 2–8 × 0.8–1.2 cm, many flowered, with peduncles up to ca. 10 cm, smooth, pendent. Female glumes dark brown-purple, lanceolate or oblong-lanceolate, pale 1-veined costa excurrent into a mucro. Utricles gray-green, becoming light brown, ca. 1/2 as long as glume, ovate, biconvex, ca. 3 mm, slender, 6–8-veined, base shortly stipitate, apex gradually attenuate into a beak, orifice truncate. Nutlets brown, tightly enveloped, elliptic; style base not thickened; stigmas 2.</description>
  <distribution>Marshes, meadows, riversides [Japan, Russia (Far East); North America (Alaska)].</distribution>
  <discussion>No specimens from China have been seen by the present authors. Standley et al. (Fl. N. Amer. 23: 383–384. 2002) suggested that Asian populations are a different species from North American Carex lyngbyei and are appropriately given species status.</discussion>
</treatment>

