<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>409.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>cinerascens</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Herb. Boissier, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 2: 1017. 1902</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>灰化薹草 hui hua tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, long stoloniferous. Culms 25–60 cm tall, tufted, acutely trigonous, smooth, scabrous in lower part of inflorescence, clothed at base with yellow-brown or brown bladeless sheaths disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves shorter than or equaling culm, flat, 2–4 mm wide. Lowest involucral bract leaflike, longer than or equaling inflorescence, sheathless, remaining ones setaceous. Spikes 3–5; upper 1 or 2 spikes male, narrowly cylindric, 2–5 cm; remaining spikes female, occasionally some becoming androgynous and bearing several male flowers at apex, narrowly cylindric, 15–30 × 2–4 mm, densely many flowered, lower spikes with peduncles, upper sessile. Female glumes dark brown or purplish, oblong-lanceolate, ca. 2.5 mm, margins narrowly white hyaline, yellow-green 3-veined costa excurrent into a mucro, apex acute, rarely obtuse. Utricles gray, light green, or yellow-green, longer than glume, ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, ferruginous punctate, obscurely veined, base contracted into a short stipe, apex gradually attenuate into an obscure beak, orifice entire. Nutlets slightly tightly enveloped, obovate-oblong, ca. 1.5 mm; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Lakesides, marshes, wet places. Anhui, Heilongjiang, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol, Shaanxi [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

