<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>415.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rubrobrunnea</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. D. Hooker, Fl. Brit. India</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 710. 1894</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “rubro-brunnea” ].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>点囊薹草 dian nang tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 20–60 cm tall, acutely trigonous, slightly stiff, smooth, slightly scabrous, clothed at base with brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves longer than culm, blades linear, 3–4 mm wide, flat, leathery, margins scabrous. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, longer than inflorescence, rarely shorter, upper ones setaceous, sheathless. Spikes 4–6, approximate, disposed in fastigiate inflorescence; terminal spike male or gynaecandrous, linear-cylindric, 40–55 × 2–4 mm, densely many flowered, with peduncle or sessile; lateral spikes female (occasionally some of these becoming androgynous and bearing several male flowers apically), cylindric, 35–70 × 3–4 mm, densely many flowered, lowest with peduncle 1–1.5 cm, others gradually becoming subsessile to sessile. Female glumes castaneous, lanceolate, margins narrowly white hyaline, yellow-green 3-veined costa excurrent into a mucro, apex acuminate. Utricles brown to olivaceous, slightly shorter than glume, oblong or oblong-lanceolate, plano-convex, 2.5–4 mm, lustrous, densely minutely papillose, nerveless except for 2 marginal costas, apex abruptly contracted into a long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, broadly obovoid, ca. 1.5 mm; stigmas 2, 0.5–2 × as long as utricle. Fl. and fr. (May–)Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Grassland slopes, wet places in forests, rock crevices along valleys or streamsides, moist places; 1000–3900 m. Anhui, Gansu, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hubei, Jiangxi, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Xizang, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Bhutan, India, Myanmar, N Vietnam].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucral bracts shorter than inflorescence</statement>
      <determination>415c. var. brevibracteata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucral bracts longer than inflorescence.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles ca. 2.5 mm; stigmas ca. 1/ 2 length of utricle</statement>
      <determination>415a. var. rubrobrunnea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles 3–4 mm; stigmas ca. 2 × as long as utricle</statement>
      <determination>415b. var. taliensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

