<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>437.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>dimorpholepis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Steudel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Pl. Glumac.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 214. 1855</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>二形鳞薹草 er xing lin tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>cernua</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 35–80 cm tall, acutely trigonous, scabrous above, clothed at base with red-brown to blackish brown bladeless sheaths. Leaves shorter than or equaling culm, blades linear, 4–7 mm wide, flat, margins slightly revolute. Lower 2 involucral bracts leaflike, surpassing inflorescence, upper ones setaceous. Spikes 5 or 6, approximate; terminal spike gynaecandrous, 40–60 mm; lateral spikes female, upper 3 with male flowers at base, cylindric, 45–55 × 5–6 mm, with slender peduncles 1.5–6 cm, pendent. Female glumes pale, sparsely ferruginous flecked, obovate-oblong, 4–4.5 mm, membranous, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous awn ca. 2.2 mm at emarginate or truncate apex. Utricles red-brown, ferruginous flecked, longer than glume, elliptic or elliptic-lanceolate, ca. 3 mm, slightly compressed, densely papillose, base cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice entire; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Moist soil of ditch sides and roadsides; 200–1300 m. Anhui, Gansu, Guangdong, Henan, Hubei, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Liaoning, Shaanxi, Shandong, Sichuan, Zhejiang [India, Japan, Korea, Myanmar, Nepal, Sri Lanka, N Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

