<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>438.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>phacota</species_name>
    <species_authority>Sprengel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 826. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>镜子薹草 jing zi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>shichiseitensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms tufted, 20–75 cm tall, acutely trigonous, clothed at base with yellowish brown or dark yellow-brown sheaths disintegrating into reticulate fibers. Leaves subequaling culm, blades linear, 3–5 mm wide, flat, margins revolute. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, conspicuously surpassing inflorescence, sheathless, upper ones setaceous. Spikes 3–5, approximate; terminal spike male, rarely with a few female flowers at apex, narrowly cylindric, 45–65 × 1.5–2 mm, with peduncle; lateral spikes female, rarely a few male flowers at apex, long cylindric, 2.5–6.5 × 3–4 mm, densely many flow-ered, with slender, slightly scabrous peduncles, lowest one 2–3 cm, pendent. Female glumes pale, ferruginous flecked, oblong, ca. 2 mm (excluding awn), green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous awn at truncate or emarginate apex. Utricles dark brown, longer than glume, broadly ovate or elliptic, biconvex, 2.5–3 × ca. 1.8 mm, densely papillose, nerveless except for 2 costas on edges, broadly convex, apex abruptly contracted into a short beak, orifice entire or emarginate. Nutlets brown, slightly loosely enveloped, suborbicular or broadly ovate, ca. 1.5 mm, densely papillose; style long, base not thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Mar–May.</description>
  <distribution>Moist soil of grasslands, ditches, streambanks, roadsides. Anhui, Fujian, Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Shandong, Sichuan, Taiwan, Yunnan, Zhejiang [India, Indonesia, Japan, Malaysia, Myanmar, Nepal, Sri Lanka, N Thailand, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

