<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>440.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>teinogyna</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ill. Gen. Carex</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 60. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>长柱头薹草 chang zhu tou tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>scabriculmis</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Kükenthal) Ohwi</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>teinogyna</species_name>
    <variety_name>scabriculmis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Kükenthal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 25–60(–90) cm tall, slender, triquetrous, slightly scabrous, clothed with few bladeless sheaths. Leaves shorter than or equaling culms, blades 2.5–3 mm wide, conduplicate at base, canaliculate on midrib surface, flattened at upper part, scabrous on veins and margins, basal sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Involucral bracts shorter than or equaling inflorescence, lower ones leaflike, upper ones setaceous, scabrous on margins, sheathed; sheaths 5–30 mm. Spikes numerous, 1–3 in an involucral bract sheath, androgynous, linear, 1–5 cm, male part shorter than female part, lower spikes sometimes branched, laxly flowered, slender or rather shortly pedunculate. Female glumes brown-yellow or brownish yellow, oblong-ovate, 4–5 mm, membranous, green 3-veined, apex acute, aristate or mucronate, sometimes muticous, hispidulous on margins of awn. Utricles dark brown, shorter than glume, oblong or narrowly elliptic, plano-convex, ca. 4.5 mm, membranous, hispidulous, several veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed to a rather long beak, orifice minutely 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish, tightly enveloped, elliptic, compressed biconvex, ca. 2 mm, sessile; style base rather thickened; stigmas 2, slender, persistent.</description>
  <distribution>Lax forests in valleys, riversides, wet places at ditch sides or on rocks, sands; 500–2000 m. Anhui, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hunan, Jiangxi, Yunnan, Zhejiang [India, Japan, Korea, Myanmar, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

