<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>441.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>bilateralis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Coll. Sci. Imp. Univ. Tokyo</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>30: 380. 1911</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>台湾薹草 tai wan tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>asperinervis</species_name>
    <species_authority>T. Koyama</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>kotoensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hayata</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>subteinogyna</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ohwi.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, without stolons. Culms densely tufted, 40–60 cm tall, triquetrous, scabrous on upper part of angles, clothed with dark brown sheaths at base, rudimentary sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves basal, much shorter than culm, blades 2–3 mm wide, flat, ± stiff, scabrous on upper surface, rather shortly sheathed. Involucral bracts shorter than spike, lower ones shortly leaflike, upper ones setaceous, sheathed, lower sheaths slightly long. Spikes 5–8, 1–3 in an involucral bract sheath, upper spikes contiguous, lower spikes rather spaced, androgynous, narrowly lanceolate, 10–15 mm, male part shorter than female part, female part somewhat laxly flowered; peduncles mostly long and slender, upper peduncles rather short. Female glumes yellow-brown, narrowly oblong, costate, margins white hyaline, apex acute or obtuse, muticous. Utricles brown, suberect, equaling or slightly shorter than glume, elliptic, compressed trigonous, ca. 4 mm, membranous, thinly several veined, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, margins hispidulous, apex gradually narrowed to a medium-sized beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, elliptic, compressed biconvex, ca. 2 mm; style slightly short, base thickened; stigmas 2, rather long, persistent.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests, wet places on mountain slopes; 1800–2000 m. Taiwan.</distribution>
</treatment>

