<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>443.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>henryi</species_name>
    <species_authority>(C. B. Clarke) L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Reipubl. Pop ularis Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 439. 2000</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>亨氏薹草 heng shi tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>longicruris</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nees</species_authority>
    <variety_name>henryi</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>C. B. Clarke</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 295. 1903.</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, ligneous, without stolons. Culms densely tufted, 80–140 cm tall, slightly stout, obtusely trigonous, smooth. Leaves basal and cauline, shorter than culm, blades 3–4 mm wide, conduplicate at base and distally gradually flattened, scabrous on both surfaces and margins, long sheathed; sheaths near base black-brown. Involucral bracts sheathed, lower involucral bract blades leafy, upper blades setaceous; sheaths 0.5–6 cm. Spikes numerous, loosely arranged in a panicle, androgynous, male part shorter than female part, linear-cylindric, 10–25 mm, with few male flowers at apex, loosely with female flowers at lower part, slender and rather long pedunculate. Female glumes brown-yellow, ovate, ca. 2 mm, membranous, green costate, apex acute, muticous. Utricles yellow-green, suberect, longer than glume, elliptic, plano-convex, ca. 3 mm, 5–7-veined abaxially, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed to a medium-sized beak, beak laxly ciliate on margins, ca. 1/3 length of utricle, orifice shortly 2-toothed, usually purple-brown on margins. Nutlets tightly enveloped, elliptic, compressed biconvex, ca. 1.7 mm; style equaling or longer than utricle, base slightly thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Aug–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>● Ditch sides, riversides, paddy field margins, roadsides on mountain slopes, wet places in forests; 500–3000 m. Anhui, Guizhou, Hubei, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Yunnan, Zhejiang.</distribution>
</treatment>

