<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>445.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>gentilis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Philom. Paris, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8, 7: 84. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>亲族薹草 qin zu tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 25–70 cm tall, slender, trigonous, smooth. Leaves shorter than culm, blades (1.5–)2–3(–4.5) mm wide, flat, scabrous on both surfaces and margins, sheathed; sheaths usually split. Involucral bracts sheathed, lower 1 or 2 leaflike, upper blade setaceous, slightly scabrous; sheaths 5–20 mm, membranous part brown, slightly split. Spikes numerous, 3–6 in an involucral bract sheath, lower spikes usually branched, androgynous, male part shorter than female part, male part of terminal spike longer, narrowly oblong, 8–12 mm, female part loosely few flowered. Female glumes brown, broadly ovate or oblong-lanceolate, 1–2 mm, membranous, 1-costate, margins white hyaline and ± erose, apex acute or obtuse, muticous. Utricles reddish brown, suberect, longer than glume, elliptic, plano-convex, 2.5–3(–4) mm, membranous, glabrous, thinly 5–7-veined, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, apex abruptly narrowed to a medium-sized beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish, tightly enveloped, elliptic, plano-convex, ca. 1.5 mm; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 2, short. Fl. and fr. Aug–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>● Forests, ditch sides, riversides, mountain slopes, rock crevices, grasslands; 1300–2200 m. Chongqing, Guizhou, Jiangxi, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Xizang, Yunnan.</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes broadly ovate, ca. 1 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 2–3 mm wide; utricles ca. 2.5 mm</statement>
      <determination>445a. var. gentilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades ca. 4.5 mm wide; utricles ca. 3 mm</statement>
      <determination>445b. var. intermedia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fem ale glumes oblong-lanceolate, 1.5–2 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades ca. 1.5 mm wide; female glumes ca. 1.5 mm; utricles 3–4 mm, beak ca. 1/3 length of utricle</statement>
      <determination>445c. var. macrocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 2–3 mm wide; female glume s ca. 2 mm; utricles ca. 3 mm, beak less than 1/3 length of utricle</statement>
      <determination>445d. var. nakaharae</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

