<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>447.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>brunnea</species_name>
    <species_authority>Thunberg</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Murray, Syst. Veg., ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14, 844. 1784</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>褐果薹草 he guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>brunnea</species_name>
    <variety_name>nakiri</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Ohwi</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>sendaica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <variety_name>nakiri</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Ohwi) Koyama.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, without stolons. Culms densely tufted, slender, 40–70 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, many leaved at base. Leaves longer or shorter than culm, blades 2–3 mm wide, conduplicate proximally, distally gradually flattened, scabrous on both surfaces and margins, sheathed; sheaths short, usually less than 5 cm, splitting at membranous part. Involucral bracts sheathed, lower involucral bracts blades leaflike, upper blades setaceous; sheaths 7–20 mm, brownish green. Spikes few to more than 10, usually 1 or 2 in an involucral bract sheath, not branched, distance between 2 spikes up to more than 10 cm, spikes androgynous, male part much shorter than female part, cylindric, 1.5–3 cm, densely many flowered, pedunculate; peduncles short at upper part, long at lower part. Female glumes yellowish brown, shortly brown striate, ovate, ca. 2.5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acute or obtuse, muticous. Utricles brown, suberect, longer than glume, elliptic or suborbicular, compressed plano-convex, 3–3.5 mm, membranous, thinly 9-veined abaxially, white hispidulous on both surfaces, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex abruptly narrowed to a short beak, beak less than 1 mm, 2-toothed at orifice. Nutlets yellow-brown, tightly enveloped, suborbicular, compressed biconvex, base estipitate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Jun–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>Mountain slopes, forests or among shrubs in valleys, riversides, shady places at roadsides, sunny places at watersides; 200–1800 m. Anhui, Fujian, Gansu, Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Xizang, Yunnan, Zhejiang [India, Japan, Korea, Nepal, Philippines, Vietnam; Australia].</distribution>
</treatment>

