<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>449.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>sendaica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Philom. Paris, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8, 7: 42. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>仙台薹草 xian tai tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slender, stoloniferous. Culms densely tufted, 10–35 cm tall or more, slender, triquetrous, smooth, scabrid near apex. Leaves basal, shorter than or equaling culm, blades 2–3 mm wide, flat or sometimes slightly conduplicate, scabrous on margins, sheathed; sheaths 2–3 cm, usually splitting. Involucral bracts sheathed, lower blades linear, upper blades setaceous; sheaths 5–10 mm, lateral part of sheath membranous, brown. Spikes 3 or 4(–8), single in an involucral bract sheath, space up to 5.5 cm, uppermost 2 ± contiguous, androgynous, terminal spike with male part longer than female part, lateral spikes with female part longer than male part, oblong, 8–15 mm, female part slightly densely few to more than 10-flowered; peduncles thin. Female glumes reddish brown, ovate, 2–2.5 mm, membranous, 3-veined, apex acute, muticous. Utricles reddish brown, suberect, longer than glume, broadly elliptic or broadly ovate, plano-convex, ca. 3 mm, membranous, thinly several veined abaxially, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex abruptly narrowed to a short beak, beak less than 1 mm, hispidulous on margins, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets yellowish, tightly enveloped, suborbicular, compressed plano-convex, ca. 2 mm, base estipitate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 2, exserted part longer than utricle. Fl. and fr. Aug–Oct.</description>
  <distribution>Thickets, grasslands, wet places on mountain slopes, ditch sides in valleys, rock crevices, field banks; 100–1900 m. Guizhou, Henan, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Zhejiang [Japan].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms 10–35 cm tall; spikes 3 or 4, oblong-cylindric</statement>
      <determination>449a. var. sendaica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms more than 35 cm tall; spikes up to 8, shortly cylindric</statement>
      <determination>449b. var. pseudosendaica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

