<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>453.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>omeiensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Tang</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Fan Mem. Inst. Biol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 361. 1932</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>峨眉薹草e mei tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>omeiensis</species_name>
    <variety_name>multifascula</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Q. S. Wang.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather long, ligneous, horizontal. Culms laxly tufted, 40–65 cm tall, triquetrous, smooth, scabrid nearly apex, clothed at base with dark brown and bladeless sheaths. Leaves slightly short, equaling or slightly longer than culm, blades 0.4–1.2 cm wide, flat, ± stiff, smooth on adaxial surface, scabrous on abaxial surface and margins; sheaths 5–10 cm, dark brown, membranous part of sheaths usually splitting to base. Involucral bracts sheathed, lower involucral bract blades leaflike or setaceous, usually shorter than spike, upper bracts bladeless, sheaths 5–7 mm, brownish, white hyaline on margins of mouth. Spikes numerous, 3–8 spikes fascicled in an involucral bract sheath; terminal spike male; remaining spikes female, densely arranged in a raceme near apex, cylindric, 10–20 mm, sparsely few to more than 10-flowered, thinly pedunculate. Female glumes brownish yellow, ovate, ca. 2 mm, membranous, 1-costate. Utricles reddish brown, suberect, longer than glume, elliptic, plano-convex, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, glabrous, 7–9-veined abaxially, base abruptly contracted into a short stipe, apex gradually narrowed into a short beak less than 1 mm, orifice emarginate. Nutlets yellowish brown, tightly enveloped, ovate-orbicular, plano-convex, ca. 1.5 mm, base estipitate; style persistent, base slightly thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. May–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>● Watersides in valleys, roadsides on mountain slopes, wet places in forests; ca. 1800 m. Hubei, NW Hunan, Shaanxi, Sichuan (Emei Shan).</distribution>
</treatment>

