<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>457.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>orbicularinucis</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. K. Dai</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Phytotax. Sin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 183. 1999</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>圆坚果薹草 yuan jian guo tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome slightly elongate. Culms loosely tufted, 35–55 cm tall, medium thick, obtusely trigonous, smooth, several brown and bladeless sheathed at base, sheaths eventually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves sheathed, lower blades shorter than culm, upper blades nearly equaling culm, blades 3–4 mm wide, flat, ± stiff, scabrous on veins and margins; sheaths 3–4 cm. Involucral bracts sheathed or upper 2 or 3 nearly not sheathed, longer than spikes. Spikes 3–5, androgynous, with few male flowers at upper part, densely with many female flowers at lower part, oblong or broadly ovate, 0.8–1.5 cm; lowermost spike with a ca. 7 cm peduncle, upper 2 or 3 spikes almost sessile. Female glumes pallid or pale cinnamon-colored, ovate or narrowly ovate, ca. 3 mm, membranous, green 3-veined, apex acuminate, mucronate or aristate. Utricles yellowish green or stramineous, longer than glume, suberect, suborbicular, plano-convex, ca. 4 mm, membranous, glabrous, 9–13-veined abaxially, base broadly cuneate, apex abruptly contracted into a medium-sized to long beak, orifice shortly 2-toothed. Nutlets stramineous, tightly enveloped, broadly obovate or suborbicular, plano-convex, ca. 2 mm, base broadly cuneate; style persistent, base thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Jun–Sep.</description>
  <distribution>● Thickets on mountain slopes or in ravines, dry places in grasslands, rarely at watersides, in ditches; 1700–1900 m. S Sichuan, C Yunnan (Kunming).</distribution>
</treatment>

