<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>461.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>parva</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nees</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Wight, Contr. Bot. India,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>120. 1834</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>小薹草 xiao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>unifoliata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kükenthal &amp; Handel-Mazzetti</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Kobresia</genus_name>
    <species_name>lolonum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Handel-Mazzetti.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather stout, usually elongate. Culms loosely tufted, 10–35 cm tall, rather soft, often flattened, smooth, with brown bladeless basal sheaths, old sheath not splitting into fibers. Basal leaf 1, cauline leaves shorter than culm, blades flat or involute, 1–1.2 mm wide, smooth. Inflorescence 1-spiked, terminal, androgynous (very rarely completely male); male part many flowered, longer than female part; female part 2–4(–6)-flowered. Female glumes dark brown to brown, caducous, oblong-lanceolate, 5–6.5 mm, 3-veined costa of 2 lowest glumes excurrent into a mucro or a short awn up to 7 mm in length, apex acute to slightly obtuse. Utricles suberect first, reflexed at maturity, lanceolate-rhombic, nearly half globose in transverse section, 6–8 mm (including ca. 1.5 mm spongy base), papery, many veined, apex gradually attenuate into a rather long beak, orifice adaxially obliquely truncate. Nutlet shortly cylindric, trigonous, 3.5–4.5 mm, with stipe ca. 1.5 mm and embraced in spongy base of utricle; rachilla soft, flat, slightly longer than nutlet, not exserted; stigmas 3. Fr. May–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Forest margins, mountain slopes, bogs, wet places along riverbanks; 2300–4400 m. Gansu, Qinghai, Shaanxi, Xizang, Yunnan [Bhutan, India (Sikkim), Nepal; C Asia].</distribution>
</treatment>

