<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>466.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rara</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 284. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>松叶薹草 song ye tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>biwensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>pseudobiwensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Kitagawa</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>rara</species_name>
    <variety_name>biwensis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Franchet) Kükenthal ex Matsumura.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short. Culms densely tufted, 20–30 cm tall, smooth to slightly scabrous above. Leaves shorter to slightly longer than culm, blades 0.5–1 mm wide, flat or involute, smooth or slightly scabrous on upper margins; basal sheaths split into gray-brown fibers. Inflorescence 1-spiked, terminal, androgynous; male part distinct, linear, 4–12 mm, 5–17-flowered; female part oblong to shortly cylindric, 4–10 mm, densely 6–18-flowered. Female glumes brown but diluted on upper margins, oblong-ovate, 1.5–2 mm, 3-veined, apex rounded-obtuse. Utricles horizontally patent at maturity, equaling to slightly longer than glume, broadly ovate to elliptic-ovate, slightly swollen, trigonous, 1.5–2.5 mm, faintly veined or distinctly veined near base, sometimes with rusty spots, base rounded-obtuse, apex gradually attenuate into a short beak, orifice subtruncate. Nutlet tightly enveloped, elliptic to ovate, trigonous, 1–2 mm; style base not thickened, persistent; stigmas 3. Fl. and fr. Apr–May.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, forest margins, banks of mountain streams, shady and wet grassy places; 1000–3300 m. Anhui, Guangdong, Heilongjiang, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Jilin, Liaoning, Sichuan, Xizang, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Bhutan, NE India, Japan, Korea, Nepal].</distribution>
</treatment>

