<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>485.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>nubigena</species_name>
    <species_authority>D. Don ex Tilloch &amp; Taylor</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Philos. Mag. J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>62: 455 . 1823</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>云雾薹草 yun wu tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, indurate. Culms tufted, 10–70 cm tall, trigonous, scabrous above, clothed with brown bladeless sheaths at base. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 1–2 mm wide, flat or plicate, apex acuminate; membranous side of leaf sheaths not transversely wrinkled, with purple-red spots. Lower involucral bracts 1 or 2 leaflike, green, much surpassing inflorescence, upper involucral bracts setaceous. Spicate inflorescence long cylindric, 2.5–50 × 0.7–1 cm, dense at apex, lower ones distant; spikes numerous, androgynous, ovate 5–9 × 4–6 mm, sometimes spikes branched at base. Female glumes pale green, ovate, 2.5–2.8 mm, membranous, green 1-veined, apex acute, awned. Utricles pale green, rarely tinged with red-brown, longer than glume, ovate-lanceolate or oblong-elliptic, plano-convex, 2.5–3.5 × ca. 1 mm, membranous, many veined on both faces, glabrous, base shortly stipitate, margins thickened, without wings, apex gradually narrowed into a long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets pale brown, tightly enveloped, broadly elliptic or suborbicular, plano-convex, ca. 1.2 mm, base shortly stipitate; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Jun–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Streamsides, forest margins and roadsides on slopes, grassy slopes, wet places; (1100–)1300–3700 m. Chongqing, Gansu, Guizhou, Hubei, Ningxia, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Xizang, Yunnan [?Afghanistan, Bhutan, India, Indonesia (Java), Japan, Malaysia, Nepal, ?Pakistan, Philippines, Russia (Kuril Islands), Sri Lanka, Vietnam].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikes 3–5, densely congested w ithout space</statement>
      <determination>485c. subsp. pseudoarenicola</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikes many (more than 10), dispersed, lower one slightly spaced.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles lanceolate-ovate, ca. 3 × 1 mm, light green; spike ca. 5 mm wide</statement>
      <determination>485a. subsp. nubigena</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles broadly lanceolate, tinged with red-brown</statement>
      <determination>485b. subsp. albata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

