<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>498.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>unisexualis</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. B. Clarke</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 316. 1904</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>单性薹 草 dan xing tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>fluviatilis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <variety_name>unisexualis</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(C. B. Clarke) Kükenthal.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome long creeping, slender, clothed with brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Culms (10–)15–50 cm tall, compressed trigonous, with pale brown sheaths at base. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 1–2.5 mm wide, flat or plicate, apex acuminate. Involucral bracts setaceous or glumelike. Plants dioecious (rarely monoecious); female spicate inflorescence cylindric, 2.5–8 × 0.7–1 cm; male inflorescence rather narrow, 5–6 mm wide; spikes 15–30, unisexual, rarely androgynous; female spikes oblong-ovate, 5–8 × ca. 4 mm wide; male spikes oblong, ca. 6 × 2–3 mm. Female glumes pale green, ovate, 2–3 mm, sparsely ferruginous puncticulate, margins white hyaline, green 1-veined costa excurrent into an awn at acute apex. Utricles greenish or pale, ferruginous dotted, longer than glume, ovate, plano-convex, 2–3 × 1–1.5 mm, membranous, many veined on both faces, base subrounded, spongy, shortly stipitate, upper margins serrulate winged, apex gradually narrowed into a scabrous beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets dark brown, loosely enveloped, ovate or elliptic, plano-convex, ca. 1.2 mm, lustrous, base shortly stipitate, apex rounded; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Lakesides, ponds, swamps, grasslands. Anhui, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Japan].</distribution>
</treatment>

