<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>500.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>pseudocuraica</species_name>
    <species_authority>F. Schmidt</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. Saint Pétersbourg, Sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7, 12(2) [Reis. Amur-Land., Bot.]: 67. 1868</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>漂筏 薹草 piao fa tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>chordorrhiza</species_name>
    <species_authority>Ehrhart ex Linnaeus f.</species_authority>
    <variety_name>pseudocuraica</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(F. Schmidt) Trautvetter.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome rather thick, short, with long, trigonous, horizontal, rather thickened stolons. Culms 15–40 cm tall, compressed trigonous, scabrous above, clothed with gray-brown bladed sheaths. Leaves shorter than culm, blades greenish, linear, 1.5–3 mm wide, flat. Involucral bracts glumelike. Inflorescence slightly loose, oblong-cylindric, 1.5–3 cm; spikes 5–10, usually androgynous, rarely unisexual, rarely entirely female, elliptic-ovate, 4–10 mm. Female glumes ferruginous-yellow, glumelike, ovate or elliptic-ovate, 2.5–4 × ca. 1.5 mm, margins white hyaline, apex acute. Utricles pale brown or stramineous, equaling or longer than glume, ovate or elliptic, plano-convex, 2.5–4 mm, membranous, spongy, 6- or 7-veined or more abaxially, rather rarely faintly veined adaxially, base rounded or cuneate, shortly stipitate, upper margins narrowly winged, apex abruptly contracted into a short compressed beak, orifice pale hyaline, obliquely truncate, slightly 2-toothed adaxially. Nutlets slightly loosely enveloped, ovate or elliptic, plano-convex, 1.2–1.7 mm, base shortly stipitate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 2. Fr. Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Swamps, lakesides. Heilongjiang, Jilin, Nei Mongol [Japan, Korea, Russia (Far East, E Siberia)].</distribution>
  <discussion>This species is sometimes placed in its own section, Carex sect. Chordorrhizae (Heuffel) Meinshausen.</discussion>
</treatment>

