<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>504.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>duriuscula</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. A. Meyer</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg Divers Savans</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 214. 1831</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>寸草 cun cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants with slender, long creeping rhizomes and bunches of shoots forming loose tufts. Culms 5–20 cm tall, slender, smooth, clothed at base with gray-brown sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 1–1.5 mm wide, involute, stiff, margins slightly scabrous. Involucral bracts glumelike. Inflorescence ovate or globose, 5–15 × ca. 5 mm; spikes 3–6, androgynous, ovate, dense, 4–6 mm. Female glumes ferruginous-brown, broadly ovate or elliptic, 3–3.2 mm, white hyaline on margins and apex, apex acute or obtuse. Utricles ferruginous or yellow-brown, shorter to slightly longer than glume, ovate, ovate-elliptic, or broadly ovate, plano-convex, 3–4.5 × ca. 2 mm, leathery, slightly lustrous at maturity, many veined on both faces, base subrounded, spongy, thickly stipitate, apex abruptly contracted into a short scabrous beak, orifice white hyaline, obliquely truncate, shallowly cleft abaxially. Nutlets slightly loosely enveloped, suborbicular or broadly elliptic, 1.5–2 × 1.5–1.7 mm; style base thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Apr–Jun.</description>
  <distribution>Grasslands, slopes, wet places or rocky and sandy areas on riverbanks, roadsides, semidry regions, meadows; (below 100–)200–700 m. Gansu, Hebei, Heilongjiang, Henan, Jilin, Liaoning, Nei Mongol, Ningxia, Qinghai, Shaanxi, Shandong, Shanxi, Xinjiang, Xizang [Afghanistan, Kazakhstan, Korea, Kyrgyzstan, Mongolia, New Guinea, Pakistan, Russia (Far East, Siberia), Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan; SW Asia, North America].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades line ar-involute</statement>
      <determination>504a. subsp. duriuscula</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades flat.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes usually longer than or equaling utricles, broadly white hyaline on margins and at apex, apex subobtuse; inflorescence white</statement>
      <determination>504b. subsp. rigescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Female glumes usually shorter than utricles, rarely as long, brown-castaneous, with narrower hyaline margins, apex acute; inflorescence brownish</statement>
      <determination>504c. subsp. stenophylloides</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

