<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>516.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>rochebrunii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet &amp; Savatier</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl. Jap.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 555. 1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “rochebruni” ].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>书带薹草 shu dai tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, stout, indurate. Culms tufted, 25–50 cm tall, slender, trigonous, smooth, clothed at base with brown or pale brown bladeless sheaths disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter or longer than culm, blades linear, 2–3 mm wide, flat, soft; membranous side of leaf sheaths at mouth projected forming a tonguelike appendage or not. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, surpassing inflorescence. Spikes 5–10, gynaecandrous, oblong, 5–15 × 3–4 mm, upper spikes approximate, lower ones remote. Female glumes pale, oblong, 2.5–3 mm, green 3-veined costa excurrent into a scabrous short awn, apex acute. Utricles green or green-yellow, longer than glume, lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, 3–4 mm, conspicuously veined on both faces, many veined abaxially and hardly veined adaxially, or nerveless, base cuneate, shortly stipitate, upper half of margins narrowly scabrous winged, apex gradually attenuate into a long beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets tightly enveloped, plano-convex, 1.5–2 mm, base contracted and shortly stipitate, apex subrounded; style base thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. May–Aug.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, wet grasslands, swamps, grasslands and thickets at high elevations. Anhui, Gansu, Guangxi, Guizhou, Henan, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Shaanxi, Shanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Yunnan, Zhejiang [Bhutan, India, Indonesia, Japan, Nepal, Sri Lanka].</distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles nerveless; membranous side of leaf sheaths at mouth projected forming a tonguelike appendage</statement>
      <determination>516b. subsp. reptans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles conspicuously veined; membranous side of leaf sheaths at mouth not projected forming a tonguelike appendage.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2a.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2a.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles veined on both faces</statement>
      <determination>516a. subsp. rochebrunii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2b.</statement_id>
      <statement>Utricles several veined abaxially, hardly veined adaxially</statement>
      <determination>516c. subsp. remotispicula</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

