<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>521.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>craspedotricha</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nelmes</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1939: 657. 1939</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>缘毛薹草 yuan mao tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>squamata</species_name>
    <species_authority>V. I. Kreczetowicz.</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome short, indurate. Culms tufted, 30–55 cm tall, smooth, soft, clothed at base with pale brown or brown bladeless sheaths usually disintegrating into fibers. Leaves shorter than culm, blades linear, 2–3 mm wide, flat, soft, margins scabrous, apex long acuminate. Lower involucral bracts leaflike, conspicuously surpassing inflorescence, gradually tapering becoming setaceous to glumelike. Spicate inflorescence 10–15 cm, upper spikes approximate, lower ones remote; spikes 8–13, gynaecandrous, sometimes terminal spike all female, broadly ovate or ovate-orbicular, 5–10 × 3–8 mm. Female glumes pale green, narrowly ovate to elliptic, 1.8–2.5 mm, 1-veined at middle. Utricles longer than glume, elliptic or ovate, compressed, 3–3.5 × 1.2–1.5 mm, spongy, distinctly several veined on both faces, upper margins narrowly serrulate winged, apex abruptly contracted into a beak, orifice 2-toothed. Nutlets loosely enveloped, oblong to oblong-ovate, base contracted to shortly stipitate, apex subrounded; style base thickened; stigmas 2. Fl. and fr. Apr.</description>
  <distribution>Wet places, moist grasslands; ca. 300 m. Fujian, Guangdong, Henan, Hunan, Jiangxi, Zhejiang [N Thailand].</distribution>
</treatment>

