<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>satsumensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet &amp; Savatier</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl. Jap.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 558. 1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[ “satzumensis” ].</etymology>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>砂地薹草 sha di tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>nikoensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Franchet &amp; Savatier</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>satsumensis</species_name>
    <variety_name>longiculma</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Hayata</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>C.</genus_name>
    <species_name>satsumensis</species_name>
    <variety_name>nakaii</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Hayata.</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome elongate and creeping. Culms loosely tufted, triangular, 7–20 × ca. 0.15 cm, glabrous, striate. Leaves shorter or longer than culms, flat, 1.5–7 mm wide, slightly stiff, glabrous; basal leaf sheaths blackish brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts linear, shorter than inflorescence, without sheaths. Inflorescence spicate, terminal, oblong-cylindric, 3–8 × 1–1.7 cm. Spikes numerous, androgynous, dense and patent, oblong, arising from cladoprophylls with a developed female flower inside, several basal ones sometimes branched; male part of spikelet tiny, 2–3 mm, with 4 or 5 flowers; female part with numerous and dense flowers; male glumes pale yellow or pale brown, lanceolate, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, apex acuminate; female glumes pale yellow or pale brown laterally, ovate, 2–2.5 mm, membranous, with 1 midrib, margins hyaline, apex acute. Utricles pale yellow-brown at maturity, patent, slightly longer than glumes, oblong-lanceolate, bluntly trigonous, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, with 2 raised lateral veins and several fine veins abaxially, nerveless and paler adaxially, base contracted abruptly into a short stipe, apex attenuate into a long beak, orifice obliquely truncate. Nutlet pale yellow at maturity, oblong, bluntly trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base attenuate, apex not apiculate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Sandy places. Taiwan [Japan, Philippines, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

