<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>3.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>yulungshanensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>P. C. Li</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Bot. Yunnan.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 138. 1990</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>玉龙薹草 yu long tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants perennial. Culms densely tufted, up to 50 cm, trigonous, tenuous, glabrous. Leaves shorter than culms, flat or margins involute, 1–2 mm wide, basal persistent leaf sheaths dark brown. Involucral bracts leafy, shorter than inflorescence, long sheathed. Spikes 5 or 6, bisexual, androgynous, single, distant, linear-cylindric, 30–40 × 3–4 mm, terminal one with 1(or 2) branches, male part much longer than female part, branched spikes arising from cladoprophylls with a developed female flower inside; male part of lateral spikes much shorter and with only few flowers, female part with dense numerous flowers; peduncles of spikes tenuous, lowest one up to 20 cm, upper ones shorter; male glumes purplish brown, oblong-lanceolate, 4–4.5 mm, membranous, apex acuminate; female glumes purplish brown laterally, green at middle, oblong, 3.5–4 mm, papery, 3-veined, scabrid on veins, margins narrowly hyaline, apex rounded, apiculate. Utricles yellowish green, obovate-lanceolate, compressed trigonous, 3.5–4 mm, papery, pubescent, with 2 raised lateral veins and no fine veins abaxially, base attenuate into a short stipe, apex contracted into a short excurved beak, orifice truncate. Nutlet obovate-oblong, 2.2–2.5 mm, sessile, apex not apiculate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3. Rachilla ca. 0.3 mm, flat.</description>
  <distribution>● Alpine meadows and scree; 3900–4300 m. NW Yunnan (Lijiang).</distribution>
</treatment>

