<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>6.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>myosurus</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nees</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Wight, Contr. Bot. India,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>122. 1834</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>鼠尾薹草 shu wei tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>myosurus</species_name>
    <subspecies_name>spiculata</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>Boott.</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody. Culms tufted, robust, 80–120 × ca. 0.3 cm, trigonous, scabrid, leafy below middle. Leaves longer than culms, flat, 5–7 mm wide, glabrous abaxially, scabrid adaxially; basal persistent leaf sheaths dark brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence, long sheathed. Panicle compound, 20–30 cm, 3–6-branched; inflorescence branches racemose, single, 5–8 cm, 2–4-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 3–11 cm; inflorescence axes triquetrous, scabrid; bractlets glumelike. Spikes single, bisexual and androgynous, cylindric, 20–60 × 3.5–4.5 mm; male part of spike 1/4–1/2 length of or very rarely equaling female part; female part with dense and numerous flowers; male glumes pale green, oblong-lanceolate, 3.5–4 mm, membranous; female glumes green or pale green at middle and pale brown laterally, oblong, 2.5–3 mm, papery, with 1 scabrid midrib, upper margin hyaline, apex acuminate, shortly awned. Utricles pale green, longer than glumes, obovate-lanceolate, trigonous, 4–4.5 mm, papery, with several fine veins, glabrous or lateral keels hairy, base attenuate, subsessile, apex shortly beaked, beak 1/5–1/4 length of utricle, orifice minutely 2-toothed. Nutlet dark brown at maturity, closely enclosed in utricle, elliptic, trigonous, base shortly stipitate, apex nearly not apiculate; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Evergreen forests and forest margins; 1200–2000 m. SE Xizang, NW Yunnan [India, Myanmar, Nepal, Vietnam].</distribution>
</treatment>

