<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>8.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <species_name>composita</species_name>
    <species_authority>Boott</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ill. Gen. Carex</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 3. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <species_name>复序薹草 fu xu tai cao</species_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizome woody. Culms tufted, 40–60 × 0.15–0.2 cm, trigonous, smooth. Leaves basal and cauline, flat, 2–3 mm wide, glabrous abaxially, prominently scabrid adaxially; basal persistent leaf sheaths pale brown, fibriform. Involucral bracts leafy, longer than inflorescence, long sheathed. Panicle simple, 20–30 cm, 2–4-branched; inflorescence branches racemose, single, 5–8 cm, 3–8-spiked; peduncles of inflorescence branches tenuous, 5–8 cm, usually not exserted from sheaths; inflorescence axes loosely hairy on edges; bractlets glumelike. Spikes bisexual and androgynous, cylindric, 2–6 cm; male part of spike usually ca. 1/2 length of or rarely equaling female part; female part with many dense flowers; male glumes brown or brown laterally and pale green at middle, lanceolate, 3–3.5 mm, membranous, margins narrowly hyaline, apex apiculate; female glumes yellowish green at middle and reddish brown or purplish brown laterally, oblong-lanceolate, 2.5–3 mm, membranous, loosely pubescent, 3-veined, margins narrowly hyaline, apex acuminate, shortly awned. Utricles pale green, obovate or ovate-globose, flatly trigonous, slightly inflated, 3–3.5 mm, papery, with several fine veins, upper part with brown spots and loosely pubescent, base subsessile, apex shortly beaked, orifice minutely 2-toothed. Nutlet brown at maturity, loosely enclosed in utricle, ovate to triangular-ovate, trigonous, ca. 1.5 mm, base shortly stipitate, apex with contorted apiculus; style base slightly thickened; stigmas 3.</description>
  <distribution>Forests, grasslands; 1300–2500 m. Guizhou, Yunnan [Bhutan, India].</distribution>
</treatment>

